<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Business on Ian Nelson</title>
    <link>https://bloghugo.iannelson.uk/categories/business/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Business on Ian Nelson</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.146.6</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 21 Apr 2025 22:21:59 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://bloghugo.iannelson.uk/categories/business/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>In Search of My Next Challenge</title>
      <link>https://bloghugo.iannelson.uk/in-search-of-my-next-challenge/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jan 2023 13:41:19 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bloghugo.iannelson.uk/in-search-of-my-next-challenge/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Folks, this is your lucky day — Ian Nelson is back on the market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After an unprecedented &lt;em&gt;five years&lt;/em&gt; working the same gig, I will be available for shiny new contract roles from February 2023 &lt;em&gt;(edit: now April 2023, thanks to a short extension)&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://files.iannelson.uk/iannelson.pdf&#34;&gt;Download my CV here&lt;/a&gt;. Email me at &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:ian@iannelson.uk&#34;&gt;ian@iannelson.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-ive-been-doing-recently.wp-block-heading&#34;&gt;What I’ve Been Doing Recently&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since March 2018 I’ve been a Technical Lead for the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nhs.uk/nhs-app/&#34;&gt;NHS App&lt;/a&gt;, an England-wide way to access a range of NHS services via smartphone, tablet, and desktop web browser. It has been an amazing project to be a part of, and I’ve loved working in an open, collaborative, and agile delivery environment alongside a bunch of clever people from NHS Digital, Kainos, and BJSS.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Star Of The Week</title>
      <link>https://bloghugo.iannelson.uk/star-of-the-week/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 May 2014 20:30:11 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bloghugo.iannelson.uk/star-of-the-week/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As a lowly &lt;em&gt;sellsword&lt;/em&gt; amongst the ensemble cast that make up the incestuous York/Leeds IT scene, I am not usually one to be influenced by the promise of titles and honours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Time was, long ago, in my first graduate job, that I yearned for a promotion from “Solution Developer” to “Development Specialist”. Now I give little consideration to what I’m called, and sell my services on the basis of what I can &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt;, and the value I can bring to a project and an organisation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Available Again For Contract Work</title>
      <link>https://bloghugo.iannelson.uk/available-again-for-contract-work/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Mar 2012 08:03:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bloghugo.iannelson.uk/available-again-for-contract-work/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;are-you-plagued-by-bad-code-smells-are-you-plagued-by-bad-code-smells&#34;&gt;Are you plagued by bad code smells? {#are-you-plagued-by-bad-code-smells}&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;troubled-by-slow-running-database-queries-and-etl-routines-troubled-by-slow-running-database-queries-and-etl-routines&#34;&gt;Troubled by slow-running database queries and ETL routines? {#troubled-by-slow-running-database-queries-and-etl-routines}&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;in-need-of-some-scalable-and-maintainable-enterprise-integration-solutions-in-need-of-some-scalable-and-maintainable-enterprise-integration-solutions&#34;&gt;In need of some scalable and maintainable enterprise integration solutions? {#in-need-of-some-scalable-and-maintainable-enterprise-integration-solutions}&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On The Market Again</title>
      <link>https://bloghugo.iannelson.uk/on-the-market-again/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Apr 2010 08:04:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bloghugo.iannelson.uk/on-the-market-again/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This blog post comes to you live from a Starbucks in the north of England.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yesterday I wrapped up another eight months’ stint contracting at my old haunt &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.marshalls.com/&#34;&gt;Marshalls Plc&lt;/a&gt;. It’s been a genuinely interesting gig, working on two distinct greenfield projects using bang up to date technologies including .NET 4.0 and MVC2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it hasn’t just been a benefit for my CV, I think Marshalls might have got a little something out of the arrangement too, as Marshalls’ Development Manager Sion Harrison commented yesterday:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ian Nelson, MCPD</title>
      <link>https://bloghugo.iannelson.uk/ian-nelson-mcpd/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 May 2009 11:05:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bloghugo.iannelson.uk/ian-nelson-mcpd/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Well, for the record, I passed MS exam 70-553 yesterday on my second attempt, which makes me a Microsoft Certified Professional Developer – Enterprise Application Developer:&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I also acquired a few new MCTS certifications as a happy by-product:&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My full transcript, including “legacy” certifications, is &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.iannelson.uk/content/files/MS_Learning_Transcript.pdf&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New Office Photos</title>
      <link>https://bloghugo.iannelson.uk/new-office-photos/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 May 2009 07:05:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bloghugo.iannelson.uk/new-office-photos/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.iannelson.uk/new-office-plan/&#34;&gt;promised you some photos of my new office a while back&lt;/a&gt;, didn’t I? OK, here you go…&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;The Desk&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;The Computer&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;One of These Books Is Not Like The Others&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;Bits n Bobs&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;In Gnasher We Trust&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Seeking Kindred Spirits</title>
      <link>https://bloghugo.iannelson.uk/seeking-kindred-spirits/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Apr 2009 14:04:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bloghugo.iannelson.uk/seeking-kindred-spirits/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m coming round to the realization that my hugely enjoyable first contract at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ventura.co.uk&#34;&gt;Ventura&lt;/a&gt; last summer might have been something of an anomaly. That project was decidedly agile, test-driven, and used a bunch of modern technologies including Monorail, ExtJS, Subversion, NUnit and NHibernate. The requirements were well-defined, and the team was highly effective, with a pragmatic project management team who kept the development team free from bureaucratic processes, leaving us able to get on with delivering some cracking software in double-quick time.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Failed MCP Exam 70-553 :(</title>
      <link>https://bloghugo.iannelson.uk/failed-mcp-exam-70-553/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Apr 2009 13:04:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bloghugo.iannelson.uk/failed-mcp-exam-70-553/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My current primary client has an annoying habit of closing for random days and half-days, including last Thursday afternoon. I decided to try to make the most of this time off, by taking &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.microsoft.com/learning/en/us/exams/70-553.mspx&#34;&gt;Microsoft exam 70-553&lt;/a&gt;, which has the snappy title “&lt;em&gt;UPGRADE: MCSD Microsoft .NET Skills to MCPD Enterprise Application Developer by Using the Microsoft .NET Framework: Part 1&lt;/em&gt;”. I’ve already passed the second part of the upgrade process (70-554), so passing this exam would give me no fewer than four new certifications, including the prestigious MCPD Enterprise Application Developer.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Zero Interest Bug</title>
      <link>https://bloghugo.iannelson.uk/zero-interest-bug/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Dec 2008 12:12:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bloghugo.iannelson.uk/zero-interest-bug/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I started my career in professional software development a decade or so ago by testing and fixing banking code that had fallen victim to the millennium bug.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Could the prospect of zero percent interest rates create a similar boom in demand for software developers?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.contractoruk.com/004128.html&#34;&gt;Contractor UK&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interest rates have plummeted from 5% to 2% since early October and are heading lower. Some analysts say 0% is not out of the question.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>12 Reasons Why I Love Unit Tests</title>
      <link>https://bloghugo.iannelson.uk/12-reasons-why-i-love-unit-tests/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2008 22:11:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bloghugo.iannelson.uk/12-reasons-why-i-love-unit-tests/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On my continuing journey through this thrilling world of professional software development, I frequently encounter teams who hold no truck with this crazy new-fangled concept of unit testing. Heck, truth be told, I sometimes come across teams who don’t use &lt;em&gt;source control&lt;/em&gt;, but that’s by the bye.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In these situations, I try my best to lead by example, continuing to practise TDD on any new code that I cut, and insisting on covering with unit tests any pre-existing code which I have to modify. Sooner or later, this prompts someone to ask why I am doing this (often insinuating that I am wasting my time, and by implication the client’s money). At that point, flustered, I invariably struggle to remember or adequately articulate the many and various ways in which unit testing makes me a better developer. So, consider this blog post a personal aide-mémoire to help me the next time this occurs (as well as being a homage to &lt;a href=&#34;http://uk.youtube.com/watch?v=DW1AHrTNBao&#34;&gt;Jake Shillingford’s second-best song&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Going For It</title>
      <link>https://bloghugo.iannelson.uk/going-for-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jan 2008 12:01:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bloghugo.iannelson.uk/going-for-it/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve never been a fan of those &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.allposters.com/-st/Motivational-Posters_c12920_p6_.htm&#34;&gt;motivational posters&lt;/a&gt; that you see on office walls (usually in sales or marketing departments) that attempt to depict a word like “Opportunity” or “Teamwork” with a single image, usual of some nature scene or a lone individual rising above the odds to achieve a difficult goal. To my mind they always look a bit facile, glib and superficial. “Destiny” equates to a holiday villa on the Maldives?  “Integrity” is a Lion? “Success” appears to involve hang-gliding off towards the ocean in an action which brings to mind Reginald Perrin?! I demand more thought and more words from my motivational office decorations!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ian Nelson, MCSD.Net</title>
      <link>https://bloghugo.iannelson.uk/ian-nelson-mcsd-net/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Feb 2007 16:02:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bloghugo.iannelson.uk/ian-nelson-mcsd-net/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am now a Microsoft Certified Solution Developer in .NET 1.x technologies. This is a qualification that I’ve been working towards on and (more often than not) off for the past four years or so. It’s not really the case that the exams were super-hard, just that it took occasional motivation to get round to taking them!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, was it worth it?  Did I learn anything en route?  Did the exams boost my employability?  Would I be more inclined to employ someone with an MCSD than an applicant without?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>I’m an MCAD!</title>
      <link>https://bloghugo.iannelson.uk/im-an-mcad/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Nov 2004 13:11:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bloghugo.iannelson.uk/im-an-mcad/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Woohoo!  I just passed &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.microsoft.com/learning/exams/70-320.asp&#34;&gt;MS exam 70-320&lt;/a&gt; with a score of 936, and am now a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.microsoft.com/learning/mcp/mcad/default.asp&#34;&gt;Microsoft Certified Application Developer&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
