<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Hugo on Ian Nelson</title>
    <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/tags/hugo/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Hugo on Ian Nelson</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.146.6</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 10 May 2025 22:44:33 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://blog.iannelson.uk/tags/hugo/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>From WordPress to Hugo: A Return to Simpler Times</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/hugo/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 May 2025 22:44:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/hugo/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img loading=&#34;lazy&#34; src=&#34;https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2025/05/Kenzie.png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know, I know, you&amp;rsquo;ve &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.iannelson.uk/back-and-trying-a-ghost-in-the-cloud/&#34;&gt;heard&lt;/a&gt; all this &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.iannelson.uk/here-we-go-again&#34;&gt;before&lt;/a&gt;. Once again Ian is migrating his blog from one platform to another. And yes, it&amp;rsquo;s true that I have spent more of my life converting my blog posts between different platforms and markup languages than I ever have actually writing the damn blog posts in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a certain pleasing symmetry to it. I began my blogging life in the late 1990s with nothing more than some hand-rolled HTML, a text editor, and a dial-up connection. Over the years I have moved my content over to various platforms: .Text, Community Server, WordPress (twice!), GraffitiCMS, Ghost, and now I find myself almost back where I began.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2025/05/Kenzie.png"></p>
<p>I know, I know, you&rsquo;ve <a href="https://blog.iannelson.uk/back-and-trying-a-ghost-in-the-cloud/">heard</a> all this <a href="https://blog.iannelson.uk/here-we-go-again">before</a>. Once again Ian is migrating his blog from one platform to another. And yes, it&rsquo;s true that I have spent more of my life converting my blog posts between different platforms and markup languages than I ever have actually writing the damn blog posts in the first place.</p>
<p>There&rsquo;s a certain pleasing symmetry to it. I began my blogging life in the late 1990s with nothing more than some hand-rolled HTML, a text editor, and a dial-up connection. Over the years I have moved my content over to various platforms: .Text, Community Server, WordPress (twice!), GraffitiCMS, Ghost, and now I find myself almost back where I began.</p>
<p>Not with hand-coded HTML, no, but with something close: <a href="https://gohugo.io/">Hugo</a>, the static site generator. A modern tool with old-world sensibilities. Fast, minimal, fiercely text-based. The kind of thing that makes you feel rather chuffed with yourself for avoiding a CMS and database.</p>
<h2 id="the-nudge">The Nudge</h2>
<p>This time around the change wasn&rsquo;t purely for the fun of trying out a new platform, and it wasn&rsquo;t purely nostalgic. Like many tech migrations, it has been prompted by a small but decisive shift in nonfunctional requirements. I have recently closed my limited company after 17 years, and with that closure I lost my Microsoft Partner benefits, which had included $100/month in Azure credits. That, in turn, meant that I could no longer justify the modest but non-zero cost of keeping a Linux VM running 24/7 just to serve up WordPress.</p>
<p>And truth be told, I don&rsquo;t miss it. Keeping a server and WordPress patched felt increasingly out of proportion to the task of publishing the occasional blog post. In general I find that as I hurtle towards my fifties I have a new-found desire for simplicity in my life, and seek to reduce the complexity of my <a href="https://amzn.to/4ddpW5A">Algorithms To Live By</a>.</p>
<p>So I shut it all down.</p>
<h2 id="simpler-times-static-pages">Simpler Times, Static Pages</h2>
<p>I now generate my blog using Hugo, deployed automatically via <a href="https://github.com/features/actions">GitHub Actions</a> to an <a href="https://azure.microsoft.com/en-us/products/app-service/static">Azure Static Web App</a> (on the free tier, naturally). The site regenerates in a blink, uploads itself automatically on every commit, and serves HTML with a kind of quiet efficiency that makes you wonder why you ever needed a MySQL database in the first place.</p>
<p>All my content lives in Markdown. No block editors, no HTML, no custom CSS. Just words and headings and the occasional image. Oh alright, and I have used a couple of Hugo shortcodes for embedding Youtube videos and <a href="https://gist.github.com">Gists</a>. It&rsquo;s all versioned in GitHub, and I write my posts in VSCode, just as nature intended.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2025/05/VSCode.png"></p>
<p>The migration itself wasn&rsquo;t too painful — helped hugely by this <a href="https://github.com/SchumacherFM/wordpress-to-hugo-exporter">WordPress to Hugo Exporter</a>, followed by a bunch of regex-driven find and replace, and some bespoke tidying (which was actually quite soothing). I&rsquo;ve now got a lean set of posts going back years, shorn of legacy cruft and published with a feather-light footprint.</p>
<h2 id="the-theme-and-the-mood">The Theme and the Mood</h2>
<p>I&rsquo;m using the <a href="https://github.com/adityatelange/hugo-PaperMod">PaperMod</a> theme, which strikes a good balance between clarity and flexibility. I haven&rsquo;t done much in the way of customisation — nor do I particularly want to. That&rsquo;s kind of the point. Simplifying my life. The whole exercise is about reducing friction: to be able to write, publish, and think out loud without needing a ten-step deployment pipeline, a detour into CSS (not my strong suit), or being beholden to whatever WordPress was doing to my words.</p>
<h2 id="but-will-it-stick">But Will It Stick?</h2>
<p>The real question, of course, is whether this move to yet another platform will rekindle my blogging habit. I hope so. There&rsquo;s something appealing about the quiet permanence of a static site: no dashboards, no &ldquo;distraction layer&rdquo;, just me and my words. I&rsquo;m also at a point in my life where my kids need less of my time, and I&rsquo;ve amassed quite a few war stories from life in the world of enterprise software development which I feel able to share.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve come full circle, but this time the tools are better, and the reasons clearer. If you&rsquo;re thinking of simplifying your online life, or just fancy a fresh start for your blog, I&rsquo;d recommended giving Hugo a look.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
