<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>London on Ian Nelson</title>
    <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/tags/london/</link>
    <description>Recent content in London on Ian Nelson</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.146.6</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 04 May 2025 22:01:07 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://blog.iannelson.uk/tags/london/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>London, I Apologise: An Unexpected Romance with the Capital</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/london-i-apologise/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Apr 2025 22:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/london-i-apologise/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For most of my adult life, in a way typical of those of us from the North, I have disdained London.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Too big. Too busy. Too smug. Too&amp;hellip; &lt;em&gt;London&lt;/em&gt;. I’ve long maintained that its gravitational pull distorts the rest of the country, and that one’s quality of life improves in direct proportion to one’s distance from Zone 1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yet — I am beginning to suspect that, deep down, behind my carefully-curated facade, I really rather like it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>For most of my adult life, in a way typical of those of us from the North, I have disdained London.</p>
<p>Too big. Too busy. Too smug. Too&hellip; <em>London</em>. I’ve long maintained that its gravitational pull distorts the rest of the country, and that one’s quality of life improves in direct proportion to one’s distance from Zone 1.</p>
<p>And yet — I am beginning to suspect that, deep down, behind my carefully-curated facade, I really rather like it.</p>
<p>It started innocently enough: a team away day, one of those softly-mandated pilgrimages to headquarters. The sort of day filled with icebreakers (Lord help me),  and colleagues sketching their superhero alter-egos (naturally). But something about it all — the spring sunshine, the civility of strangers answering my dumb questions on the tube, the sheer <em>pleasantness</em> of the whole affair — began to crack my cynicism.</p>
<p>The train journey down there was full but tolerable. I even forgave the freeze-dried coffee sachet (£2.50, thanks LNER) and found unexpected delight in the rhythm of Audible piped through noise-cancelling headphones. I listened to Tony Blair musing on technocracy and health reform. The irony was not lost on me.</p>
<p>We gathered in a sleek office somewhere in Canary Wharf and talked about six-week software cycles and data integration. It should have been excruciating. But it wasn’t. It was&hellip; <em>fine</em>. I met a bright twenty-something who knew his stuff and didn’t make me feel ancient. I had a mini sushi box that I dearly wished had been a maxi. I bonded over high-level architecture diagrams and event-driven dreams.</p>
<p>Later, in the pub (where I eked out two £7.85 pints), I traded gossip and shots with colleagues I had previously only seen in pixelated form. At some point, without quite noticing, I found myself thinking: this is nice.</p>
<p>Two hours later, back on the train with a £7.49 Cornish pasty and aching legs, I declared it aloud: <em>I have decided to like London now.</em></p>
<p>It’s only two hours from Selby. The Elizabeth Line exists. The people — heaven help me — are making an effort. Even the pasty wasn’t terrible.</p>
<p>And so, London, I offer you this: a retraction. Not quite an apology I suppose, and certainly not a love letter. But a grudging acknowledgment that I’ve changed my mind. You’re alright. Let’s not get carried away.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p><em>“Even a leopard can change its spots,” said Jocelyn when I told her. Quite right. And this particular leopard now travels with paracetamol in his rucksack, and periodically stretches in train aisles.</em></p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
