<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Goodreads on Ian Nelson</title>
    <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/tags/goodreads/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Goodreads on Ian Nelson</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.146.6</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 03 May 2025 22:42:55 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://blog.iannelson.uk/tags/goodreads/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>I&#39;m on Goodreads Now</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/im-on-goodreads-now/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 May 2025 15:15:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/im-on-goodreads-now/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Since 2018 I&amp;rsquo;ve been reading far more than I used to. Partly that&amp;rsquo;s because my kids have grown older and don&amp;rsquo;t need quite as much of my time (though they still seem to need quite a lot of money). But it&amp;rsquo;s also thanks to Audible. I&amp;rsquo;ve been listening to audiobooks while I walk the dog, potter about the house, and commute — effectively turning previously &amp;ldquo;wasted&amp;rdquo; time into surprisingly rich reading hours.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Since 2018 I&rsquo;ve been reading far more than I used to. Partly that&rsquo;s because my kids have grown older and don&rsquo;t need quite as much of my time (though they still seem to need quite a lot of money). But it&rsquo;s also thanks to Audible. I&rsquo;ve been listening to audiobooks while I walk the dog, potter about the house, and commute — effectively turning previously &ldquo;wasted&rdquo; time into surprisingly rich reading hours.</p>
<p>Each year, I write a blog post rounding up my favourite reads — <a href="https://blog.iannelson.uk/series/books-of-the-year/">you can find that series here</a>. These have become some of my most popular posts, suggesting that quite a few of you are also on the hunt for good books — or at least enjoy mildly judgmental end-of-year lists.</p>
<p>This year, I’ve started using <a href="https://www.goodreads.com">Goodreads</a> to track what I’m reading (or listening to) throughout the year. If you’ve enjoyed my annual roundups, you might like to follow me there. I’m not one for long reviews, but I do keep it updated, and you can see what I’m currently enjoying, abandoning, or pretending to have finished.</p>
<p>Yes, Goodreads is owned by Amazon, which I know some people aren’t wild about. Fair enough. It’s not perfect, but it’s a decent tool for keeping track of books, and I’m finding it quite useful so far.</p>
<p>Books I&rsquo;ve enjoyed so far in 2025 include:</p>
<ul>
<li><em>Source Code</em> by Bill Gates</li>
<li><em>The Anxious Generation</em> by Jonathan Haidt</li>
<li><em>Money</em> by David McWilliams</li>
<li><em>How Big Things Get Done</em> by Bent Flyvbjerg</li>
<li><em>The Staff Engineer’s Path</em> by Tanya Reilly</li>
<li><em>Lessons</em> by Ian McEwan</li>
<li><em>The Secret History</em> by Donna Tartt</li>
<li><em>Mania</em> by Lionel Shriver</li>
<li><em>On Leadership</em> by Tony Blair</li>
</ul>
<p>If any of those appeal — or if you’re simply curious about what I’m reading when I’m not wrangling distributed systems or Lego bricks — you can follow me here: <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/user/show/119445213-ian-nelson">https://www.goodreads.com/user/show/119445213-ian-nelson</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
