<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Conferences on Ian Nelson</title>
    <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/tags/conferences/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Conferences on Ian Nelson</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.146.6</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 04 May 2025 20:46:51 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://blog.iannelson.uk/tags/conferences/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>DDDNorth 2014 Review</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/dddnorth-2014-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2014 20:11:52 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/dddnorth-2014-review/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I had no excuse for not attending &lt;a href=&#34;http://dddnorth.co.uk/&#34;&gt;DDDNorth&lt;/a&gt; this year, as it was held at Leeds University, a relatively short drive from home. Not that I’d be looking for an excuse – these free events are always superbly organised and provide a valuable opportunity to see sessions from a wide range of speakers without having to take time off work. It’s no wonder the tickets are always snapped up so quickly.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I had no excuse for not attending <a href="http://dddnorth.co.uk/">DDDNorth</a> this year, as it was held at Leeds University, a relatively short drive from home. Not that I’d be looking for an excuse – these free events are always superbly organised and provide a valuable opportunity to see sessions from a wide range of speakers without having to take time off work. It’s no wonder the tickets are always snapped up so quickly.</p>
<p>As a contractor, I also appreciate the opportunity that DDDNorth affords me to catch up with so many friends and colleagues that I’ve worked with over the years, and it was great to see so many familiar faces.</p>
<p>With five slots during the day each offering five concurrent sessions there were plenty of difficult choices to be made. In general, I tried to attend sessions offering information I didn’t think I would be able to get from books, blogs or PluralSight – stories from the trenches and architectural concepts rather than deep dives on specific technologies.</p>
<p>The first session I attended was “<strong>So You Want To Be A Tech Lead – 10 Things You Need To Do To Succeed</strong>” by <a href="http://www.hammond-turner.org.uk/">Joel Hammond-Turner</a> (<a href="https://twitter.com/rammesses">@rammesses</a>). I was delighted to find that the eponymous ten things were not airy-fairy woolly soft-skill type things, but in fact consisted of ten topics backed by a whole bunch of concrete real-world actionable suggestions. These ranged from large architectural tasks (use NuGet obsessively for all internal dependencies, set up automated release management with Octopus, etc) to the little things that can make a difference (be willing to take your headphones off, read and share <a href="http://blog.cwa.me.uk/">The Morning Brew</a>, add photographs to Personas..)</p>
<p>Next I saw “<strong>Not Just Layers! What Can Pipelines and Events Do For You?</strong>“, presented by DDD circuit regular <a href="http://codebetter.com/iancooper/">Ian Cooper</a> (<a href="https://twitter.com/icooper">@icooper</a>). This was the most technical session that I saw, and required some serious concentration. Ian started his presentation with some slides that explained the theoretical background behind the architectural concepts he was introducing. These were beautiful and densely packed with information, and I plan to review them at my leisure! He then fired up Visual Studio and demonstrated some C# implementations of the patterns previously described. Kudos to Ian for creating a successful presentation on a fairly dry architectural topic – inevitably it could only scratch the surface but has whetted my appetite to venture beyond the typical layering approach when considering candidate software architectures.</p>
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
<p>As I hurtle inexorably towards my 40s, and noting the general absence of older coders in the workplace, I have been starting to wonder whether I need to identify alternative career paths away from the code face. So the following talk was of particular interest to me.</p>
<p>Ceri Shaw’s (<a href="https://twitter.com/cerishaw">@cerishaw</a>) talk “<strong>Join The Dark Side – Why Developers Should Consider Management</strong>” began by covering some of the negative managerial stereotypes that we techies tend to hold (yes, there was a Dilbert cartoon). She continued by looking at the traits needed to be an effective line manager or project manager within a technical team, identifying (as the session title suggests) that developers did in fact possess many of the requisite skills. Although I’m still not entirely convinced that a full-time management role is the right move for me personally, I can see how some aspect of mentoring or scrum mastering might not be entirely incompatible with my desire to retain a hands-on techie, and I will be seeking out some of the resources she mentioned to learn more.</p>
<p>There were a number of interesting short grok talks during lunchtime. I particularly enjoyed hearing <a href="http://www.relentlessdevelopment.net/">Grant Crofton</a> (<a href="https://twitter.com/relentlessdev">@relentlessdev</a>) describe his attempts to use functional programming to determine the most appropriate school for his son! That sounds like a slightly more practical means of developing skills in F# than my own efforts to use it solve some of the Project Euler problems.</p>
<p>“<strong>Burnout Is Real And It’s Coming To Get You</strong>” was the title of <a href="http://www.devjoy.com/">Richard Dalton’s</a> (<a href="https://twitter.com/richardadalton">@richardadalton</a>) talk, which I consider to be the highlight of the day. Richard took a potentially worrying subject and gave hope and advice for all of us who have at some time felt ourselves to be at some point along the burnout continuum.</p>
<p>I was particularly interested in the observation that it is precisely those of us who place a high value on our work (and are willing to give up a Saturday to attend a conference) who are likely to feel burned out and overly self-critical of our perceived inability to drive technical change or achieve as much as we would like.
The Agile movement, Richard suggested, was born as the result of an entire industry feeling burnt out and unable to get things done.
He cautioned us not to be jealous of or constantly compare ourselves to other developers, and to consider what aspects of life are poorer for those in our industry who are able to devote vast amounts of time to developing open source frameworks or writing popular blogs. I was also pleased to hear someone else mention the guilt that they feel when they choose to spend their hard-earned free time reading for pleasure instead of being glued to PluralSight or reading tech books. We do need to go easier on ourselves if we’re in this for the long haul.</p>
<p>The issue of age naturally came up – Richard concluded that there is no discernable mental decline between a programmer aged 20 and the same aged 40, it’s just that we have many more demands on our time around this age, leaving us with less contingency time to catch up on the less productive days. If we make it through this period in our lives without quitting the industry, it was suggested that things could actually be easier in our 50s as children become more self-sufficient and we once again have some time to spare.</p>
<p>In summary, it was a very reassuring talk, wrapped up with helpful advice on how to handle burnout – what works and what doesn’t.</p>
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
<p>In recent years the projects that I have worked on have involved much web services work (both as a client and server), so I was interested to hear <a href="https://twitter.com/david_whitney">David Whitney’s</a> (<a href="https://twitter.com/david_whitney">@david_whitney</a>) “<strong>Lessons Learned Running A Public API</strong>” talk, full of tips gathered developing the Rest API for Justgiving.com<br>
There was a good mixture of hard technical advice (how to handle versioning, authentication, what data formats to support..) along with softer ideas of the supporting work required to create and maintain a successful public API (generated documentation, SDKs, not being a slave to external requirements or a single client, getting a product manager).</p>
<p>I was particularly struck by the openness of the approach recommended by David, which involved creating public Google groups to push support issues into the community, and making a public uptime page available. Lots of good tips from the trenches here. Once again, here was some real actionable advice from a session that we can take away and put into practice.</p>
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
<p>And that (after the customary prize draws and closing comments), was that. Thanks to <a href="https://twitter.com/apwestgarth">Andrew Westgarth</a>, <a href="http://www.blackmarble.co.uk/">Black Marble</a>, the <a href="http://www.leeds.ac.uk/">University of Leeds</a>, and all the sponsors and speakers for once again staging a vital event. The development community in the North would be much poorer without this large multi-track multi-session event, and I look forward to attending again next year.</p>
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Agile Yorkshire @ The Pub – Gojko Adzic, 10th June 2009</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/agile-yorkshire-the-pub-gojko-adzic-10th-june-2009/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jun 2009 08:06:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/agile-yorkshire-the-pub-gojko-adzic-10th-june-2009/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you’re in the Leeds area next Wednesday, why not come along to this Agile Yorkshire session?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;10th-june--gojko-adzic-slim-the-future-of-fitnesse&#34;&gt;10th June – Gojko Adzic: Slim, The Future Of FitNesse&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;details&#34;&gt;Details&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This talk will introduce Slim, the most important upgrade to &lt;a href=&#34;http://fitnesse.org/&#34;&gt;FitNesse&lt;/a&gt; in years. Slim is the new test runner which promises to bring platform interoperability, easier integration, a much simpler programming model and lots of small helpers that will allow us to write and maintain executable specifications and acceptance tests easier. This is a session for .NET and Java developers. Some prior exposure to FitNesse and FIT would be beneficial, but not required.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>If you’re in the Leeds area next Wednesday, why not come along to this Agile Yorkshire session?</p>
<blockquote>
<h2 id="10th-june--gojko-adzic-slim-the-future-of-fitnesse">10th June – Gojko Adzic: Slim, The Future Of FitNesse</h2>
<h3 id="details">Details</h3>
<p>This talk will introduce Slim, the most important upgrade to <a href="http://fitnesse.org/">FitNesse</a> in years. Slim is the new test runner which promises to bring platform interoperability, easier integration, a much simpler programming model and lots of small helpers that will allow us to write and maintain executable specifications and acceptance tests easier. This is a session for .NET and Java developers. Some prior exposure to FitNesse and FIT would be beneficial, but not required.</p>
<h3 id="speaker">Speaker</h3>
<p>Gojko Adzic is a software craftsman with a passion for new technologies, programming and writing. He runs <a href="http://neuri.co.uk/">Neuri Ltd</a>, a UK-based consultancy that helps companies build better software by introducing agile practices and tools and improving communication between software teams, stakeholders and clients. See <a href="http://gojko.net/about/">http://gojko.net/about/</a> for more details.</p>
<p>Venue: Victoria Hotel, Central Leeds</p>
<p>Date/Time: Wednesday, 10th June, <strong>6:30pm sharp</strong>.</p>
<p>More details: <a href="http://www.agileyorkshire.org/">http://www.agileyorkshire.org/</a></p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Agile Yorkshire @ The Pub – Exploratory Testing, May 13th</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/agile-yorkshire-the-pub-exploratory-testing-may-13th/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 May 2009 11:05:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/agile-yorkshire-the-pub-exploratory-testing-may-13th/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If I can get a pass out from helping to look after the burgeoning Nelson family for an evening, I’ll be going along to this Agile Yorkshire session next Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;may-13th--ralph-williams-exploratory-testing&#34;&gt;May 13th – Ralph Williams: Exploratory Testing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;details&#34;&gt;Details&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this session, Ralph will provide an overview of some techniques that bring Agility into the world of testing. (The world of testing is a strange place: regarded by most people as a nice place to visit but you wouldn’t want to live there, it is an unmapped wilderness where the waterfall methodology still roams unfettered.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>If I can get a pass out from helping to look after the burgeoning Nelson family for an evening, I’ll be going along to this Agile Yorkshire session next Wednesday.</p>
<h2 id="may-13th--ralph-williams-exploratory-testing">May 13th – Ralph Williams: Exploratory Testing</h2>
<h3 id="details">Details</h3>
<p>In this session, Ralph will provide an overview of some techniques that bring Agility into the world of testing. (The world of testing is a strange place: regarded by most people as a nice place to visit but you wouldn’t want to live there, it is an unmapped wilderness where the waterfall methodology still roams unfettered.)</p>
<p>The main focus will be on one such technique, Exploratory Testing. It is defined by many as “simultaneous learning, test design and test execution”, but Ralph will attempt to be more helpful. After the presentation many of you will claim this is what you have been doing all along, but now it has a fancy name you can use it without shame and companies can sell you high-priced consultancy in it.</p>
<h3 id="speaker">Speaker</h3>
<p>Ralph Williams is a Test Consultant at the Yorkshire Building Society, based in Bradford. The Society develops much of the application software used throughout its 140 branches and offices, and Ralph is responsible for managing the testing for some of these systems. He has previously worked in various management, testing and development roles at Erudine, Wanadoo and British Telecom, and specialises in Agile Testing and chocolate.</p>
<p>Venue: Victoria Hotel, Central Leeds</p>
<p>Date/Time: Wednesday, 13th May, 6.30pm for a 7.00pm start.</p>
<p>More details: <a href="http://www.agileyorkshire.org/">http://www.agileyorkshire.org/</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Alt.Net UK In The North</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/alt-net-uk-in-the-north/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2009 20:04:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/alt-net-uk-in-the-north/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I spent much of this weekend over in Bradford, talking shop with the good folks at the Alt.Net UK ‘in the North’ conference. I had a great time, learned much, and am grateful to &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.blackmarble.co.uk/blogs/rfennell/&#34;&gt;Richard Fennell&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.blackmarble.co.uk/&#34;&gt;Black Marble&lt;/a&gt; and the other organisers and sponsors for making the event possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was the first &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Open_Space_Technology&#34;&gt;Open Spaces&lt;/a&gt; event I’ve attended, and I was pleasantly surprised at how orderly and productive the sessions turned out to be. Unlike conventional sales-pitch conferences of the MSDN roadshow variety, this was more of an open forum, with an expectation that all of the relatively small number (25ish?) of participants would, well, &lt;em&gt;participate&lt;/em&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I spent much of this weekend over in Bradford, talking shop with the good folks at the Alt.Net UK ‘in the North’ conference. I had a great time, learned much, and am grateful to <a href="http://blogs.blackmarble.co.uk/blogs/rfennell/">Richard Fennell</a> of <a href="http://www.blackmarble.co.uk/">Black Marble</a> and the other organisers and sponsors for making the event possible.</p>
<p>This was the first <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Open_Space_Technology">Open Spaces</a> event I’ve attended, and I was pleasantly surprised at how orderly and productive the sessions turned out to be. Unlike conventional sales-pitch conferences of the MSDN roadshow variety, this was more of an open forum, with an expectation that all of the relatively small number (25ish?) of participants would, well, <em>participate</em>!</p>
<p>I was also surprised to find that there were more pragmatists in attendance than architecture astronauts. Maybe it’s a reflection of the current economic climate, but a common theme was on finding toolings that were <em>good enough</em> with which to deliver suitable solutions quickly and effectively, rather than striving for architectural purity and perfection.</p>
<p>It was great to hear some war stories, and learn about technologies, tools, methodologies and ideas that are currently exciting other people. It would be difficult to come away from a weekend like this one without some inspiration and a big list of several things to follow up on. Here’s mine:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong><a href="http://www.asp.net/mvc/">MVC Framework</a></strong> – like myself, a lot of the attendees have had enough of the WebForms model, and are excited about the potential of ASP.NET MVC.</li>
<li><strong><a href="http://fluentnhibernate.org/">Fluent NHibernate</a></strong> – it sounds like the project being feverishly worked on by <a href="http://blog.jagregory.com/">James Gregory</a> et al is ready for prime time. People spoke very positively of the ability to ditch XML HBM files in favour of this strongly-typed configuration.</li>
<li><strong><a href="http://www.balsamiq.com/">Balsamiq Mockups</a></strong> – loved by everyone, even despite (or should that be because of?) its use of Comic Sans MS!</li>
<li><strong>Inversion of Control</strong> – there was a wide mix of IoC containers being used. I’ve tried <a href="http://www.castleproject.org/container/index.html">Castle Windsor</a>, other people made positive murmurings about <a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/cc468366.aspx">Unity</a> and <a href="http://structuremap.sourceforge.net/Default.htm">StructureMap</a>.</li>
<li><strong><a href="http://www.typemock.com">TypeMock Isolator</a></strong> – apparently capable of mocking the unmockable.</li>
<li><strong><a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/0123740371?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=ianesbl-21&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1634&amp;creative=19450&amp;creativeASIN=0123740371">Sketching User Experiences</a></strong> – everyone who’d heard of him spoke highly of Bill Buxton’s work.</li>
<li><strong><a href="http://www.openquarters.org">Open Quarters CMS</a></strong> – a great demonstration of a CMS built on ASP.NET MVC by <a href="http://www.anthonymain.com/">Anthony Main</a> and Andrew Magee. I look forward to taking a squizz at the source, I’m sure it will be an excellent learning aid.</li>
<li><strong><a href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/ulti-swat">SWAT</a></strong> – a web testing tool developed by some folks at Ultimate Software and released on Sourceforge as an open source project (thanks to <a href="http://mckennatribe.com/">Nick</a> for the link).</li>
<li><strong>Wild Blue Yonder</strong> – a delicious amber ale from Oregon which was on tap at the Sir Titus Salt pub, to where we decamped after the planning session on Friday night. Yum!</li>
</ul>
<p>I’m probably forgetting some things, there was a lot to take in, and I regret not having a pad of paper on hand. Hopefully my memory will be jogged by the blog postings of the other attendees.</p>
<p>Thanks again to all who made it possible, and all the attendees for quality the chat and inspiration.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Seeking Kindred Spirits</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/seeking-kindred-spirits/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Apr 2009 14:04:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/seeking-kindred-spirits/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m coming round to the realization that my hugely enjoyable first contract at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ventura.co.uk&#34;&gt;Ventura&lt;/a&gt; last summer might have been something of an anomaly. That project was decidedly agile, test-driven, and used a bunch of modern technologies including Monorail, ExtJS, Subversion, NUnit and NHibernate. The requirements were well-defined, and the team was highly effective, with a pragmatic project management team who kept the development team free from bureaucratic processes, leaving us able to get on with delivering some cracking software in double-quick time.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I’m coming round to the realization that my hugely enjoyable first contract at <a href="http://www.ventura.co.uk">Ventura</a> last summer might have been something of an anomaly. That project was decidedly agile, test-driven, and used a bunch of modern technologies including Monorail, ExtJS, Subversion, NUnit and NHibernate. The requirements were well-defined, and the team was highly effective, with a pragmatic project management team who kept the development team free from bureaucratic processes, leaving us able to get on with delivering some cracking software in double-quick time.</p>
<p>So, it has been something of a surprise to move onto pastures new and discover that there are still organisations out there who follow the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Waterfall_model">Waterfall model</a> and highly prescriptive change control processes. It also seems that no amount of evangelism or proselytism from freelancers such as myself is likely to change the situation any time soon – it’s just the organisational culture. To be realistic, there comes a point in time at which I have to accept that fact, shut up, and knuckle down to achieving the project deliverables in the manner requested by the client. The customer is always right, as they say.</p>
<p>As I bide my time looking for some new clients who share my development methodology ideologies, I’ve been trying to retain some semblance of sanity by keeping on top of agile techniques and technologies, and by seeking kindred spirits with whom to discuss the same. I was pleasantly surprised to discover the existence of the <a href="http://www.agileyorkshire.org">Agile Yorkshire Club</a>, who meet monthly in the back room of a pub in Leeds. So I pitched up last Wednesday, enjoyed the free beer, met some friendly and seemingly like-minded people, and listened to an interesting session by <a href="http://blogs.blackmarble.co.uk/blogs/rfennell">Richard Fennell</a> of Black Marble as he talked about <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/0201699478?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=ianesbl-21&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1634&amp;creative=19450&amp;creativeASIN=0201699478">Alistair Cockburn’s Crystal Clear</a> methodology, which seemed to me to be essentially “Pragmatic SCRUM”.</p>
<p>I’ve often heard people say that it’s a good idea to get involved with a local user group, or attend community events, and now I’m starting to appreciate why. In addition to the mind-broadening opportunities, the networking potential for freelancers is also an obvious benefit. If, like me, you’ve never before tried to get “out there” and meet other IT professionals, why not give it a shot? If a shy and reserved geek like me can do it, anyone can.</p>
<p>And if you organise or know of other, similar groups local to Leeds, I’d be interested in hearing about them.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Software Architect 2007</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/software-architect-2007/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Jun 2007 18:06:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/software-architect-2007/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last week I had the pleasure of spending a few days in London attending the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.software-architect.co.uk&#34;&gt;Software Architect 2007&lt;/a&gt; conference at the Barbican centre. It was a good conference, providing me with some useful and interesting new ideas and food for thought, whilst confirming that our team at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.marshalls.co.uk&#34;&gt;Marshalls&lt;/a&gt; are generally going about things in “the right way”, which is nice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking through my notes, the main themes that kept recurring within the different presentations that I attended were:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Last week I had the pleasure of spending a few days in London attending the <a href="http://www.software-architect.co.uk">Software Architect 2007</a> conference at the Barbican centre. It was a good conference, providing me with some useful and interesting new ideas and food for thought, whilst confirming that our team at <a href="http://www.marshalls.co.uk">Marshalls</a> are generally going about things in “the right way”, which is nice.</p>
<p>Looking through my notes, the main themes that kept recurring within the different presentations that I attended were:</p>
<ul>
<li>Avoid coupling at all costs. Use interfaces, contracts and facades to decouple components. Avoid directly referencing vendor’s class libraries or infrastructure libraries.</li>
<li>Appreciate the impact of small decisions which can eventually have a big impact on the overall architecture.</li>
<li>Devote more time and consideration to designing interfaces, contracts and public APIs (which are difficulty to change retrospectively), than private implementations which are relatively simple to change.</li>
</ul>
<p>These issues kept coming up again and again – most notably in talks by Kevlin Henney on “The Selfish Object” and Ralf Westphal on “True Component Orientation”, but also to an extent in some of Dave Wheeler’s demonstration of how to use some of the Gang of Four design patterns in .NET. So, it amazed me that a number of my fellow delegates kept raising their hands and asking questions which invariably began “Yeah, but why can’t I just…”, followed by suggestions which effectively seemed to boil down to creating hardcoded, inflexible solutions! To say that this was supposedly a conference of architects, even relatively simple concepts such as Reflection, Polymorphism and Generics seemed to be lost on some people, who apparently would be more comfortable maintaining massive switch statements for the rest of eternity!</p>
<p>This is one of the issues I have with the XP rules – I don’t believe that <a href="http://www.extremeprogramming.org/rules/simple.html">doing the simplest thing that could possibly work</a> is a good idea, at least not when creating public APIs and interfaces. Some forethought is necessary in order to architect loosely coupled solutions that will allow continued flexibility and agility when faced with inevitable change requests. I’m not arguing for the <a href="http://www.extremeprogramming.org/rules/early.html">premature development of functionality that may never be required</a>, but interfaces, APIs, inheritance models and database models are a right royal pain to change at a later date and in my experience, upfront design in these areas pays dividends.</p>
<p>Oh, my other issue with the XP rules is the notion of <a href="http://www.extremeprogramming.org/rules/collective.html">collective code ownership</a> – I’m not precious about my code (honest), but there are inevitably areas of specialism (in terms of technology and business knowledge) in which I seek to focus my energies, and other areas that I don’t care for, or wish to maintain. We can’t all understand everything about every system, and it’s foolish to pretend that this is the case. Allowing or requiring an entire team to be comfortable maintaining the whole codebase is likely to prohibit anybody learning very much about anything, and even with rigorously enforced coding standards and comprehensive unit tests can lead to an unfortunate swiss cheese / patchwork quilt effect. All IMHO, of course.</p>
<p>My favourite session of the conference was by <a href="http://www.ralfw.de">Ralf Westphal</a>, who clearly and concisely (his English is better than that of many native speakers!) explained the benefits of using Contract First Development and a microkernel approach to remove component dependencies and development bottlenecks. It’s an approach that I can’t wait to try.</p>
<p>One of the other things that pleased me about the conference was the realisation that we at Marshalls are (especially for such a stable, old-economy company), way ahead of the pack in terms of technology – whilst other delegates I spoke with are still using earlier versions of .NET, or even still on VB6 / Win32 API, we continue to make appropriate use of the latest offerings from Redmond.</p>
<p>A few other observations from my days in London:</p>
<ul>
<li>Trying to change from the Circle to Piccadilly lines at King’s Cross at rush hour involves crossing a packed concourse buzzing with hardened commuters that brought to mind that Zurich insurance TV advert which shows futuristic cars on traffic signal-free intersections narrowly avoiding collisions thanks to automated guidance systems!</li>
<li>Unlike at MSDN events (where all speakers use vanilla installations of Vista/XP and search Windows Live using IE7), there’s a great variety of hardware and software in popular use now – I witnessed presentations on Dell, Sony Vaio, and MacBook (running both OS X and Vista, through BootCamp), with some highly-configured operating systems, and every presenter used Safari or Firefox – no IE in sight. Didn’t see any Ubuntu, mind.</li>
<li>Section 20 of the <a href="http://www.opsi.gov.uk/ACTS/acts1997/97022--f.htm#20">Architect’s Act 1997</a> prohibits the use of the “Software Architect” job title. Curiously, “Golf Course Architect” is fine.</li>
<li>In all respects, central London is about as far removed from the Isle of Mull (where I was a week previously) as it’s possible to imagine. Increasingly so, it really does come across as a kind of city state, a world city, with a cosmopolitan feeling quite unlike anywhere else in the UK.</li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MSDN Technical Roadshow 2007</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/msdn-technical-roadshow-2007/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Mar 2007 22:03:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/msdn-technical-roadshow-2007/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m off to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.microsoft.com/uk/techroadshow2007/msdn/default.mspx&#34;&gt;MSDN Technical roadshow&lt;/a&gt; in Harrogate tomorrow, and am actually really looking forward to it this time. These events are free, so always well worth attending when they’re local, but some years are certainly better than others – it mostly depends on the material being covered. I remember one year circa 2003-4, when .NET was well established, but before the Whidbey release, so the majority of the day was effectively just a sales pitch covering elementary .NET concepts, presumably for those laggards who hadn’t yet made the great leap from VB6. Another data-binding demo, anybody?  Yawn.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I’m off to the <a href="http://www.microsoft.com/uk/techroadshow2007/msdn/default.mspx">MSDN Technical roadshow</a> in Harrogate tomorrow, and am actually really looking forward to it this time. These events are free, so always well worth attending when they’re local, but some years are certainly better than others – it mostly depends on the material being covered. I remember one year circa 2003-4, when .NET was well established, but before the Whidbey release, so the majority of the day was effectively just a sales pitch covering elementary .NET concepts, presumably for those laggards who hadn’t yet made the great leap from VB6. Another data-binding demo, anybody?  Yawn.</p>
<p>By contrast, this time round there’s no shortage of exciting potential topics, and as I’ve mentioned recently, I’ve been having difficulty making time to get stuck into learning some of the new technologies that are on the horizon. So the opportunity of a day out watching some powerpoint presentations, demos, and trying to soak up an understanding of this stuff really appeals to me – is that sad?!</p>
<p>The two sessions I’m most looking forward to are <a href="http://www.danielmoth.com/Blog/">Daniel Moth</a> covering LINQ and other forthcoming language enhancements in the Orcas release, and <a href="http://blogs.msdn.com/mikeormond/default.aspx">Mike Ormond</a>&rsquo;s session on AJAX development. Should be good.</p>
<p>Oh, entertainingly, someone found my blog this week by Googling for <a href="http://www.google.com/search?q=%22msdn&#43;event%22&#43;dress&#43;code&amp;">“msdn event” dress code</a> – my advice is to go casual; stick to the usual geek staples of t-shirt with jeans or combats and you can’t go far wrong!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>eXtreme .NET</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/extreme-net/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jun 2005 21:06:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/extreme-net/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Up at 0500 yesterday and onto the early GNER Mallard down to that London town for the MSDN briefing on eXtreme programming with .NET. It was pleasant not to be driving for a change, and speeding through the Yorkshire countryside early on a midsummer morning was very relaxing – what a stark contrast with the hot crowded tube that I had to catch on arrival to the big smoke. Three stops down to Oxford Circus seemed to last as long as the entire preceeding train journey. How people do this every single day I do not know..&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Up at 0500 yesterday and onto the early GNER Mallard down to that London town for the MSDN briefing on eXtreme programming with .NET. It was pleasant not to be driving for a change, and speeding through the Yorkshire countryside early on a midsummer morning was very relaxing – what a stark contrast with the hot crowded tube that I had to catch on arrival to the big smoke. Three stops down to Oxford Circus seemed to last as long as the entire preceeding train journey. How people do this every single day I do not know..</p>
<p>Anyway, I digress. The tech briefing was excellent, a full day’s set of presentations on eXtreme development practices by the very erudite and engaging <a href="http://www.roodyn.com/">Dr Neil Roodyn</a>, with additional demos by some of the MSDN UK guys. During questioning, nobody in the audience was arguing against using the XP practices espoused, in fact most questioners simply wanted to know how to get project managers and business leaders bought in to the ideas. The general consensus was that suits and customers don’t want to hear about pair programming and <a href="http://www.testdriven.com/">TDD</a>, they want to see devs working on coding new functionality, which is obviously frustrating for those of us cutting the code. Hopefully sessions like the one on Friday will help to inspire a groundswell of enthusiasm for agile practices amongst developers and team leads which the business leaders will eventually be unable to ignore. Dr Neil suggested that we don’t try to immediately enforce all 12 XP principles in our workplaces, but start using those which work for us, basically those which we can sneak in under the managements noses!  Nobody can stop you from writing unit tests and adopting a TDD approach to your coding, and may only start asking questions when they see how much more productive you’re becoming, and how fewer bugs are found in your code. After all, producing quality code is your job, and nobody will stop you from doing your job well.</p>
<hr>
<p>While I remember, some of the books mentioned by Neil were:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/exec/obidos/ASIN/0201604566">&ldquo;Software For Your Head&rdquo; by Jim McCarthy</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/exec/obidos/ASIN/0349113467">&ldquo;The Tipping Point&rdquo; by Malcolm Gladwell</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/exec/obidos/ASIN/1587991845">&ldquo;Fooled By Randomness&rdquo; by Nassim Nicholas Taleb</a></li>
</ul>
<p>and I have noted down that I should find the time to visit:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.microsoft.com/uk/msdn/postevents">http://www.microsoft.com/uk/msdn/postevents</a> – for a copy of the slides</li>
<li><a href="http://agilealliance.com">http://agilealliance.com</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.xpertise.co.uk">http://www.xpertise.co.uk</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
