<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Conferences on Ian Nelson</title>
    <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/tags/conferences/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Conferences on Ian Nelson</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.146.6</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 10 May 2025 20:10:09 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://blog.iannelson.uk/tags/conferences/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>NDC Porto 2024</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/ndc-porto-2024/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Oct 2024 22:09:29 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/ndc-porto-2024/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I had the pleasure of spending ISO Week 42 in the beautiful Portuguese coastal city of Porto, attending the NDC Porto 2024 conference for software developers by &lt;a href=&#34;https://ndcconferences.com/&#34;&gt;NDC Conferences&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s been a long time since I attended a multi-day conference – perhaps even as long ago as &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.iannelson.uk/software-architect-2007/&#34;&gt;Software Architect 2007&lt;/a&gt; (where I first learned about Dependency Injection and IOC Containers) which makes me feel quite ancient. Having been a freelancer since 2008, it’s often difficult to justify taking time out to attend conferences, no matter how valuable they might be to one’s career in the longer term. The face cost of the conference ticket is usually dwarfed by the loss of contract income (real or perceived) whilst being unable to bill a client.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I had the pleasure of spending ISO Week 42 in the beautiful Portuguese coastal city of Porto, attending the NDC Porto 2024 conference for software developers by <a href="https://ndcconferences.com/">NDC Conferences</a>.</p>
<p>It’s been a long time since I attended a multi-day conference – perhaps even as long ago as <a href="https://blog.iannelson.uk/software-architect-2007/">Software Architect 2007</a> (where I first learned about Dependency Injection and IOC Containers) which makes me feel quite ancient. Having been a freelancer since 2008, it’s often difficult to justify taking time out to attend conferences, no matter how valuable they might be to one’s career in the longer term. The face cost of the conference ticket is usually dwarfed by the loss of contract income (real or perceived) whilst being unable to bill a client.</p>
<p>But circumstances conspired to make my attendance at NDC Porto possible this year. Firstly, I’m currently doing some exclusive and inside IR35 work for a client, which effectively results in me having some mandatory days off to play with for the first time in over 15 years. And secondly, I was lucky enough to win an all-access pass to any NDC Conference at a raffle held at the last <a href="https://www.dddnorth.co.uk">DDD North</a> event this March – so many thanks to the good folk at <a href="https://blackmarble.com">Black Marble</a> for organising that event, and to <a href="https://ndcconferences.com">NDC</a> for offering the prize.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2024/10/IMG_7645-1.jpeg"></p>
<p>I had never been to Porto before, so took the opportunity to spend the weekend prior to the conference doing the tourist thing. The October weather was fantastic for walking around the historic city centre, taking in the cathedral, Torre dos Clérigos, and views of the Duoro river. My goodness, but it’s hilly though!</p>
<p>From my journal that Sunday:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“I realised that Porto doesn’t just appeal to my sense of sight. Of course the views are fantastic, but on a sunny Sunday like today there is also excellent music that carries far and wide from a range of talented buskers. Electric acoustic guitars and electric violins seemed to be the order of the day, with a mixture of classic and popular tunes. Porto also smells nice – people seem to have a variety of different fragrances that differ from those that I usually smell in Leeds. Of course there are great tastes in the form of the wines and seafood. And finally there are even things to touch – ceramic tiles, cork panels etc. Truly, this city is a feast for the senses.”</p></blockquote>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2024/10/IMG_7417.jpeg">
<img loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2024/10/IMG_7427.jpeg">
<img loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2024/10/IMG_7438.jpeg">
<img loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2024/10/IMG_7462.jpeg">
<img loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2024/10/IMG_7478.jpeg">
<img loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2024/10/IMG_7498.jpeg">
<img loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2024/10/IMG_7508.jpeg">
<img loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2024/10/IMG_7514.jpeg">
<img loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2024/10/IMG_7549.jpeg"></p>
<h2 id="workshop--designing-microservices">Workshop – Designing Microservices</h2>
<p>Before the conference proper began on Wednesday, there were nine two-day workshops to choose from. I opted to attend <em>Designing Microservices</em> by <a href="https://samnewman.io">Sam Newman</a>. I had previously read Sam’s book <em><a href="https://amzn.to/3UgfVME">Building Microservices</a></em>, and have been using microservices of some variety or other on projects since 2018. While these have sometimes been successful, I have often had the niggling doubt that some implementations on which I have worked could more accurately be described as being Distributed Monoliths, and I was eager to spend some focused time understanding when the lure of microservices should be resisted, and to dig into implementation patterns, along with examining related topics such as whether to use multirepo or monorepo approaches for source control.</p>
<p>As with Sam’s book, while ostensibly about microservices, the workshop also covered a wide range of more general architectural and software development topics that could be equally applied to traditional monoliths. It also struck a good balance between technical topics and organisational ones – how to structure teams for success when delivering a microservice-based solution. I appreciated this holistic coverage, as well as the tacit admission that microservice architectures may often not be the correct solution for a given project.</p>
<p>The workshop was delivered at a good pace, neither labouring points unnecessarily, nor glossing over more thorny topics that were worthy of due consideration. There was a good mixture of slides, dialogue, and some collaborative activity in small groups.</p>
<p>My only minor disappointment with the two-day workshop was a sense that a small minority of the other attendees were insufficiently engaged – returning late to the workshop room from our plentiful breaks, and checking their phones frequently. I assume they were attending at the behest of their employer rather than of their own volition, but this behaviour seemed disrespectful to Sam and the other attendees. I tried to ignore it.</p>
<h2 id="my-10-favourite-sessions">My 10 Favourite Sessions</h2>
<p>After the initial two days of workshops, the remaining three days were filled with over a hundred traditional one-hour sessions, with up to six sessions running concurrently. This led to sometimes difficult decisions about which sessions to attend. My strategy was generally to attend sessions covering higher-level broad-brush type topics, rather than those covering niche technologies which I could learn through reading online documentation. But even within these self-imposed guidelines, there was a wealth of material to choose from. I attended around twenty sessions – here are some thoughts on my favourite ten:</p>
<h3 id="keynote-tidy-first-a-daily-exercise-in-empirical-design-by-kent-beck">Keynote: Tidy First? A Daily Exercise in Empirical Design by Kent Beck</h3>
<p>The conference proper opened on Wednesday morning with a Keynote by Kent Beck, the creator of extreme programming, early proponent of Test-Driven Development, and one of the 17 original signatories to the Agile Manifesto. Like all the keynotes, this took place in the huge main expo hall of the conference. I can see the logistical logic behind this decision – notably that it is large enough to house all of the delegates, and ensures that the conference can kick off at 9am sharp, even if latecomers are still arriving. But on the downside there were no seats close to the stage area (I am 48 years old, the prospect of standing up for an hour didn’t appeal), whereas from the area with seats it was a struggle to hear Kent over the background chatter and espresso machines. I would learn from my mistakes and prop myself up on a table near the front for the following days’ keynotes.</p>
<p>My geriatric grumblings notwithstanding, from the portions I heard properly, this was a great talk, and I look forward to rewatching this on YouTube to fill in the gaps. Unlike every other session that I saw during the week, Kent did not have a traditional slide deck, but instead projected some freeform sketches to illustrate the concepts he discussed.</p>
<p>There was much talk about the perennial topics (and personal bugbears) of estimation, and the cost of software development, and how software designers can influence when money is spent and earned. The concept of optionality was introduced – if software can be changed, then the design does not matter. Features are easy to see, but options are difficult to see, yet this is why we invest in software. The cost of software is the cost of changing it, not the cost of building it. Some changes are surprisingly expensive, yet others are surprisingly cheap.</p>
<p>Some of my favourites quotes from the session (of which there were many, some of which would appear in the slides of other speakers later in the week):</p>
<ul>
<li>“Why can’t you estimate how long it will take to walk across a minefield?”</li>
<li>“Software should grow like a tree grows.”</li>
<li>“You can ignore the constraints, but the constraints are not going to ignore you.”</li>
<li>“I am delighted when the next generation surpasses me.”</li>
</ul>
<p>Kent wrapped up with a few words on this year’s hot topic of AI. He drew parallels with the development of highly efficient steam engines during the Industrial Revolution, and explained how this had actually led to an increase in the use of coal (the Jevon’s Paradox). He offered that the AIs are not coming for our jobs any time soon and that we are, in fact entering a new golden age for programming. This topic would crop up again throughout the conference.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2024/10/IMG_7607.jpeg"></p>
<h3 id="being-staff-plus-by-ian-cooper">Being Staff Plus by Ian Cooper</h3>
<p>Having now notched up 27 years at the code face, I have recently been giving some considerations as to where to take my career in the coming years, without having to sell my soul to the devil and venture over to the dark side of management. This session from Ian Cooper on “Staff Plus” roles offered some great advice on the nature of senior technical leadership roles, and how to “move beyond code” while staying resolutely technical.</p>
<p>Ian offered a good balance of high-level strategic career advice married with a bunch of helpful tactical hints and tips for how to succeed (and demonstrate that success) in such roles, and I urge any other greybeards feeling frustrated with their careers to watch this presentation (<a href="https://youtu.be/l-oCDQGH3EU?si=nAIK3UqvDUhQPZpl">the version from NDC Oslo is online here</a>).</p>
<p>This was the first session that sent me scurrying to Amazon to buy some recommended books (it would not be the last!). By the time I got home to England on Saturday both <em><a href="https://amzn.to/3YtNpcY">T</a><a href="https://amzn.to/3NxVNlu">he Staff Engineer’s Path: A Guide for Individual Contributors Navigating Growth and Change</a></em> by Tanya Reilly and <em><a href="https://amzn.to/3NxWpHF">Staff Engineer: Leadership Beyond the Management Track</a></em> by Will Larson would be waiting for me.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2024/10/Image-20-10-2024-at-16.36-5.jpeg"></p>
<h3 id="definition-of-insanity--timeouts-retries-and-idempotency-by-sam-newman">Definition Of Insanity – Timeouts, retries, and idempotency by Sam Newman</h3>
<p>This session by Sam Newman focused on some of key techniques for developing resilient distributed systems: Timing out remote calls that do not complete in a timely fashion, Retrying unsuccessful calls, and how to achieve idempotency to ensure that calls can be retried safely without undesirable side-effects.</p>
<p>This topic is highly relevant to a distributed system that I am developing for my current client, so I listened intently and appreciated the detailed low-level advice. I was particularly interested in the observation that <em>if a retry of an idempotent request succeeds, we should send back the same semantic response that we would have sent had the original request succeeded</em>. Also new to me was the concept of a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bloom_filter">Bloom Filter</a>.</p>
<p>Improving the resilience of distributed systems has been an interest of mine since reading the first edition of <em><a href="https://amzn.to/3C3Qh7m">Release It!</a></em> by Michael Nygard in 2009. I’m delighted to see that Sam is currently authoring <a href="https://samnewman.io/books/building-resilient-distributed-systems/">a new book on this topic</a>, due for publication in 2025.</p>
<h3 id="open-source-open-mind-the-cost-of-free-software-by-dylan-beattie">Open Source, Open Mind: The Cost of Free Software by Dylan Beattie</h3>
<p>A light-hearted talk to end the first day of the conference, this session by Dylan Beattie was a whistle-stop tour of the history of open source software, covering notable successes, failures and lawsuits, followed by some thoughts on where “free software” goes from here.</p>
<p>A recording of <a href="https://youtu.be/vzYqxo13I1U?si=eacYByQwreIj2O_U">an earlier version of this talk from NDC Oslo 2024 is available online</a>, but Dylan had added extra material to the talk since then to cover the recent disputes between WordPress.com owners Automattic and WP Engine.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2024/10/IMG_7630.jpeg"></p>
<h3 id="keynote-can-you-trust-your-large-language-model-by-jodie-burchell">Keynote: Can you trust your (large language) model? by Jodie Burchell</h3>
<p>Thursday’s keynote by data scientist Jodie Burchell talked about how the quality of Large Language Models (LLMs) such as ChatGPT has been measured, and highlighted structural deficiencies with both the benchmarks as well as the AI tooling themselves. I confess to not having devoted much time over the past year to understanding the “AI revolution”, so did not know what to expect from this talk, but I found it a fascinating and highly approachable explanation that has piqued my interest. My contemporary notes from this session read “Such a good talk. Chase down the slides, and sessions from <a href="https://youtu.be/lLNJld729bc?si=x2ASipnm2PGcKt6d">earlier</a> <a href="https://youtu.be/9EI_lqPUVEE?si=jR9HOaAHIPnc_qoD">NDCs</a>“.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2024/10/Image-20-10-2024-at-16.36-1024x768.jpeg"></p>
<h3 id="orchestration-vs-choreography-the-good-the-bad-and-the-trade-offs-by-laïla-bougriâ">Orchestration vs. Choreography: The good, the bad, and the trade-offs by Laïla Bougriâ</h3>
<p>Designing distributed systems regularly involves trying to decide between synchronous or asynchronous communication, and orchestration or choreography (and the combinations thereof). There are, of course, tradeoffs to make, but the design decisions are often made when considering only the happy path scenarios.</p>
<p>This excellent talk by Laïla Bougriâ took this complex nuanced subject, with all of its “it depends” messiness, and offered concrete guidance for when and how to implement each approach. One of my favourite sessions of the whole conference, and Laïla coped excellently with audio problems for the first third of the presentation.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2024/10/Image-20-10-2024-at-16.27-2-1024x768.jpeg"></p>
<h3 id="a-developer-goes-to-the-movies-by-simon-painter">A Developer Goes to the Movies by Simon Painter</h3>
<p>Thursday, the middle day of the conference proper, was a long one, but fortunately there were some great light-hearted talks later in the day to balance those that required more intense thinking.</p>
<p>I had previously enjoyed seeing Simon Painter give his talk “From Ancient Greeks to Modern Geeks: Basic Machine Learning Algorithms” at DDD North in Hull in March 2024. For this new talk, he brings together his twin passions of movies and coding by presenting a visual history of computing and software developers as seen by Hollywood.</p>
<p>I don’t seem to have made as many notes on this talk, preferring to relax and enjoy the show (though sadly without popcorn), but I do recall enjoying the segments on <a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0086567/">WarGames</a>, <a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0113957">The Net</a> and <a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0113243">Hackers</a> (which I really must watch again soon). It was also intriguing to learn that the distinction for the first person to have portrayed a computer hacker in a movie goes to none other than Benny Hill!</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2024/10/IMG_7647.jpeg"></p>
<h3 id="how-simple-is-as-simple-as-possible-by-rendle">How Simple Is “As Simple As Possible”? by Rendle</h3>
<p>Rendle has been doing this programming lark for even longer than me. But unlike me (who merely grumbles about our industry through the medium of Instagram memes shared with equally bitter colleagues), Rendle is an ex-professional standup comic who takes the grumbling to a whole new level by holding up a (black) mirror to our industry in conference presentations such as this one.</p>
<p>The thing is, as the saying goes, <em>it’s funny because it’s true</em>. Rendle is on a mission to highlight how unnecessarily complex we have made most aspects of software design, development and deployment during his career, and proselytise for an easier, simpler and more productive life. Amen to that.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2024/10/IMG_7650.jpeg"></p>
<h3 id="keynote-start-here-mindset-shifts-and-tools-for-building-career-confidence-in-a-post-pandemic-era-by-denise-jacobs">Keynote: Start Here: Mindset Shifts and Tools for Building Career Confidence in a Post-Pandemic Era by Denise Jacobs</h3>
<p>For Friday’s final keynote of the conference, I took my now-customary standing spot up front near the stage… and then immediately regretted it as I noticed the pens and paper dotted around the tables. I realised with horror that this was going to be an interactive session, and considered retreating to the back of the room. I do not generally enjoy audience participation, have no “fun facts” on hand to share about myself, and abhor “icebreakers” at the start of meetings and workshops.</p>
<p>But, I told myself that I had come all this way to Porto with the intention of adopting a growth mindset and learning as much as possible, so ought to give it a go. I’m glad I did, as Denise’s talk became one of my favourite of the conference, and the audience participation exercises (which were not as scary as I had feared) helped to boost my confidence and further renew my interest in my career.</p>
<p>I ordered yet another book recommendation on the back of this talk – <em><a href="https://amzn.to/3BNS3JM">Chatter: The Voice in Our Head and How to Harness It</a></em> by Ethan Kross, but opted for Audible this time to reduce the number of Amazon packages that would be arriving at home in my absence.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2024/10/Image-20-10-2024-at-16.25-4.jpeg"></p>
<h3 id="the-next-decade-of-software-development-by-richard-campbell">The Next Decade of Software Development by Richard Campbell</h3>
<p>Richard Campbell is best known to me as the co-host of the <a href="https://www.dotnetrocks.com">.NET Rocks!</a> podcast, but his interest and expertise in science, computing, and technology is far broader than that niche (he gave another talk at this conference on the topic of Nuclear Power).</p>
<p>This talk on the Next Decade of Software Development has been presented many times over the years and been regularly updated as new trends such as the Cloud emerge and gradually become mainstream. It reviews where we’ve been, examines the trend lines, and looks forward to which trends and technologies we will need to learn to remain relevant in our roles in the upcoming years. As with many of the other talks, this naturally touched on AI, and joined that consensus that we are entering a period where the LLMs will aid our software development work rather than directly threatening it. At a more prosaic level, Richard was also positive that .NET and Blazor are not going anywhere any time soon.</p>
<h2 id="final-thoughts">Final Thoughts</h2>
<p>I thoroughly enjoyed my time at NDC Porto. The conference is expertly organised by a team who have clearly been doing this for quite some time. The venue – <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Porto_Convention_Centre">a former customshouse on the banks of the Duoro</a> – was airy and inspirational. The complementary food and drink was delicious and plentiful. The speakers were knowledgeable and friendly, making themselves available for questions outside of the sessions themselves. Generally I found my fellow attendees to be amiable and approachable, and appreciated mingling amongst the wide variety of nationalities present from across the European continent and further afield. I remain disheartened by the male skew in the gender balance of attendees at tech conferences, but it was pleasing to note how many (excellent) female speakers gave talks – I suspect and hope that NDC are doing all they reasonably can to improve diversity.</p>
<p>I return home to Yorkshire, and back to the code face, with a renewed enthusiasm for my chosen career and a rekindled excitement for technologies (both new and old – some of the talks by Anders Norås have made me nostalgic for my Amiga 500 and 1200!). Oh, and with an ever-growing pile of books to read!</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2024/10/IMG_7578.jpeg">
<img loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2024/10/IMG_7673.png"></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DDDNorth 2022</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/dddnorth-2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Dec 2022 15:48:39 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/dddnorth-2022/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday morning I arose unusually early for a Saturday and drove eastwards to attend this year’s &lt;a href=&#34;https://dddnorth.co.uk/&#34;&gt;DDDNorth&lt;/a&gt; at the University of Hull. These free, community-driven events held at the weekend offer an invaluable opportunity to learn from peers in the industry in a relaxed environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Five concurrent sessions in each timeslot means that tough decisions often have to be made about which to attend! In acknowledgement of my maturing years (I’ve been reading up on &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Optimal_stopping&#34;&gt;optimal stopping&lt;/a&gt;) and the niche that I have carved out for myself, I chose to stick to those sessions that focused on backend and distributed architecture and development.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday morning I arose unusually early for a Saturday and drove eastwards to attend this year’s <a href="https://dddnorth.co.uk/">DDDNorth</a> at the University of Hull. These free, community-driven events held at the weekend offer an invaluable opportunity to learn from peers in the industry in a relaxed environment.</p>
<p>Five concurrent sessions in each timeslot means that tough decisions often have to be made about which to attend! In acknowledgement of my maturing years (I’ve been reading up on <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Optimal_stopping">optimal stopping</a>) and the niche that I have carved out for myself, I chose to stick to those sessions that focused on backend and distributed architecture and development.</p>
<p>My choice for the first session of the day was an overview of <strong>.NET Minimal APIs</strong> by Microsoft MVP Kevin Smith (<a href="https://twitter.com/kev_bite">@kev_bite</a>). Restful APIs on the Microsoft .NET platform frequently form a key part of the systems that I design and develop, so it’s vital to stay abreast of the latest techniques for implementing these. Kev’s session was really useful to me as it concisely demonstrated the approaches available in .NET Core 7 Minimal APIs, freeing me of the need to discover what’s new via reading documentation or other means. I particularly appreciated seeing demonstrations of approaches for the automated testing of APIs, and some of the post-session Q&amp;A about how best to structure real-world enterprise .NET APIs was insightful.</p>
<p><img alt="Kevin Smith is presenting in a lecture theatre" loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2023/08/image.jpeg">
Kevin Smith demos how to test .NET Minimal APIs</p>
<p>I’ve blogged before about the <a href="https://blog.iannelson.uk/on-the-inherent-negativity-of-computer-programmers/">Inherent Negativity of Computer Programmers</a>, and it’s fair to say that this pessimism hasn’t changed as my career has progressed! As an architect of distributed systems, knowledge of techniques for handling unavailable or poorly-performing dependencies are an essential part of my day-to-day toolset. Andy Clark’s (<a href="https://twitter.com/TechyChap">@techychap</a>) entertaining session “<strong>When Microservices Go Bad</strong>” covered a variety of strategies such as caching, retries, timeouts, circuit breakers, bulkheads and rate limiting. For each of these, he showed how they can be achieved using the excellent open source library <a href="https://github.com/App-vNext/Polly">Polly</a>. I’ve been using some of Polly’s features on my current project (I’ve been a long-time fan of <a href="https://blog.iannelson.uk/a-circuit-breaker-which-trips-on-frequency-of-failures/">Circuit Breaker</a> since I first learned of it from reading Michael Nygard’s <em><a href="https://amzn.to/3VwRvwP">Release It!</a></em> book), but this session opened my eyes to the full gamut of how Polly could help protect the systems I design. Hat-tip to Andy for the live demos in this session, and for contending with the multi-monitor weirdness.</p>
<p>The third session was my favourite of the day. “<strong>Don’t Put Your Messages In A Bottle: Implement Messaging Patterns</strong>” saw <a href="https://azure.microsoft.com/en-gb/products/service-bus">Azure Service Bus</a> Senior Program Manager Eldert Grootenboer (<a href="https://twitter.com/egrootenboer">@egrootenboer</a>) provide a whistle-stop overview of fourteen (fourteen!) separate messaging patterns. The Circuit Breaker pattern made another appearance, as did some patterns which were new to me such as Sequential Convoy and Transactional Outbox. I’ve been getting by with simply using Azure Storage Queues for most of my queueing requirements in recent years, but this presentation reminded me of the richer techniques that are possible with Service Bus. This hour-long session flew by and left me wanting more. Time to dust off my copy of <a href="https://amzn.to/3Uu78Ee">Hohpe and Woolf’s Enterprise Integration Patterns</a> and brush up ahead of my next distributed architecture challenge.</p>
<p>“<strong>Software Architecture: In Search of the Fourth Chord</strong>” by straight-speaking Paul Michaels (<a href="https://twitter.com/paul_michaels">@paul_michaels</a>) was a more laid-back session which covered many of the common problems and trade-offs faced by Software Architects. Paul rightly highlighted that the architect is likely the only person on a project who cares about the full range of functional and nonfunctional characteristics of a system. But I’m not sure that his throwaway comment “no-one ever says ‘can you make the system scale?&rsquo;” is strictly true – I think this can depend on the project and sector. For example, a large part of my working life during the pandemic has involved ensuring that the NHS App and associated systems can scale to meet spikes in traffic, and here scalability and universal access are often of higher importance than, say, a richer feature set.</p>
<p>The session concluded by suggesting that, much as Status Quo have been able to have a successful musical career with a limited number of chords, so the average Software Architect can get a long way in their chosen career through judicious application of the Message Broker, Event Sourcing and CQRS patterns.</p>
<p>The final session I attended was “<strong>SOA Lessons Learnt (or, Microservices Done Better)</strong>“, where Sean Farmar (<a href="https://twitter.com/farmar">@farmar</a>) gave an entertaining and often opinionated run through his  experiences developing and architecting distributed systems since the 1990s. The general premise was that while technologies and fashions may change over the years, the key thing is to avoid coupling at all costs – a theme which I remember noting from my attendance at <a href="https://blog.iannelson.uk/software-architect-2007/">Software Architect 2007</a> fifteen years ago. It was also nice to be reminded of Peter Deutsch’s <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fallacies_of_distributed_computing">Fallacies of Distributed Computing</a>, which are even more relevant today than they were in the mid-90s.</p>
<p>Finally, before the dark and rainy drive home, it was time for goodbyes and the traditional prize draw. I’m delighted to report that I had the good fortune to win a <a href="https://github.com/">GitHub</a>-branded scarf which I shall wear with pride to protect my nesh self against the inclement Yorkshire winter that lies ahead.</p>
<p>Many thanks to all who presented, organised and sponsored this year’s DDDNorth. As ever, it was an enjoyable and productive way to spend a Saturday.</p>
<p><img alt="A handsome forty-something software engineer models his new GitHub-branded scarf" loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2023/08/image-1-scaled.jpeg">
Sporting my lovely new GitHub scarf</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DDDNorth 2014 Review</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/dddnorth-2014-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2014 20:11:52 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/dddnorth-2014-review/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I had no excuse for not attending &lt;a href=&#34;http://dddnorth.co.uk/&#34;&gt;DDDNorth&lt;/a&gt; this year, as it was held at Leeds University, a relatively short drive from home. Not that I’d be looking for an excuse – these free events are always superbly organised and provide a valuable opportunity to see sessions from a wide range of speakers without having to take time off work. It’s no wonder the tickets are always snapped up so quickly.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I had no excuse for not attending <a href="http://dddnorth.co.uk/">DDDNorth</a> this year, as it was held at Leeds University, a relatively short drive from home. Not that I’d be looking for an excuse – these free events are always superbly organised and provide a valuable opportunity to see sessions from a wide range of speakers without having to take time off work. It’s no wonder the tickets are always snapped up so quickly.</p>
<p>As a contractor, I also appreciate the opportunity that DDDNorth affords me to catch up with so many friends and colleagues that I’ve worked with over the years, and it was great to see so many familiar faces.</p>
<p>With five slots during the day each offering five concurrent sessions there were plenty of difficult choices to be made. In general, I tried to attend sessions offering information I didn’t think I would be able to get from books, blogs or PluralSight – stories from the trenches and architectural concepts rather than deep dives on specific technologies.</p>
<p>The first session I attended was “<strong>So You Want To Be A Tech Lead – 10 Things You Need To Do To Succeed</strong>” by <a href="http://www.hammond-turner.org.uk/">Joel Hammond-Turner</a> (<a href="https://twitter.com/rammesses">@rammesses</a>). I was delighted to find that the eponymous ten things were not airy-fairy woolly soft-skill type things, but in fact consisted of ten topics backed by a whole bunch of concrete real-world actionable suggestions. These ranged from large architectural tasks (use NuGet obsessively for all internal dependencies, set up automated release management with Octopus, etc) to the little things that can make a difference (be willing to take your headphones off, read and share <a href="http://blog.cwa.me.uk/">The Morning Brew</a>, add photographs to Personas..)</p>
<p>Next I saw “<strong>Not Just Layers! What Can Pipelines and Events Do For You?</strong>“, presented by DDD circuit regular <a href="http://codebetter.com/iancooper/">Ian Cooper</a> (<a href="https://twitter.com/icooper">@icooper</a>). This was the most technical session that I saw, and required some serious concentration. Ian started his presentation with some slides that explained the theoretical background behind the architectural concepts he was introducing. These were beautiful and densely packed with information, and I plan to review them at my leisure! He then fired up Visual Studio and demonstrated some C# implementations of the patterns previously described. Kudos to Ian for creating a successful presentation on a fairly dry architectural topic – inevitably it could only scratch the surface but has whetted my appetite to venture beyond the typical layering approach when considering candidate software architectures.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Two eyes and two ears is not enough kit for &lsquo;Not Just Layers&rsquo; @DDDNorth @ICooper<br>
— Mark Dickinson (@tuganetmark) October 18, 2014</p></blockquote>
<p>As I hurtle inexorably towards my 40s, and noting the general absence of older coders in the workplace, I have been starting to wonder whether I need to identify alternative career paths away from the code face. So the following talk was of particular interest to me.</p>
<p>Ceri Shaw’s (<a href="https://twitter.com/cerishaw">@cerishaw</a>) talk “<strong>Join The Dark Side – Why Developers Should Consider Management</strong>” began by covering some of the negative managerial stereotypes that we techies tend to hold (yes, there was a Dilbert cartoon). She continued by looking at the traits needed to be an effective line manager or project manager within a technical team, identifying (as the session title suggests) that developers did in fact possess many of the requisite skills. Although I’m still not entirely convinced that a full-time management role is the right move for me personally, I can see how some aspect of mentoring or scrum mastering might not be entirely incompatible with my desire to retain a hands-on techie, and I will be seeking out some of the resources she mentioned to learn more.</p>
<p>There were a number of interesting short grok talks during lunchtime. I particularly enjoyed hearing <a href="http://www.relentlessdevelopment.net/">Grant Crofton</a> (<a href="https://twitter.com/relentlessdev">@relentlessdev</a>) describe his attempts to use functional programming to determine the most appropriate school for his son! That sounds like a slightly more practical means of developing skills in F# than my own efforts to use it solve some of the Project Euler problems.</p>
<p>“<strong>Burnout Is Real And It’s Coming To Get You</strong>” was the title of <a href="http://www.devjoy.com/">Richard Dalton’s</a> (<a href="https://twitter.com/richardadalton">@richardadalton</a>) talk, which I consider to be the highlight of the day. Richard took a potentially worrying subject and gave hope and advice for all of us who have at some time felt ourselves to be at some point along the burnout continuum.</p>
<p>I was particularly interested in the observation that it is precisely those of us who place a high value on our work (and are willing to give up a Saturday to attend a conference) who are likely to feel burned out and overly self-critical of our perceived inability to drive technical change or achieve as much as we would like.
The Agile movement, Richard suggested, was born as the result of an entire industry feeling burnt out and unable to get things done.
He cautioned us not to be jealous of or constantly compare ourselves to other developers, and to consider what aspects of life are poorer for those in our industry who are able to devote vast amounts of time to developing open source frameworks or writing popular blogs. I was also pleased to hear someone else mention the guilt that they feel when they choose to spend their hard-earned free time reading for pleasure instead of being glued to PluralSight or reading tech books. We do need to go easier on ourselves if we’re in this for the long haul.</p>
<p>The issue of age naturally came up – Richard concluded that there is no discernable mental decline between a programmer aged 20 and the same aged 40, it’s just that we have many more demands on our time around this age, leaving us with less contingency time to catch up on the less productive days. If we make it through this period in our lives without quitting the industry, it was suggested that things could actually be easier in our 50s as children become more self-sufficient and we once again have some time to spare.</p>
<p>In summary, it was a very reassuring talk, wrapped up with helpful advice on how to handle burnout – what works and what doesn’t.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>SUPERB talk on Burnout by @richardadalton – someone should get a video made for HR departments to see. #dddnorth</p>
<p>— Joel Hammond-Turner (@rammesses)</p></blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Fantastic talk on burnout by @richardadalton #dddnorth one of the highlights of the day!</p>
<p>— Rushby (@rushbys)</p></blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>So @richardadalton talk was stand out, absolutely hit the nail on the head. Covered points i&rsquo;d not even considered. Well done #dddnorth</p>
<p>— Kirsty Busfield (@kirstybu)</p></blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>@richardadalton&rsquo;s talk has been the best one at #dddnorth. Burnout is prevalent in the software industry.</p>
<p>— Mark Robinson (@Defstun)</p></blockquote>
<p>In recent years the projects that I have worked on have involved much web services work (both as a client and server), so I was interested to hear <a href="https://twitter.com/david_whitney">David Whitney’s</a> (<a href="https://twitter.com/david_whitney">@david_whitney</a>) “<strong>Lessons Learned Running A Public API</strong>” talk, full of tips gathered developing the Rest API for Justgiving.com<br>
There was a good mixture of hard technical advice (how to handle versioning, authentication, what data formats to support..) along with softer ideas of the supporting work required to create and maintain a successful public API (generated documentation, SDKs, not being a slave to external requirements or a single client, getting a product manager).</p>
<p>I was particularly struck by the openness of the approach recommended by David, which involved creating public Google groups to push support issues into the community, and making a public uptime page available. Lots of good tips from the trenches here. Once again, here was some real actionable advice from a session that we can take away and put into practice.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Really enjoyed the @david_whitney session on APIs to round off the day at #dddnorth</p>
<p>– Paul D&rsquo;Ambra (@pauldambra)</p></blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Good solid advice so far from #dddnorth presentations.</p>
<p>— Chris Gibbons (@jibubo)</p></blockquote>
<p>And that (after the customary prize draws and closing comments), was that. Thanks to <a href="https://twitter.com/apwestgarth">Andrew Westgarth</a>, <a href="http://www.blackmarble.co.uk/">Black Marble</a>, the <a href="http://www.leeds.ac.uk/">University of Leeds</a>, and all the sponsors and speakers for once again staging a vital event. The development community in the North would be much poorer without this large multi-track multi-session event, and I look forward to attending again next year.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Come out of #dddnorth with loads of ideas &amp; thoughts, just got to find time to look into them</p>
<p>— Nathan Gloyn (@NathanGloyn)</p></blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Such a long day at #dddnorth today, but totally worth it as always. Excellent day out in Leeds. @DDDNorth</p>
<p>— Gary Emery (@gaz_y2k4)</p></blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>@DDDNorth First ever visit to DDD North. Excellent day, massive thanks to all involved!</p>
<p>— Chris Shepherd (@Shepless)</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Agile Yorkshire @ The Pub – Gojko Adzic, 10th June 2009</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/agile-yorkshire-the-pub-gojko-adzic-10th-june-2009/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jun 2009 08:06:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/agile-yorkshire-the-pub-gojko-adzic-10th-june-2009/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you’re in the Leeds area next Wednesday, why not come along to this Agile Yorkshire session?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;10th-june--gojko-adzic-slim-the-future-of-fitnesse&#34;&gt;10th June – Gojko Adzic: Slim, The Future Of FitNesse&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;details&#34;&gt;Details&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This talk will introduce Slim, the most important upgrade to &lt;a href=&#34;http://fitnesse.org/&#34;&gt;FitNesse&lt;/a&gt; in years. Slim is the new test runner which promises to bring platform interoperability, easier integration, a much simpler programming model and lots of small helpers that will allow us to write and maintain executable specifications and acceptance tests easier. This is a session for .NET and Java developers. Some prior exposure to FitNesse and FIT would be beneficial, but not required.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>If you’re in the Leeds area next Wednesday, why not come along to this Agile Yorkshire session?</p>
<blockquote>
<h2 id="10th-june--gojko-adzic-slim-the-future-of-fitnesse">10th June – Gojko Adzic: Slim, The Future Of FitNesse</h2>
<h3 id="details">Details</h3>
<p>This talk will introduce Slim, the most important upgrade to <a href="http://fitnesse.org/">FitNesse</a> in years. Slim is the new test runner which promises to bring platform interoperability, easier integration, a much simpler programming model and lots of small helpers that will allow us to write and maintain executable specifications and acceptance tests easier. This is a session for .NET and Java developers. Some prior exposure to FitNesse and FIT would be beneficial, but not required.</p>
<h3 id="speaker">Speaker</h3>
<p>Gojko Adzic is a software craftsman with a passion for new technologies, programming and writing. He runs <a href="http://neuri.co.uk/">Neuri Ltd</a>, a UK-based consultancy that helps companies build better software by introducing agile practices and tools and improving communication between software teams, stakeholders and clients. See <a href="http://gojko.net/about/">http://gojko.net/about/</a> for more details.</p>
<p>Venue: Victoria Hotel, Central Leeds</p>
<p>Date/Time: Wednesday, 10th June, <strong>6:30pm sharp</strong>.</p>
<p>More details: <a href="http://www.agileyorkshire.org/">http://www.agileyorkshire.org/</a></p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Agile Yorkshire @ The Pub – Exploratory Testing, May 13th</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/agile-yorkshire-the-pub-exploratory-testing-may-13th/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 May 2009 11:05:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/agile-yorkshire-the-pub-exploratory-testing-may-13th/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If I can get a pass out from helping to look after the burgeoning Nelson family for an evening, I’ll be going along to this Agile Yorkshire session next Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;may-13th--ralph-williams-exploratory-testing&#34;&gt;May 13th – Ralph Williams: Exploratory Testing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;details&#34;&gt;Details&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this session, Ralph will provide an overview of some techniques that bring Agility into the world of testing. (The world of testing is a strange place: regarded by most people as a nice place to visit but you wouldn’t want to live there, it is an unmapped wilderness where the waterfall methodology still roams unfettered.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>If I can get a pass out from helping to look after the burgeoning Nelson family for an evening, I’ll be going along to this Agile Yorkshire session next Wednesday.</p>
<h2 id="may-13th--ralph-williams-exploratory-testing">May 13th – Ralph Williams: Exploratory Testing</h2>
<h3 id="details">Details</h3>
<p>In this session, Ralph will provide an overview of some techniques that bring Agility into the world of testing. (The world of testing is a strange place: regarded by most people as a nice place to visit but you wouldn’t want to live there, it is an unmapped wilderness where the waterfall methodology still roams unfettered.)</p>
<p>The main focus will be on one such technique, Exploratory Testing. It is defined by many as “simultaneous learning, test design and test execution”, but Ralph will attempt to be more helpful. After the presentation many of you will claim this is what you have been doing all along, but now it has a fancy name you can use it without shame and companies can sell you high-priced consultancy in it.</p>
<h3 id="speaker">Speaker</h3>
<p>Ralph Williams is a Test Consultant at the Yorkshire Building Society, based in Bradford. The Society develops much of the application software used throughout its 140 branches and offices, and Ralph is responsible for managing the testing for some of these systems. He has previously worked in various management, testing and development roles at Erudine, Wanadoo and British Telecom, and specialises in Agile Testing and chocolate.</p>
<p>Venue: Victoria Hotel, Central Leeds</p>
<p>Date/Time: Wednesday, 13th May, 6.30pm for a 7.00pm start.</p>
<p>More details: <a href="http://www.agileyorkshire.org/">http://www.agileyorkshire.org/</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Alt.Net UK In The North</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/alt-net-uk-in-the-north/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2009 20:04:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/alt-net-uk-in-the-north/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I spent much of this weekend over in Bradford, talking shop with the good folks at the Alt.Net UK ‘in the North’ conference. I had a great time, learned much, and am grateful to &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.blackmarble.co.uk/blogs/rfennell/&#34;&gt;Richard Fennell&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.blackmarble.co.uk/&#34;&gt;Black Marble&lt;/a&gt; and the other organisers and sponsors for making the event possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was the first &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Open_Space_Technology&#34;&gt;Open Spaces&lt;/a&gt; event I’ve attended, and I was pleasantly surprised at how orderly and productive the sessions turned out to be. Unlike conventional sales-pitch conferences of the MSDN roadshow variety, this was more of an open forum, with an expectation that all of the relatively small number (25ish?) of participants would, well, &lt;em&gt;participate&lt;/em&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I spent much of this weekend over in Bradford, talking shop with the good folks at the Alt.Net UK ‘in the North’ conference. I had a great time, learned much, and am grateful to <a href="http://blogs.blackmarble.co.uk/blogs/rfennell/">Richard Fennell</a> of <a href="http://www.blackmarble.co.uk/">Black Marble</a> and the other organisers and sponsors for making the event possible.</p>
<p>This was the first <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Open_Space_Technology">Open Spaces</a> event I’ve attended, and I was pleasantly surprised at how orderly and productive the sessions turned out to be. Unlike conventional sales-pitch conferences of the MSDN roadshow variety, this was more of an open forum, with an expectation that all of the relatively small number (25ish?) of participants would, well, <em>participate</em>!</p>
<p>I was also surprised to find that there were more pragmatists in attendance than architecture astronauts. Maybe it’s a reflection of the current economic climate, but a common theme was on finding toolings that were <em>good enough</em> with which to deliver suitable solutions quickly and effectively, rather than striving for architectural purity and perfection.</p>
<p>It was great to hear some war stories, and learn about technologies, tools, methodologies and ideas that are currently exciting other people. It would be difficult to come away from a weekend like this one without some inspiration and a big list of several things to follow up on. Here’s mine:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong><a href="http://www.asp.net/mvc/">MVC Framework</a></strong> – like myself, a lot of the attendees have had enough of the WebForms model, and are excited about the potential of ASP.NET MVC.</li>
<li><strong><a href="http://fluentnhibernate.org/">Fluent NHibernate</a></strong> – it sounds like the project being feverishly worked on by <a href="http://blog.jagregory.com/">James Gregory</a> et al is ready for prime time. People spoke very positively of the ability to ditch XML HBM files in favour of this strongly-typed configuration.</li>
<li><strong><a href="http://www.balsamiq.com/">Balsamiq Mockups</a></strong> – loved by everyone, even despite (or should that be because of?) its use of Comic Sans MS!</li>
<li><strong>Inversion of Control</strong> – there was a wide mix of IoC containers being used. I’ve tried <a href="http://www.castleproject.org/container/index.html">Castle Windsor</a>, other people made positive murmurings about <a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/cc468366.aspx">Unity</a> and <a href="http://structuremap.sourceforge.net/Default.htm">StructureMap</a>.</li>
<li><strong><a href="http://www.typemock.com">TypeMock Isolator</a></strong> – apparently capable of mocking the unmockable.</li>
<li><strong><a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/0123740371?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=ianesbl-21&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1634&amp;creative=19450&amp;creativeASIN=0123740371">Sketching User Experiences</a></strong> – everyone who’d heard of him spoke highly of Bill Buxton’s work.</li>
<li><strong><a href="http://www.openquarters.org">Open Quarters CMS</a></strong> – a great demonstration of a CMS built on ASP.NET MVC by <a href="http://www.anthonymain.com/">Anthony Main</a> and Andrew Magee. I look forward to taking a squizz at the source, I’m sure it will be an excellent learning aid.</li>
<li><strong><a href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/ulti-swat">SWAT</a></strong> – a web testing tool developed by some folks at Ultimate Software and released on Sourceforge as an open source project (thanks to <a href="http://mckennatribe.com/">Nick</a> for the link).</li>
<li><strong>Wild Blue Yonder</strong> – a delicious amber ale from Oregon which was on tap at the Sir Titus Salt pub, to where we decamped after the planning session on Friday night. Yum!</li>
</ul>
<p>I’m probably forgetting some things, there was a lot to take in, and I regret not having a pad of paper on hand. Hopefully my memory will be jogged by the blog postings of the other attendees.</p>
<p>Thanks again to all who made it possible, and all the attendees for quality the chat and inspiration.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Seeking Kindred Spirits</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/seeking-kindred-spirits/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Apr 2009 14:04:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/seeking-kindred-spirits/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m coming round to the realization that my hugely enjoyable first contract at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ventura.co.uk&#34;&gt;Ventura&lt;/a&gt; last summer might have been something of an anomaly. That project was decidedly agile, test-driven, and used a bunch of modern technologies including Monorail, ExtJS, Subversion, NUnit and NHibernate. The requirements were well-defined, and the team was highly effective, with a pragmatic project management team who kept the development team free from bureaucratic processes, leaving us able to get on with delivering some cracking software in double-quick time.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I’m coming round to the realization that my hugely enjoyable first contract at <a href="http://www.ventura.co.uk">Ventura</a> last summer might have been something of an anomaly. That project was decidedly agile, test-driven, and used a bunch of modern technologies including Monorail, ExtJS, Subversion, NUnit and NHibernate. The requirements were well-defined, and the team was highly effective, with a pragmatic project management team who kept the development team free from bureaucratic processes, leaving us able to get on with delivering some cracking software in double-quick time.</p>
<p>So, it has been something of a surprise to move onto pastures new and discover that there are still organisations out there who follow the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Waterfall_model">Waterfall model</a> and highly prescriptive change control processes. It also seems that no amount of evangelism or proselytism from freelancers such as myself is likely to change the situation any time soon – it’s just the organisational culture. To be realistic, there comes a point in time at which I have to accept that fact, shut up, and knuckle down to achieving the project deliverables in the manner requested by the client. The customer is always right, as they say.</p>
<p>As I bide my time looking for some new clients who share my development methodology ideologies, I’ve been trying to retain some semblance of sanity by keeping on top of agile techniques and technologies, and by seeking kindred spirits with whom to discuss the same. I was pleasantly surprised to discover the existence of the <a href="http://www.agileyorkshire.org">Agile Yorkshire Club</a>, who meet monthly in the back room of a pub in Leeds. So I pitched up last Wednesday, enjoyed the free beer, met some friendly and seemingly like-minded people, and listened to an interesting session by <a href="http://blogs.blackmarble.co.uk/blogs/rfennell">Richard Fennell</a> of Black Marble as he talked about <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/0201699478?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=ianesbl-21&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1634&amp;creative=19450&amp;creativeASIN=0201699478">Alistair Cockburn’s Crystal Clear</a> methodology, which seemed to me to be essentially “Pragmatic SCRUM”.</p>
<p>I’ve often heard people say that it’s a good idea to get involved with a local user group, or attend community events, and now I’m starting to appreciate why. In addition to the mind-broadening opportunities, the networking potential for freelancers is also an obvious benefit. If, like me, you’ve never before tried to get “out there” and meet other IT professionals, why not give it a shot? If a shy and reserved geek like me can do it, anyone can.</p>
<p>And if you organise or know of other, similar groups local to Leeds, I’d be interested in hearing about them.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Software Architect 2007</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/software-architect-2007/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Jun 2007 18:06:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/software-architect-2007/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last week I had the pleasure of spending a few days in London attending the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.software-architect.co.uk&#34;&gt;Software Architect 2007&lt;/a&gt; conference at the Barbican centre. It was a good conference, providing me with some useful and interesting new ideas and food for thought, whilst confirming that our team at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.marshalls.co.uk&#34;&gt;Marshalls&lt;/a&gt; are generally going about things in “the right way”, which is nice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking through my notes, the main themes that kept recurring within the different presentations that I attended were:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Last week I had the pleasure of spending a few days in London attending the <a href="http://www.software-architect.co.uk">Software Architect 2007</a> conference at the Barbican centre. It was a good conference, providing me with some useful and interesting new ideas and food for thought, whilst confirming that our team at <a href="http://www.marshalls.co.uk">Marshalls</a> are generally going about things in “the right way”, which is nice.</p>
<p>Looking through my notes, the main themes that kept recurring within the different presentations that I attended were:</p>
<ul>
<li>Avoid coupling at all costs. Use interfaces, contracts and facades to decouple components. Avoid directly referencing vendor’s class libraries or infrastructure libraries.</li>
<li>Appreciate the impact of small decisions which can eventually have a big impact on the overall architecture.</li>
<li>Devote more time and consideration to designing interfaces, contracts and public APIs (which are difficulty to change retrospectively), than private implementations which are relatively simple to change.</li>
</ul>
<p>These issues kept coming up again and again – most notably in talks by Kevlin Henney on “The Selfish Object” and Ralf Westphal on “True Component Orientation”, but also to an extent in some of Dave Wheeler’s demonstration of how to use some of the Gang of Four design patterns in .NET. So, it amazed me that a number of my fellow delegates kept raising their hands and asking questions which invariably began “Yeah, but why can’t I just…”, followed by suggestions which effectively seemed to boil down to creating hardcoded, inflexible solutions! To say that this was supposedly a conference of architects, even relatively simple concepts such as Reflection, Polymorphism and Generics seemed to be lost on some people, who apparently would be more comfortable maintaining massive switch statements for the rest of eternity!</p>
<p>This is one of the issues I have with the XP rules – I don’t believe that <a href="http://www.extremeprogramming.org/rules/simple.html">doing the simplest thing that could possibly work</a> is a good idea, at least not when creating public APIs and interfaces. Some forethought is necessary in order to architect loosely coupled solutions that will allow continued flexibility and agility when faced with inevitable change requests. I’m not arguing for the <a href="http://www.extremeprogramming.org/rules/early.html">premature development of functionality that may never be required</a>, but interfaces, APIs, inheritance models and database models are a right royal pain to change at a later date and in my experience, upfront design in these areas pays dividends.</p>
<p>Oh, my other issue with the XP rules is the notion of <a href="http://www.extremeprogramming.org/rules/collective.html">collective code ownership</a> – I’m not precious about my code (honest), but there are inevitably areas of specialism (in terms of technology and business knowledge) in which I seek to focus my energies, and other areas that I don’t care for, or wish to maintain. We can’t all understand everything about every system, and it’s foolish to pretend that this is the case. Allowing or requiring an entire team to be comfortable maintaining the whole codebase is likely to prohibit anybody learning very much about anything, and even with rigorously enforced coding standards and comprehensive unit tests can lead to an unfortunate swiss cheese / patchwork quilt effect. All IMHO, of course.</p>
<p>My favourite session of the conference was by <a href="http://www.ralfw.de">Ralf Westphal</a>, who clearly and concisely (his English is better than that of many native speakers!) explained the benefits of using Contract First Development and a microkernel approach to remove component dependencies and development bottlenecks. It’s an approach that I can’t wait to try.</p>
<p>One of the other things that pleased me about the conference was the realisation that we at Marshalls are (especially for such a stable, old-economy company), way ahead of the pack in terms of technology – whilst other delegates I spoke with are still using earlier versions of .NET, or even still on VB6 / Win32 API, we continue to make appropriate use of the latest offerings from Redmond.</p>
<p>A few other observations from my days in London:</p>
<ul>
<li>Trying to change from the Circle to Piccadilly lines at King’s Cross at rush hour involves crossing a packed concourse buzzing with hardened commuters that brought to mind that Zurich insurance TV advert which shows futuristic cars on traffic signal-free intersections narrowly avoiding collisions thanks to automated guidance systems!</li>
<li>Unlike at MSDN events (where all speakers use vanilla installations of Vista/XP and search Windows Live using IE7), there’s a great variety of hardware and software in popular use now – I witnessed presentations on Dell, Sony Vaio, and MacBook (running both OS X and Vista, through BootCamp), with some highly-configured operating systems, and every presenter used Safari or Firefox – no IE in sight. Didn’t see any Ubuntu, mind.</li>
<li>Section 20 of the <a href="http://www.opsi.gov.uk/ACTS/acts1997/97022--f.htm#20">Architect’s Act 1997</a> prohibits the use of the “Software Architect” job title. Curiously, “Golf Course Architect” is fine.</li>
<li>In all respects, central London is about as far removed from the Isle of Mull (where I was a week previously) as it’s possible to imagine. Increasingly so, it really does come across as a kind of city state, a world city, with a cosmopolitan feeling quite unlike anywhere else in the UK.</li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MSDN Technical Roadshow 2007</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/msdn-technical-roadshow-2007/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Mar 2007 22:03:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/msdn-technical-roadshow-2007/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m off to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.microsoft.com/uk/techroadshow2007/msdn/default.mspx&#34;&gt;MSDN Technical roadshow&lt;/a&gt; in Harrogate tomorrow, and am actually really looking forward to it this time. These events are free, so always well worth attending when they’re local, but some years are certainly better than others – it mostly depends on the material being covered. I remember one year circa 2003-4, when .NET was well established, but before the Whidbey release, so the majority of the day was effectively just a sales pitch covering elementary .NET concepts, presumably for those laggards who hadn’t yet made the great leap from VB6. Another data-binding demo, anybody?  Yawn.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I’m off to the <a href="http://www.microsoft.com/uk/techroadshow2007/msdn/default.mspx">MSDN Technical roadshow</a> in Harrogate tomorrow, and am actually really looking forward to it this time. These events are free, so always well worth attending when they’re local, but some years are certainly better than others – it mostly depends on the material being covered. I remember one year circa 2003-4, when .NET was well established, but before the Whidbey release, so the majority of the day was effectively just a sales pitch covering elementary .NET concepts, presumably for those laggards who hadn’t yet made the great leap from VB6. Another data-binding demo, anybody?  Yawn.</p>
<p>By contrast, this time round there’s no shortage of exciting potential topics, and as I’ve mentioned recently, I’ve been having difficulty making time to get stuck into learning some of the new technologies that are on the horizon. So the opportunity of a day out watching some powerpoint presentations, demos, and trying to soak up an understanding of this stuff really appeals to me – is that sad?!</p>
<p>The two sessions I’m most looking forward to are <a href="http://www.danielmoth.com/Blog/">Daniel Moth</a> covering LINQ and other forthcoming language enhancements in the Orcas release, and <a href="http://blogs.msdn.com/mikeormond/default.aspx">Mike Ormond</a>&rsquo;s session on AJAX development. Should be good.</p>
<p>Oh, entertainingly, someone found my blog this week by Googling for <a href="http://www.google.com/search?q=%22msdn&#43;event%22&#43;dress&#43;code&amp;">“msdn event” dress code</a> – my advice is to go casual; stick to the usual geek staples of t-shirt with jeans or combats and you can’t go far wrong!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>eXtreme .NET</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/extreme-net/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jun 2005 21:06:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/extreme-net/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Up at 0500 yesterday and onto the early GNER Mallard down to that London town for the MSDN briefing on eXtreme programming with .NET. It was pleasant not to be driving for a change, and speeding through the Yorkshire countryside early on a midsummer morning was very relaxing – what a stark contrast with the hot crowded tube that I had to catch on arrival to the big smoke. Three stops down to Oxford Circus seemed to last as long as the entire preceeding train journey. How people do this every single day I do not know..&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Up at 0500 yesterday and onto the early GNER Mallard down to that London town for the MSDN briefing on eXtreme programming with .NET. It was pleasant not to be driving for a change, and speeding through the Yorkshire countryside early on a midsummer morning was very relaxing – what a stark contrast with the hot crowded tube that I had to catch on arrival to the big smoke. Three stops down to Oxford Circus seemed to last as long as the entire preceeding train journey. How people do this every single day I do not know..</p>
<p>Anyway, I digress. The tech briefing was excellent, a full day’s set of presentations on eXtreme development practices by the very erudite and engaging <a href="http://www.roodyn.com/">Dr Neil Roodyn</a>, with additional demos by some of the MSDN UK guys. During questioning, nobody in the audience was arguing against using the XP practices espoused, in fact most questioners simply wanted to know how to get project managers and business leaders bought in to the ideas. The general consensus was that suits and customers don’t want to hear about pair programming and <a href="http://www.testdriven.com/">TDD</a>, they want to see devs working on coding new functionality, which is obviously frustrating for those of us cutting the code. Hopefully sessions like the one on Friday will help to inspire a groundswell of enthusiasm for agile practices amongst developers and team leads which the business leaders will eventually be unable to ignore. Dr Neil suggested that we don’t try to immediately enforce all 12 XP principles in our workplaces, but start using those which work for us, basically those which we can sneak in under the managements noses!  Nobody can stop you from writing unit tests and adopting a TDD approach to your coding, and may only start asking questions when they see how much more productive you’re becoming, and how fewer bugs are found in your code. After all, producing quality code is your job, and nobody will stop you from doing your job well.</p>
<hr>
<p>While I remember, some of the books mentioned by Neil were:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/exec/obidos/ASIN/0201604566">&ldquo;Software For Your Head&rdquo; by Jim McCarthy</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/exec/obidos/ASIN/0349113467">&ldquo;The Tipping Point&rdquo; by Malcolm Gladwell</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/exec/obidos/ASIN/1587991845">&ldquo;Fooled By Randomness&rdquo; by Nassim Nicholas Taleb</a></li>
</ul>
<p>and I have noted down that I should find the time to visit:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.microsoft.com/uk/msdn/postevents">http://www.microsoft.com/uk/msdn/postevents</a> – for a copy of the slides</li>
<li><a href="http://agilealliance.com">http://agilealliance.com</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.xpertise.co.uk">http://www.xpertise.co.uk</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
