<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Hardware on Ian Nelson</title>
    <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/tags/hardware/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Hardware on Ian Nelson</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.146.6</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 10 May 2025 23:18:06 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://blog.iannelson.uk/tags/hardware/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Friday Retrospective: My First Printer</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/friday-retrospective-my-first-printer/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2014 05:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/friday-retrospective-my-first-printer/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My first printer was a Star LC-20 nine pin dot matrix that I received as a Christmas present when I was 15 years old. That’s the kind of nerdy teenager I was, folks. All yuletide long our home rang out with the deafening noise made by those pins rapidly and repeatedly punching through a flimsy ink-soaked ribbon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Incidentally, Radio 4 are forever running features about the ongoing decline in audible birdsong in the English countryside. Personally, I think it’s a travesty that a whole generation of kids will grow up unfamiliar with the nerve-shattering noise of a built-to-last dot matrix, the inimitable caterwauling of a 33.6 kbps modem connecting to a dial-up BBS, or the satisfying clunk as a 3.5 inch floppy is gleefully accepted by a disk drive. Moving to an SSD may have provided an incredible boost to my development productivity, but there’s a part of me that misses hearing the faint humming and scratching sounds of traditional hard disk heads moving across a highly-polished platter. But I digress…&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>My first printer was a Star LC-20 nine pin dot matrix that I received as a Christmas present when I was 15 years old. That’s the kind of nerdy teenager I was, folks. All yuletide long our home rang out with the deafening noise made by those pins rapidly and repeatedly punching through a flimsy ink-soaked ribbon.</p>
<p>Incidentally, Radio 4 are forever running features about the ongoing decline in audible birdsong in the English countryside. Personally, I think it’s a travesty that a whole generation of kids will grow up unfamiliar with the nerve-shattering noise of a built-to-last dot matrix, the inimitable caterwauling of a 33.6 kbps modem connecting to a dial-up BBS, or the satisfying clunk as a 3.5 inch floppy is gleefully accepted by a disk drive. Moving to an SSD may have provided an incredible boost to my development productivity, but there’s a part of me that misses hearing the faint humming and scratching sounds of traditional hard disk heads moving across a highly-polished platter. But I digress…</p>
<p>That first printer cost my parents £169.99 – not an insignificant amount of money back in 1991. It printed onto tractor-feed paper, and I received a <em>huge</em> box of the stuff for Christmas. Theoretically it was also capable of printing onto standard A4 sheets too, but this involved so much hassle gingerly feeding individual sheets into the machine that it was simpler just to forget it and stick with the tractor feed option. As a result, all of my GCSE English coursework was submitted on somewhat crinkly US Letter sized tractor feed paper. It may not have been beautiful, but it was considerably more presentable than my handwriting, and I was determined to use the cutting-edge option, dammit!</p>
<p>The LC20 was controlled by four buttons which had to be pressed in odd combinations to trigger line feeds and page feeds (ask your parents), and to switch between one of the four inbuilt “fonts”. More complex settings could be made by poking at shy DIP switches with a biro. It was all a far cry from the wireless connection to embedded web servers that we’ve come to expect from our peripherals these days.</p>
<p>Around the same time as this, I recall shelling out £60 for a Roctec “Roclite” External 1.44 Mb Floppy Drive, after reading exhaustive floppy drive reviews in the inaugural issue of <em>Amiga Shopper</em>. This was pre-Amazon, of course, so I usually made such purchases from GemSoft on Furnival Gate in Sheffield – a day-long expedition via the number 85 bus.</p>
<p>Oh, and a year or so later, I worked all summer long to save the £400 I needed to buy a 20Mb hard drive. Yes, twenty whole megabytes to play with – just imagine the opportunities that this presented to me!</p>
<p>What about you, dear reader? Do you have any fond memories of your earliest computer hardware?</p>
<hr>
<p>Image by <a href="http://www.retrocomputing.net/">Museo del Computer</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wacom Bamboo</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/wacom-bamboo/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Sep 2011 10:09:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/wacom-bamboo/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Almost everyone who has wandered past the various desks that I’ve occupied over the last year has passed comment on my &lt;a href=&#34;http://amzn.to/1rrSHfo&#34;&gt;Wacom Bamboo Pen Graphics Tablet&lt;/a&gt;. So, let me say a few words about my experiences with that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the longest time, I had been perfectly content to use various &lt;a href=&#34;http://amzn.to/1tLMAqb&#34;&gt;Logitech VX / MX mouses&lt;/a&gt; as my secondary input device, occasionally using a &lt;a href=&#34;http://amzn.to/PBaiVJ&#34;&gt;Microsoft Arc Mouse&lt;/a&gt; (very convenient to carry around in my rucksack).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Almost everyone who has wandered past the various desks that I’ve occupied over the last year has passed comment on my <a href="http://amzn.to/1rrSHfo">Wacom Bamboo Pen Graphics Tablet</a>. So, let me say a few words about my experiences with that.</p>
<p>For the longest time, I had been perfectly content to use various <a href="http://amzn.to/1tLMAqb">Logitech VX / MX mouses</a> as my secondary input device, occasionally using a <a href="http://amzn.to/PBaiVJ">Microsoft Arc Mouse</a> (very convenient to carry around in my rucksack).</p>
<p>But in the Spring of 2010, I developed a nagging pain in my right forefinger. It sounds silly and trivial, but over the course of a couple of months it developed from a barely-susceptible twinge to something that was genuinely impacting my life – I struggled to open Coke bottles or turn the key in our garage door’s stiff lock.</p>
<p>I turned for advice to Joe Steele, my personal guru of alternative input devices, and someone who I knew had previously suffered with RSI. Dr Steele confirmed that my symptoms mirrored those that he had experienced some years previously, and prescribed a course of two tablets – one for home use and one for client sites.</p>
<p>The Wacom Bamboo is an excellent piece of kit, and reasonably priced compared to other tablets and decent mouses. But it does take quite some getting used to. There is a knack to moving the pen around <em>just</em> above the surface of the tablet – a gap small enough that the movement is perceived by the tablet (and the mouse cursor moves), but without actually touching the tablet (which leads to dragging-and-dropping). This is particularly problematic if you venture anywhere near Visual Studio’s Solution Explorer – it was quite embarrassing how many times I checked strange folder/file moves into source control in the early days of my Bamboo usage. This acted as a good lesson to steer clear of Solution Explorer and get into the habit of navigating using ReSharper instead!</p>
<p>Overall, it took me a good few months before I was as fast and accurate using the Bamboo as I was using a traditional mouse. This could be quite frustrating when I just wanted to get something done, and on a number of occasions The Wife snuck into my office and caught me of an evening, guiltily risking my health with an old VX Revolution. As with many things, perseverance is the key – having Bamboos at both home and work certainly helped. Over time the pain in my finger subsided and has now disappeared altogether.</p>
<p>Two specific tips if you’re thinking of giving the Wacom Bamboo a try for day-to-day computing use:</p>
<p>Firstly, be sure to configure the device to use “Mouse Mode” rather than the default “Pen Mode”. Mouse mode “moves the screen cursor with a ‘pick up and slide’ motion similar to using a traditional mouse”, whilst Pen mode “sets the cursor so that its movement corresponds with the position of your Bamboo pen on the tablet – wherever you place your pen on the tablet, the cursor will jump to a corresponding point on the screen.” In my experience, Pen mode led to the cursor jumping wildly around the screen unless I gave consideration to where on the tablet I was placing the pen – a very unnatural experience after many years of using a “traditional” mouse.</p>
<p>Secondly, I suggest mapping the lower button on the barrel of the pen to the “double-click” action, as trying to emulate a double-click by tapping the pen nib on the tablet twice in quick succession is awkward – a problem which compounds if you need to perform many double-clicks, such as navigating around a file hierarchy in Windows Explorer.</p>
<p>I mentioned a few years ago that <a href="https://blog.iannelson.uk/a-keyboard-makes-a-hell-of-a-difference/">a keyboard makes a hell of a difference</a> – well, it turns out that selection of secondary input devices can also make a huge difference to the long-term viability of a career, if you can invest the time to become proficient in their use.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Keyboard Makes A Hell Of A Difference</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/a-keyboard-makes-a-hell-of-a-difference/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2008 16:08:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/a-keyboard-makes-a-hell-of-a-difference/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It occurred to me recently that I’m not getting any younger, and that sitting hunched over a keyboard for a dozen hours a day will probably lead to some form of RSI sooner or later. So I started looking for ways to improve my daily working environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.johnsadventures.com/archives/2008/05/a-chair-makes-a-hell-of-a-difference.html&#34;&gt;John&lt;/a&gt;, I can’t afford a Herman Miller chair, and even if I could, I’m a freelancer rather than a telecommuter&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; so I would have to regularly carry the chair on the train to client sites, where they would probably ostracise me for being a weirdo who brings his own chair to the office. So I looked for something a little more portable, and decided that perhaps it was finally time for me to try one of those fancy split ergonomic keyboards that I’ve always scoffed at. After reading a few review on Amazon, I plumped for the &lt;a href=&#34;http://amzn.to/RPdDlW&#34;&gt;Microsoft Natural Ergonomic Keyboard 4000&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>It occurred to me recently that I’m not getting any younger, and that sitting hunched over a keyboard for a dozen hours a day will probably lead to some form of RSI sooner or later. So I started looking for ways to improve my daily working environment.</p>
<p>Unlike <a href="http://www.johnsadventures.com/archives/2008/05/a-chair-makes-a-hell-of-a-difference.html">John</a>, I can’t afford a Herman Miller chair, and even if I could, I’m a freelancer rather than a telecommuter<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> so I would have to regularly carry the chair on the train to client sites, where they would probably ostracise me for being a weirdo who brings his own chair to the office. So I looked for something a little more portable, and decided that perhaps it was finally time for me to try one of those fancy split ergonomic keyboards that I’ve always scoffed at. After reading a few review on Amazon, I plumped for the <a href="http://amzn.to/RPdDlW">Microsoft Natural Ergonomic Keyboard 4000</a>.</p>
<p>I should probably mention at this point that I’ve never been formally taught to type, and I don’t touch-type in the traditional way, with fingers sticking loyally around the ASDF JKL: keys. I’ve been more of an autodidact, typing quickly but inefficiently, a few finger dancing crazily around the keys whilst the others (notably my pinkies) float lazily in the air, dreaming of the time they were once called upon to pull a wishbone or contribute to a clenched fist.</p>
<p>This means that initially, I found adjusting to the layout of the ergonomic keyboard quite tough – I was slowed down, and had to relearn the relative positions of the keys. For a week or so, I only used the new keyboard at home, as it would have been too slow and frustrating for workaday use. But gradually I grew accustomed to it, and found that I appreciated being able to rest my palms on the wrist-rest, with fingers dropping down towards the keys courtesy of the reverse slope.</p>
<p>So, I took a further plunge, and bought a second keyboard to take to the office. A few months more have passed, and now I can’t imagine using anything else on a daily basis. It really is more comfortable, and my shoulders and arms feel considerably more relaxed. I’m also back up to the kind of wpm that achieved on a standard keyboard.</p>
<p>Other than the ergonomic design, the 4000 series boasts a few other features, some of which may appeal, depending on the kind of applications you frequently use:</p>
<p>Notably, all the function keys have been relabelled with additional functionality such as Undo, Redo, New, Open, Close, Spell, Save and Print. Depending on your mentality you will either find this incredibly useful or incredibly annoying (if you’re in the latter camp then you’ll be pleased to know that ordinary service can be resumed thanks to an “F Lock” key.</p>
<p>I am fond of the button which launches Calculator (one of my most often-launched applications), as well as the buttons to control volume and pause media player (which works fine with iTunes 7).</p>
<p>I also appreciate the additional four buttons above the numeric keypad – putting an extra equals, parentheses and backspace where you’ll find them most useful when working with a spreadsheet or similar</p>
<p>There are also buttons to launch a web browser, email application, navigate to a search engine, open favourites, navigate back and forth, a zoom control, and five customisable buttons – but to be honest I haven’t made use of any of these. YMMV.</p>
<p>So, in summary – having got past those difficult early “getting to know you” dates, I now foresee a long and happy relationship with the 4000 series. And I’m sure my shoulders will be happy to hear that.</p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>does anybody say “telecommuter” these days?  It sounds very 1996…&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
