<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Books of the Year on Ian Nelson</title>
    <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/series/books-of-the-year/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Books of the Year on Ian Nelson</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.146.6</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 26 Apr 2025 22:03:15 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://blog.iannelson.uk/series/books-of-the-year/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The Books I Most Enjoyed Reading in 2024</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/the-books-i-most-enjoyed-reading-in-2024/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Dec 2024 16:31:33 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/the-books-i-most-enjoyed-reading-in-2024/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Cover of Burn Book by Cara Swisher&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; src=&#34;https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2024/12/BurnBook.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As 2024 draws to a close, I’ve taken some time to reflect on the books that made the greatest impact on me this year. From deep dives into technology and politics to introspective reads on life and risk, these are the titles that enriched my year – and might just enrich yours too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you pressed me on the subject, I would say that my very favourite book of 2024 was &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://amzn.to/3DcUiXT&#34;&gt;Burn Book: A Tech Love Story&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; by veteran tech journalist Kara Swisher.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img alt="Cover of Burn Book by Cara Swisher" loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2024/12/BurnBook.jpg"></p>
<p>As 2024 draws to a close, I’ve taken some time to reflect on the books that made the greatest impact on me this year. From deep dives into technology and politics to introspective reads on life and risk, these are the titles that enriched my year – and might just enrich yours too.</p>
<p>If you pressed me on the subject, I would say that my very favourite book of 2024 was <strong><a href="https://amzn.to/3DcUiXT">Burn Book: A Tech Love Story</a></strong> by veteran tech journalist Kara Swisher.</p>
<p>2024 marks thirty years since I first “got on the internet” when I was studying at university. I started out sending emails and browsing <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Usenet">Usenet</a> using <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pine_%28email_client%29">PINE</a>, then had my world turned upside down when <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NCSA_Mosaic">NCSA Mosaic</a> and the first versions of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Netscape_Navigator">Netscape Navigator</a> allowed me to start surfing the web. Since then I’ve been lucky enough to follow an enjoyable career building distributed software systems that rely on the internet.</p>
<p>During this same period, Kara Swisher has covered that ever-changing technology sector for outlets including <em>The Washington Post</em>, <em>The Wall Street Journal</em> and <em>The New York Times</em>. <em>Burn Book</em> is a sharp, irreverent critique of the technology industry, blending memoir, satire and journalism. It delivers a candid account of tech’s rise to dominance and its often-problematic relationship with power, ethics, and accountability. Swisher doesn’t shy away from naming names, offering unfiltered takes on figures such as Elon Musk, Mark Zuckerberg, Steve Jobs, Bill Gates, Jeff Bezos, and many others. There is a wealth of great anecdotes here, and no small amount of disdain for many of the man-child Silicon Valley tech bros who have changed our world so completely over the last thirty years.</p>
<p>My favourite technical book of the year was the second edition of <a href="https://amzn.to/3BtC6su"><strong>Building Microservices: Designing Fine-Grained Systems</strong></a> by Sam Newman, who I had the pleasure of learning from when I attended his two-day Microservices workshop at <a href="https://blog.iannelson.uk/ndc-porto-2024/">NDC Porto 2024</a> in October. Although ostensibly focused on Microservices, this 600-page tome offers plenty of good advice that applies more broadly to the design, implementation, and operation of any modern software system. Newman writes engagingly, backing up his candid opinions with case studies and offering concrete advice wherever possible. Highly recommended.</p>
<p>Away from the code face, I’ve appreciated the insights into effective technical leadership that I have gained from two complementary books <strong><a href="https://amzn.to/3OWqYHN">Staff Engineer: Leadership Beyond the Management Track</a></strong> by Will Larson and <a href="https://amzn.to/41GcH9w"><strong>The Staff Engineer’s Path: A Guide for Individual Contributors Navigating Growth and Change</strong></a> by Tanya Reilly. Both offer plenty of practical advice and insights for anyone in (or aspiring to enter) a “Staff Plus” role.</p>
<h2 id="politics">Politics</h2>
<p>I spent some of my early summer weekends accumulating blisters as I walked the local streets delivering campaign material to help re-elect our excellent local MP Keir Mather. For background encouragement I did this while listening to the audiobook of <a href="https://amzn.to/4grzt9D"><strong>This Time No Mistakes: How to Remake Britain</strong></a> by Will Hutton. It is a wide-ranging treatise covering over a century of political history on both sides of the Atlantic and attributes the UK’s current political and economic challenges to persistent adherence to free-market ideologies and minimal state intervention over the past 45 years. Drawing inspiration from early 20th-century New Liberalism and the post-1945 Labour government, Hutton advocates for a blend of ethical socialism and progressive liberalism, which he refers to as the “We Society”, balancing individual aspirations with collective welfare. Occasionally I found this a little too dry and worthy for my liking, with the recounted historical events seeming far removed from current day politics. But generally it kept me inspired and motivated, particularly in the more forward-looking sections that offered a manifesto for change.</p>
<p><img alt="Cover of One Boy, Two Bills and a Fry-Up by Wes Streeting" loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2024/12/WesStreeting.jpg"></p>
<p>My favourite book by a politician this year was only tangentially about politics. <strong><a href="https://amzn.to/3D7fH4L">One Boy, Two Bills and a Fry-Up: A Memoir of Growing Up and Getting On</a></strong> is an engaging memoir by current Health Secretary Wes Streeting, recounting his experiences growing up in poverty with teenage parents who struggled to make ends meet. Despite the hardships faced, Streeting highlights the love and support from his family, and also the opportunities afforded to him by impactful teachers, ultimately leading to attending Cambridge University and embarking on a career in politics. Streeting wears his heart on his sleeve, making for a very personal memoir that offers human-centric vignettes into the factors that shaped his ideology.</p>
<h2 id="money-and-risk">Money and Risk</h2>
<p>I read a second autobiography this summer by another boy from a modest upbringing in East London who made a better life for himself, though this one followed a very different path from that of the Health Secretary. <strong><a href="https://amzn.to/49v70NU">The Trading Game: A Confession</a></strong> by Gary Stevenson details the author’s ascent to become a leading trader at Citibank, working on the Short-Term Interest Rate Trading desks in London and later Tokyo. The memoir delves into the opulent yet morally ambiguous lifestyle of high finance, exposing systemic flaws and the widening wealth gap in the years that followed the 2007-8 global financial crisis. Despite his success, Stevenson grappled with the ethical implications of profiting from the economic downturns that adversely affected the less affluent, and he has since become an advocate for economic equality, using his platform to educate the public on financial disparities. I didn’t particularly relish the chapters describing bankers’ hedonism, but I was fascinated by later sections detailing the corporate games played by Citibank as Stevenson sought to leave the organisation.</p>
<p>Most of us will never have the levels of money that bring the kind of ethical dilemmas faced by Gary Stevenson. For the rest of us, advice on how to manage our own more modest finances can be found in <strong><a href="https://amzn.to/4ismC90">The Psychology of Money: Timeless lessons on wealth, greed, and happiness</a></strong> by Morgan Housel. Housel argues that financial success and security is not necessarily linked to intelligence or mathematical skill but to understanding human nature and managing emotions like greed, fear, and envy. The book is written in a conversational and approachable style, combining research with 19 short stories emphasising that managing money well requires understanding yourself and your relationship with money.</p>
<p>In a similar vein, <strong><a href="https://amzn.to/3P596L3">On the Edge: The Art of Risking Everything</a></strong> by Nate Silver digs into the psyche and strategies of individuals who thrive in high-stakes environments, from poker players to venture capitalists. He introduces the concept of “The River”, representing a community of analytical, independent-minded and risk tolerant individuals, and contrasts it with “The Village,” symbolising risk-averse, conventional thinkers. There is a huge amount of information in this book about gambling, particularly poker, which rekindled some of my interest in the game theory branch of mathematics. There are also some fascinating chapters recounting Silver’s meetings with Sam Bankman-Fried during the tumultuous period following cryptocurrency exchange FTX’s collapse and preceding his incarceration. It’s clear that Bankman-Fried had a very different relationship with risk than most of us, and this serves as a cautionary tale, illustrating the perils of risk-taking without understanding the potential consequences.</p>
<p><img alt="Cover of Around the World in 80 Games by Marcus du Sautoy" loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2024/12/Games.jpg"></p>
<p>Game-playing and risk-taking without the potential for such life-changing consequences is the subject of <strong><a href="https://amzn.to/4f5YtSD">Around the World in 80 Games</a></strong> by British mathematician Marcus du Sautoy. The Jules Verne-inspired narrative circumnavigates the globe and explores a diverse array of games, from ancient board games like the Royal Game of Ur to contemporary favourite such as Settlers of Catan. It considers the cultural significance of games, and the roles they play in different societies, in addition to investigating the mathematical concepts underpinning these games, including probability, game theory and combinatorics. Du Sautoy also explores what makes games fun and interesting, captivating players into wishing for just one more turn (<em>e.g. Wingspan</em>, <em>Ticket To Ride</em>) compared to those that can drag on interminably and lead to boredom and resentment (<em>Monopoly</em>). In 2024 I have very much appreciated the fact that my children are of an age where they are able and willing to play decent games like <em>7 Wonders</em>, <em>Darwin’s Journey</em> and <em>Everdell</em> with me, and found Du Sautoy’s book to offer pleasing insights into why we find these games so enjoyable.</p>
<h2 id="fiction">Fiction</h2>
<p>As is usually the case, I read more non-fiction than fiction during the year. On the few occasions that I did pick up a novel, it seems I have been drawn to those featuring rather flawed protagonists, to say the least. <strong><a href="https://amzn.to/3OKIajp">American Psycho</a></strong> by Bret Easton Ellis was, in retrospect, perhaps not the most relaxing choice of audiobook to accompany my January commutes on the congested roads of Leeds City Centre. The novel is infamous for its explicit and shocking depictions of ultra-violence, but I was more intrigued by its lengthy and monotonous monologues on 1980s bands, stereo systems, and skincare routines.</p>
<p><img alt="Cover of We Need to Talk About Kevin by Lionel Shriver" loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2024/12/Kevin.jpg"></p>
<p>In the summer months (now commuting by train) I listened to the short but harrowing psychological novel <strong><a href="https://amzn.to/3Vsg8Nm">We Need to Talk About Kevin</a></strong> by Lionel Shriver. Told through a series of letters written by Eva Katchadourian to her estranged husband Franklin, the story explores Eva’s attempt to make sense of their teenage son Kevin’s horrifying act of violence – a school massacre he commits shortly before his 16th birthday. The novel is a chilling and fascinating exploration of parental responsibility, societal violence, and complexities of love and blame.</p>
<p>Finally, wrapping up a triptych of novels featuring notable and troubled anti-heroes, I read <strong><a href="https://amzn.to/3ZHMqXa">Lolita</a></strong> by Vladimir Nabokov later in the year. The unreliable narrator Humbert Humbert is charming and eloquent, seducing the reader with his wit and intellect, even as he recounts his abhorrent exploitation of a young girl. I did not realise before I began reading this book that it was originally written in English, despite Nabokov’s Russian heritage. The intricate wordplay, subtleties, and cultural references are beguiling, and I frequently felt compelled to highlight words or phrases on my Kindle for later recall. It was also a delight to recognise many turns of phrase and imagery from the lyrics of one of my favourite songs, <em>Lolita Elle</em> by ’90s band <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jack_%28band%29">Jack</a>. American imagery from Humbert and Lolita’s road trip across the United States also evoked my memories of our summer holiday driving in Utah and Nevada.</p>
<p>While visiting the States this summer, I spent the hot Nevadan evenings sitting in the shade in my mother-in-law’s courtyard reading <a href="https://amzn.to/3VtXJQi"><strong>London Fields</strong></a> by Martin Amis. I had previously tried reading Amis in my early twenties, encouraged to do so by my intellectual and more literary-minded housemate Hugh. But at the time I found Amis’s prose to be dense and challenging, and it said little to me about my life at the time (back then I preferred the lighter <em>fin de siècle</em> ennui of Douglas Coupland). But on returning to Amis’ “London Trilogy” in my forties, I find myself relishing these dark satires of modern life, the deeply flawed characters, and the way that the cities of London and New York symbolise both opportunity and corruption. Most of all I love the gloriously esoteric words and the lovingly-crafted sentences, many of which I again highlighted on my Kindle. Having re-read <a href="https://amzn.to/4f5i3ym"><strong>Money</strong></a> in 2018 and <em>London Fields</em> this year, I plan to revisit <a href="https://amzn.to/49vBMWH"><strong>The Information</strong></a> in 2025.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>People? People are chaotic quiddities living in one cave each. They pass the hours in amorous grudge and playback and thought-experiment. At the camp fire they put the usual fraction on exhibit, and listen to their own silent gibber about how they’re feeling and how they’re going down. We’ve been there.</p>
<p>— Martin Amis, London Fields</p></blockquote>
<h2 id="music">Music</h2>
<p><img alt="Cover of Deliver Me From Nowhere by Warren Zanes" loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2024/12/Nowehre.jpg"></p>
<p>My favourite music book of the year was <strong><a href="https://amzn.to/4g8pTsw">Deliver Me From Nowhere: The Making of Bruce Springsteen’s Nebraska</a></strong> by Warren Zanes. In contrast to the rock autobiographies by Bono, Jarvis Cocker, and Dave Grohl that have graced my year-end blog post in recent years and which contain a wide-range of anecdotes, Zanes’ book focuses on one specific recording. The <em>Nebraska</em> LP, recorded solo on a four-track cassette recorder in a New Jersey bedroom, was a stark departure from Springsteen’s earlier, more grandiose works. It showcased a raw, introspective side, and featured narratives of violence, despair, and existential contemplation. Zanes is a true fan and diligent researcher, who through interviews with Springsteen and others explores how <em>Nebraska</em> challenged industry norms and left a lasting impact on music, paving the way for future generations of lo-fi and indie rock artists to produce music in their bedrooms. For a broader read, I also enjoyed <strong><a href="https://amzn.to/4g1s8gR">R.E.M. Album by Album</a></strong> by Max Pilley, a comprehensive retrospective of the thirty-year recording career of one of my favourite bands. This featured many facts and insights into the band and music that I wasn’t previously aware of, and led to me streaming their LPs with fresh ears, not unlike the impact that <em>Revolution In The Head</em> by Ian McDonald once had upon my appreciation of The Beatles’ recordings.</p>
<h2 id="life-and-how-to-live-it">Life and How to Live It</h2>
<p><img alt="Cover of Fluke by Brian Klaas" loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2024/12/fluke.jpg"></p>
<p><strong><a href="https://amzn.to/4iMM5Kq">Fluke: Chance, Chaos, and Why Everything We Do Matters</a></strong> by Dr. Brian Klaas explores the influence of randomness and chaos on human lives and decision-making. Klaas examines how small, seemingly insignificant events – flukes – can cascade into pivotal moments, shaping the course of history, politics, and personal trajectories.</p>
<p>The book examines topics like the butterfly effect, exploring how initial conditions can lead to wildly unpredictable outcomes, and the role of luck versus skill in success and failure. Klaas uses vivid anecdotes from history, science, and contemporary life to demonstrate how randomness interacts with human agency, often creating illusions of control where none exists.</p>
<p>Despite acknowledging the pervasive role of chance, this book ultimately offers a hopeful perspective: while randomness is unavoidable, our actions still matter. By understanding the mechanics of chaos and probability, we can better navigate uncertainty, make informed decisions, and cultivate resilience. There was a lot to take in here; much food for thought, and it’s one of the books from 2024 that I would definitely consider reading again in an attempt to digest the salient and actionable points.</p>
<p>One of the books mentioned in my <a href="https://blog.iannelson.uk/the-books-i-most-enjoyed-reading-in-2021/">2021 post</a> was <em>Four Thousand Weeks: Time And How to Use It by Oliver Burkeman</em>. He has returned with the follow-up <strong><a href="https://amzn.to/4iPT45p">Meditations for Mortals: Four Weeks to Embrace Your Limitations and Make Time for What Counts</a></strong>, and I’ve found it to be even more inspirational and actionable than the previous book. It is structured as a four-week “mental retreat” of daily meditations, centred around the topics of “Being Finite”, “Taking Action”, “Letting Go” and “Showing Up”. As someone who often struggles to decide what to do with my free time, and has been trying to find more efficient “algorithms to live by” for many years, I took great comfort from some of the poignant and reflective advice in the short chapters in this book, which is excellently researched and includes plenty of source citations to further reading. The “index of afflictions” at the back of the book is also a helpful resource.</p>
<p><img alt="Cover of Slow Productivity by Cal Newport" loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2024/12/Productivity.jpg"></p>
<p>I have thoroughly enjoyed all of Professor Cal Newport’s books, but his latest work, <strong><a href="https://amzn.to/3VDYTca">Slow Productivity: The Lost Art of Accomplishment without Burnout</a></strong> is my favourite to date, and is unsurprisingly focused, as you would expect from a book that exhorts us to do fewer things and obsess over quality. Newport highlights the unfortunate rise of performative busywork in modern corporate culture, and the negative impact that this has had on the creation of quality outputs. It goes on to suggest strategies and tactics that knowledge workers and others with a reasonable degree of autonomy in their jobs can use to live more fulfilling lives and produce higher-quality work. Alas, it does come with the caveat that many people who work in an office environment under close supervision might have a hard time fully instituting the strategies suggested: there will always be employers and clients who prioritise bureaucracy and infantilising processes over genuine productivity. But it offers the prospect of better ways of working to those who can do so, and I am hopeful that these ideas will spread across the corporate world as the benefits of their adoption are seen.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Do fewer things.<br>
Work at a natural pace.<br>
Obsess over quality.</p>
<p>— Cal Newport, Slow Productivity</p></blockquote>
<p>In 2024 I read more books than usual by reducing the amount of mainstream news media and social media that I consumed. I found this to be a more rewarding balance and it had a positive effect of my mental health. Yet even reading just one quality national newspaper per week left me with the impression that the world was going to hell in a hand cart, and by October I deliberately sought out a book to read that would offer some optimism. I found it in <strong><a href="https://amzn.to/4iA8f2a">Humankind: A Hopeful History</a></strong> by Rutger Bregman, a thought-provoking exploration of human nature that challenges the assumption that humans are fundamentally selfish and driven by greed.</p>
<p>Bregman’s central thesis is that humans are, by nature, “Homo puppy” – inherently friendly, cooperative, and capable of incredible kindness. He invites readers to adopt a more optimistic lens on humanity, rejecting cynicism and building systems that empower our better angels. I particularly enjoyed the sections of the book where Bregman’s fresh research debunked iconic studies like the Stanford Prison Experiment and Milgram Experiment, revealing flaws in their methodology and reporting. The book is a mixture of rigorous research and engaging anecdotes that offers a call to action to reimagine our social structures and advocates for policies such as Universal Basic Income, which assume the best in people and trust individuals to act responsibly.</p>
<h2 id="our-world">Our World</h2>
<p><img alt="Cover of Not the End of the World by Hannah Ritchie" loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2024/12/nottheend-1.jpg"></p>
<p>Similarly optimistic was the excellent <strong><a href="https://amzn.to/3ZUkI9R">Not the End of the World: How We Can Be the First Generation to Build a Sustainable Planet</a></strong> by Dr Hannah Ritchie. This data-driven exploration of the environmental challenges facing the planet was very reminiscent of <em>Factfulness: Ten Reasons We’re Wrong About The World – And Why Things Are Better Than You Think</em> by the late Swedish academic Hans Rosling. It challenges common misconceptions, scrutinising the actual impact of actions like eating locally and the true environmental costs of materials such as plastic. Ritchie emphasises that, contrary to pervasive doomsday narratives, we have the potential to achieve true sustainability for the first time in history.</p>
<p>If Ritchie’s work relies on accurate data to draw conclusions, what are the impacts on public policy when data is non-existent, inaccurate or misleading? That is the subject of <strong><a href="https://amzn.to/49z9F9j">Bad Data: How Governments, Politicians and the Rest of Us Get Misled by Numbers</a></strong> by Georgina Sturge, a statistician at the House of Commons Library. The book dives into the murky waters of official statistics, revealing how data – often assumed to be the bedrock of informed policy-making – is riddled with inconsistencies, guesswork, and uncertainties. It offers insightful analysis and engaging storytelling through a series of compelling narratives, which often served to provoke and anger me in a manner not dissimilar to that of <em>Invisible Women: Exposing Data Bias in a World Designed for Men</em> by Caroline Criado Perez, which featured in my <a href="https://blog.iannelson.uk/20-books-i-most-enjoyed-reading-in-2019/">blog post of 2019</a>.</p>
<p>Another book on public policy that got me angry and worked up in 2024 was <strong><a href="https://amzn.to/3ZAFkm3">The Big Con: How the Consulting Industry Weakens our Businesses, Infantilises our Governments and Warps our Economies</a></strong> by Mariana Mazzucato and Rosie Collington. Through a series of case studies it critiques how large consulting firms have entrenched themselves as indispensable advisors while simultaneously undermining the very organisations they serve. Exhaustively highlighting the dependency culture, short-termism and lack of accountability that inevitably arises, the book calls for a reevaluation of the consulting industry’s role in modern organisations and governments. It advocates for rebuilding in-house expertise and fostering a culture of long-term value creation, rather than outsourcing core functions to external advisors.</p>
<p><img alt="Cover of Material World by Ed Conway" loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2024/12/materialworld.jpg"></p>
<p>My favourite science book of the year was <strong><a href="https://amzn.to/49BEM40">Material World: A Substantial Story of Our Past and Future</a></strong> by Ed Conway, the economics editor for Sky News. He focuses on six fundamental materials – sand, salt, iron, copper, oil, and lithium – that have been instrumental in shaping human civilisation, and continue to be important for all our futures. The book highlights the many ways that these materials underpin modern life: sand is essential for silicon chips, iron and copper are foundational to construction and electrical infrastructure, and lithium is vital for contemporary battery technologies. The context of the transition to renewable energy sources and the demand that it will place on our consumption of these materials weighs heavily on the narrative.</p>
<p>We have come full circle. My books round-up blog post for 2024 ends on the same topic that it began – the impact of new technologies. If the technological changes that we have seen over the last 30 years have been remarkable, they are nothing compared to those that we are about to witness over the coming decades. <strong><a href="https://amzn.to/4fhPXzR">The Coming Wave: Technology, Power and the Twenty-First Century’s Greatest Dilemma</a></strong> by DeepMind co-founder Mustafa Suleyman covers the transformative impact of emerging technologies such as artificial intelligence (AI), synthetic biology and quantum computing on society. It explores how those technological advancements could lead to immense prosperity while simultaneously posing enormous threats to global order and individual freedoms. Notably, Suleyman highlights the “containment problem”, arguing for proactive measures by nation states to strike a balance between innovation and potential catastrophe. At a time when the full potential of technologies such as ChatGPT and synthetic biology have not yet been grasped by the majority, <em>The Coming Wave</em> offers an urgent wake-up call. An important read.</p>
<p>Thank you for reading this far! Wishing you a peaceful Christmas, and here’s to much more reading in 2025.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Books I Most Enjoyed Reading in 2023</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/the-books-i-most-enjoyed-reading-in-2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Dec 2023 15:40:15 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/the-books-i-most-enjoyed-reading-in-2023/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;politics-on-the-edge-a-memoir-from-within-by-rory-stewart&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://amzn.to/41sIGYS&#34;&gt;Politics on the Edge: A Memoir from Within&lt;/a&gt; by Rory Stewart&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My very favourite book of 2023 was this autobiography by former Minister and one-time candidate for Conservative Party leader Rory Stewart. I almost didn’t read it at all, as I was feeling a little jaded with politics at the time and considering a more light-hearted Audible purchase. I’m glad I plumped for this though, and it did offer some light relief in the form of Stewart’s dodgy accents when recounting conversations with fellow politicians of all parties and nationalities.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="politics-on-the-edge-a-memoir-from-within-by-rory-stewart"><a href="https://amzn.to/41sIGYS">Politics on the Edge: A Memoir from Within</a> by Rory Stewart</h2>
<p>My very favourite book of 2023 was this autobiography by former Minister and one-time candidate for Conservative Party leader Rory Stewart. I almost didn’t read it at all, as I was feeling a little jaded with politics at the time and considering a more light-hearted Audible purchase. I’m glad I plumped for this though, and it did offer some light relief in the form of Stewart’s dodgy accents when recounting conversations with fellow politicians of all parties and nationalities.</p>
<p>There is no flab in this book, it ploughs on at quite a fast pace through Stewart’s political career, from becoming MP for Penrith and the Border in 2010 through to his run for leader of the Conservative Party (and Prime Minister) less than a decade later. In between he is thrust with no notice into a variety of ministerial positions for which he has varying degrees of suitability and aptitude. In my <a href="https://blog.iannelson.uk/20-books-i-most-enjoyed-reading-in-2019/">2019 books blog post</a> I recommended the drier <em><a href="https://amzn.to/3GJZdOu">Why We Get the Wrong Politicians</a></em> by Isabel Hardman, in which she outlined why the failings of our ministerial system lead to roles being filled by individuals who are unsuited to them. Stewart’s book brings colourful examples of that theory, but to his credit he makes efforts to master the briefs he is given and make a practical difference to the country. Others from his party, particularly our recent Prime Ministers, are not always painted in a positive light, and he gives many interesting insights into their personalities.</p>
<p><img alt="Politics on the Edge cover" loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2023/12/51btunBtJEL._SL500_.jpg"></p>
<h2 id="tomorrow-and-tomorrow-and-tomorrow-by-gabrielle-zevin"><a href="https://amzn.to/3tl4c54">Tomorrow, and Tomorrow, and Tomorrow</a> by Gabrielle Zevin</h2>
<p>In 2023 I rediscovered the pleasure of playing computer games, eighteen years after writing a fairly grumpy blog post in which I declared that “<a href="https://blog.iannelson.uk/computer-games-i-have-loved/">The whole concept seemed utterly pointless, a real waste of time</a>“. A spring break between contracts coincided with the release of <em>Zelda: Tears of the Kingdom</em>, which I bought on a whim after stumbling across <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/games/2023/may/11/the-legend-of-zelda-tears-of-the-kingdom-review-pure-magic">Keza MacDonald’s effusive five-star review in <em>The Guardian</em></a>. Since then I’ve spent 167 hours playing that wonderful game, and have also relaxed by playing <em><a href="https://www.theguardian.com/games/2020/jul/22/creaks-review-a-darkly-surreal-puzzle-game">Creaks</a></em> on Apple Arcade and <em><a href="https://returntomonkeyisland.com/">Return to Monkey Island</a></em> (32 years after playing the original on the Amiga).</p>
<p>It was with this background that I that I read <em>Tomorrow, and Tomorrow, and Tomorrow</em> towards the end of the year. It’s a novel set over several decades about two friends who collaborate to develop and publish increasingly epic computer games whilst navigating romances, friendship, fallouts, family, health challenges, and other life-changing events. It’s very touching and heartfelt, and caused me to think about the value of play in our lives, and of maintaining friendships over extended periods.</p>
<p><img alt="Tomorrow, and Tomorrow, and Tomorrow cover" loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2023/12/51oi2QWxV-L._SL500_.jpg"></p>
<h2 id="surrender-40-songs-one-story-by-bono"><a href="https://amzn.to/3RpmslV">Surrender: 40 Songs, One Story</a> by Bono</h2>
<p>Faced with a “to-read” list that now numbers into the seventies, I made a point of actively abandoning some books that I was not enjoying during 2023, rather than struggling through them to the bitter end. As my wife Jocelyn is fond of reminding me, life is too short to read books that you’re not enjoying. Cognisant of my maturing years and the theories of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Optimal_stopping">Optimal Stopping</a>, I’ve also tended to stick to favourite genres this year rather than trying something new.</p>
<p>So, given that I enjoy biographies, and also enjoy books on rock music, Bono’s autobiography was always destined to be high on my list of favourite reads for the year. It covers U2’s lengthy career from their early schooldays in Dublin through to being the biggest band in the world, releasing classic zeitgeist-defining records including <em>The Joshua Tree</em> and <em>Achtung Baby</em>. There is an impressive cast of supporting characters mentioned in the many anecdotes in this book, including Pope John Paul II, Bill Clinton, Tony Blair, Frank Sinatra, and countless others. At one point Mikhail Gorbachev pops in for tea on a Sunday afternoon.</p>
<p><img alt="Surrender cover" loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2023/12/513jMRpuapL._SL500_.jpg"></p>
<h2 id="a-visit-from-the-goon-squad-and-the-candy-house-by-jennifer-egan"><a href="https://amzn.to/3v44ttO">A Visit from the Goon Squad</a> and <a href="https://amzn.to/3GKSLXt">The Candy House</a> by Jennifer Egan</h2>
<p>These two books were released in 2010 and 2022 respectively, and feature interrelated stories with a large set of characters, set over multiple decades. Many of the central characters work in the rock music industry, and there are themes here of friendship, aging, and loss of innocence. The first book (which won a Pulitzer Prize) is probably the better one, but the audiobook of the second has better production qualities, with each POV character being narrated by a different professional voice artist. The second book also bursts with inspired ideas about where the ubiquity of social media might take us as a society.</p>
<p><img alt="A Visit from the Goon Squad and The Candy House covers" loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2023/12/51ft9c8NwIL._SL500_.jpg"></p>
<h2 id="one-two-three-four-the-beatles-in-time-by-craig-brown"><a href="https://amzn.to/3GJPuHY">One Two Three Four: The Beatles In Time</a> by Craig Brown</h2>
<p>A huge book comprised of many short and easily-digestible chapters that occupied much of my summer vacation. Craig Brown somehow takes a subject, The Beatles, about whom so very much has been written over the last sixty years and offers fresh perspectives and anecdotes. I laughed a lot and found myself sharing passages with family and friends. Definitely one of the most enjoyable biographies I’ve ever read and, along with <em><a href="https://amzn.to/485xpAb">Revolution in the Head</a></em> by Ian MacDonald, one of the best books about The Beatles.</p>
<p><img alt="One Two Three Four cover" loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2023/12/51YSVa5TYRL._SL500_.jpg"></p>
<h2 id="the-nanny-state-made-me-a-story-of-britain-and-how-to-save-it-and-the-full-english-a-journey-in-search-of-a-country-and-its-people-by-stuart-maconie"><a href="https://amzn.to/41nwyZb">The Nanny State Made Me: A Story of Britain and How to Save It</a> and <a href="https://amzn.to/3RrgyAT">The Full English: A Journey in Search of a Country and its People</a> by Stuart Maconie</h2>
<p>Two books by DJ Stuart Maconie make my list of favourites this year. <em>The Nanny State Made Me</em> iterates through stages in Maconie’s life, highlighting how at each point the welfare state in the UK provided him with the necessary support to become a useful and productive member of society. As with most Maconie books the politics is interspersed with an abundance of cultural references, and this helped to boost my “to watch”/”to listen” lists.</p>
<p>In <em>The Full English</em>, Maconie retraces a journey through England originally taken by J.B.Priestley in his travelogue <em><a href="https://amzn.to/3Ny8YmJ">English Journey</a></em> in 1934, comparing and contrasting how the nation has changed in the intervening decades. Despite acknowledging that there is much that needs improving in England, there is also a love and sentimentality for the nation in evidence here. I was surprised to learn that Maconie’s father used to work for the same now-defunct manufacturer that employed my own Dad, so felt quite connected to those passages. I was also amused to hear him, as a proud Lancastrian, extol the virtues of Ilkley and admit that he could conceive of living there.</p>
<h2 id="the-anthropocene-reviewed-by-john-green"><a href="https://amzn.to/41xLLac">The Anthropocene Reviewed</a> by John Green</h2>
<p>In this series of essays adapted from his podcast, novelist John Green reviews and rates things as diverse as sunsets, Diet Dr Pepper, the song <em>New Partner</em> by Palace Music, the Indianapolis 500, Halley’s Comet and the QWERTY keyboard. Many of these pieces were written with the backdrop of the 2020-2021 COVID-19 pandemic, but the inevitable ensuing introspection does not result in morbidity, instead conveying hope and wonder at how miraculous the universe is. I give <em>The Anthropocene Reviewed</em> four stars.</p>
<h2 id="white-noise-by-don-delillo"><a href="https://amzn.to/3NsklfW">White Noise</a> by Don DeLillo</h2>
<p>The oldest book on my list this year, <em>White Noise</em> was written in 1985. Some of the characters and events depicted seemed oddly familiar – maybe it’s deja vu, but I can’t preclude having read this book previously and forgotten having done so!</p>
<p>I enjoyed this more than <em><a href="https://amzn.to/3v59G4D">Great Jones Street</a></em>, also by DeLillo, which I read in 2019 but which didn’t make my annual blog post that year. It is written in the first person from the POV of the protagonist, a male middle-aged college professor in a sleepy American town who has developed the field of “Hitler Studies”. Despite being almost forty years old, it covers themes of consumer culture, academia and mortality which remain relevant.</p>
<h2 id="the-storyteller-tales-of-life-and-music-by-dave-grohl"><a href="https://amzn.to/41pOSkg">The Storyteller: Tales of Life and Music</a> by Dave Grohl</h2>
<p>Another rock autobiography, and a brilliant collection of stories. Dave Grohl comes across as a very humble and lucky individual who can’t quite believe his good fortune at being a driving force behind some of the most successful bands in the world. There is an ordinariness to Grohl’s tales that is quite striking when compared to Bono’s book. Extended passages and chapters are given over to (surprisingly entertaining) anecdotes about losing a wallet at a gas station, or shopping for toys with his daughters. Yes, there’s a cast of famous names – Paul McCartney pops round to play the piano – but it’s all so natural and down to earth that you can’t begrudge Grohl his good fortune.</p>
<p><img alt="The Storyteller cover" loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2023/12/51YPIMud0eL._SL500_.jpg"></p>
<h2 id="atonement-by-ian-mcewan"><a href="https://amzn.to/3Nxs9gy">Atonement</a> by Ian McEwan</h2>
<p>I knew nothing about the plot of this novel before I started reading it; I certainly hadn’t seen the 2007 movie adaptation. I don’t consider myself to generally be a fan of historical novels, preferring those set within my own lifetime. But I found this to have terrific pace and well-drawn characters, and devoured it over the course of a weekend in May.</p>
<p><img alt="Atonement cover" loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2023/12/61KR-RUCUDL._SL500_.jpg"></p>
<h2 id="a-philosophy-of-software-design-by-john-ousterhout"><a href="https://amzn.to/3NwrFXM">A Philosophy of Software Design</a> by John Ousterhout</h2>
<p>Most of the tech books that I read in 2023 were focused on specific technologies, as I moved on from a much-loved five-year contract at NHS Digital and had to grok an unfamiliar tech stack. This delightful and relatively short book was one of the only tech-agnostic software books that I read, and I wish that it had been available to me much earlier in my career.</p>
<p>Ousterhout writes engagingly about complex software design topics, offering opinions and philosophies for an approach to development that can sometimes be at odds with that espoused in the better-known <em>Clean Code</em> by Robert Martin. I know that I won’t follow all of the advice given in this philosophy (I’ve never been a fan of code comments, for instance), but have taken to heart chapters on writing general purpose modules, and “different layer, different abstraction”.</p>
<p>As I write this I note that it is flagged on Amazon as being one of the “Most Gifted” books in the Software Design genre, and that doesn’t surprise me – it’s a book that I would like those who I collaborate with to have read and absorbed.</p>
<h2 id="why-is-this-lying-bastard-lying-to-me-searching-for-the-truth-on-political-tv-by-rob-burley"><a href="https://amzn.to/3NqNk3B">Why Is This Lying Bastard Lying To Me? Searching for the Truth on Political TV</a> by Rob Burley</h2>
<p>Rob Burley is a TV producer who has worked on and edited many of the top political shows on the BBC and ITV. In this entertaining and irreverent book he dissects what makes for a great political interview, and relives many memorable moments from Sunday morning political programmes, particularly covering recent years since the Brexit referendum.</p>
<p><img alt="Why Is This Lying Bastard Lying To Me? cover" loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2023/12/51TV9w6U8L._SL500_.jpg"></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The 20 Books I Most Enjoyed Reading in 2022</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/the-20-books-i-most-enjoyed-reading-in-2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Dec 2022 20:22:49 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/the-20-books-i-most-enjoyed-reading-in-2022/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-top-5.wp-block-heading&#34;&gt;The Top 5&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;stolen-focus-why-you-cant-pay-attention-by-johann-hari.wp-block-heading&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://amzn.to/3hZsGL5&#34;&gt;Stolen Focus: Why You Can’t Pay Attention&lt;/a&gt; by Johann Hari&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My favourite book of the year &lt;em&gt;partially&lt;/em&gt; covers the same ground as previous favourites &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://amzn.to/3v0oxtC&#34;&gt;A World Without Email&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://amzn.to/3WgPFAm&#34;&gt;Four Thousand Weeks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://amzn.to/3v07N60&#34;&gt;Ten Arguments for Deleting Your Social Media Accounts Right Now&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. But the scope of Hari’s work is much broader than these. Rather than merely telling us to stop doomscrolling Twitter and get on with life, he covers a multiplicity of factors and forces that are combining to steal the ability of many of us to focus. Social media, pollution, lack of sleep, poor diet, overwork and more are all discussed, with many pointers to third-party research.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="the-top-5.wp-block-heading">The Top 5</h2>
<h3 id="stolen-focus-why-you-cant-pay-attention-by-johann-hari.wp-block-heading"><a href="https://amzn.to/3hZsGL5">Stolen Focus: Why You Can’t Pay Attention</a> by Johann Hari</h3>
<p>My favourite book of the year <em>partially</em> covers the same ground as previous favourites <em><a href="https://amzn.to/3v0oxtC">A World Without Email</a></em>, <em><a href="https://amzn.to/3WgPFAm">Four Thousand Weeks</a></em>, and <em><a href="https://amzn.to/3v07N60">Ten Arguments for Deleting Your Social Media Accounts Right Now</a></em>. But the scope of Hari’s work is much broader than these. Rather than merely telling us to stop doomscrolling Twitter and get on with life, he covers a multiplicity of factors and forces that are combining to steal the ability of many of us to focus. Social media, pollution, lack of sleep, poor diet, overwork and more are all discussed, with many pointers to third-party research.</p>
<p>Despite the breadth and serious nature of the subject matter, I should note that some aspects of this book are also laugh-out-loud funny. I particularly enjoyed an early anecdote about Hari witnessing visitors to the Graceland museum experiencing Elvis Presley’s home by fixating on a VR iPad tour, rather than looking around the actual room in which they were standing.</p>
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
<h3 id="good-pop-bad-pop-by-jarvis-cocker.wp-block-heading"><a href="https://amzn.to/3GtDziA">Good Pop Bad Pop</a> by Jarvis Cocker</h3>
<p>When I was in my twenties I couldn’t fathom the appeal of biographies. Why, I reasoned, would I want to waste my time reading about one individual out of the billions who had lived or would ever live? Surely it would be more efficient to read distilled human knowledge on a much broader subject?</p>
<p>Well, I’m not sure exactly when I changed my opinion on this, but I must have done so because I now find myself reading several biographies each year, and they frequently appear atop my end-of-year blog posts. Other celebrity autobiographies that I enjoyed in 2022 were <em><a href="https://amzn.to/3BDV10H">The Gift of a Radio: My Childhood and Other Train Wrecks</a></em> by broadcaster Justin Webb, and <em><a href="https://amzn.to/3V6RNK1">Coal Black Mornings</a></em> by Suede frontman Brett Anderson.</p>
<p>The concept behind Cocker’s autobiography (or “inventory”) is that he cleaned out an attic space during the Covid lockdowns, deciding whether to “keep or cob” accumulated treasures/junk. This provides a conceit for many entertaining anecdotes about his life growing up in Sheffield and becoming lead singer of Pulp, all written in a most idiosyncratic style. Highlights for me included a detailed explanation of how he came to be hospitalised after fall out of a window while trying to impress a girl, and a wonderful piece on interviewing the late Leonard Cohen during his time as a BBC Radio 6 Music DJ.</p>
<p>I was sorely tempted to get the audiobook of this to hear Jarvis’s own narration, but plumped for the hardback instead which is wonderfully typeset and illustrated with many photographs of the items saved from the loft.</p>
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
<h3 id="skyfaring-a-journey-with-a-pilot-by-mark-vanhoenacker.wp-block-heading"><a href="https://amzn.to/3ArIHjC">Skyfaring: A Journey With a Pilot</a> by Mark Vanhoenacker</h3>
<p>This was a present from my wife Jocelyn for Christmas 2021. I had not been previously aware of it, so was pleasantly surprised when it became one of my favourite books of the year.</p>
<p>Vanhoenacker is a commercial airline pilot who has flown short-haul and long-haul routes for British Airways from a base in London to cities all over the world. He writes engagingly and romantically about all aspects of flying – the machines, the processes and procedures, the navigation systems, but mostly how it <em>feels</em> to transport and be transported so rapidly across space and time.</p>
<p>The prose is ethereal and dreamlike, in a manner not dissimilar to the jet lag and “place lag” that it describes. Vanhoenacker captures well the magic of aviation and inspires a desire to travel once again, following years of Covid lockdowns.</p>
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
<h3 id="the-outrun-by-amy-liptrot.wp-block-heading"><a href="https://amzn.to/3GAD5aF">The Outrun</a> by Amy Liptrot</h3>
<p>This is a fascinating memoir by Amy Liptrot who, at the age of thirty, left behind the life she lived as an alcoholic in London to return to her childhood home of Orkney. Her sublime writings about the path to recovery amongst the peaceful nature of the islands are quite hypnotic, and spoke to me, particularly the sections about gradually building new and better habits over time.</p>
<p>Nourishing and inspiring, this book is the reason that I have spent less of my free time watching TV and drinking wine this year, preferring instead to spend my time on more productive activities (like reading!)</p>
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
<h3 id="the-very-nice-box-by-laura-blackett-and-eve-gleichman.wp-block-heading"><a href="https://amzn.to/3hQ1RJf">The Very Nice Box</a> by Laura Blackett and Eve Gleichman</h3>
<p>My favourite work of fiction this year was this sparkling debut novel that captured the zeitgeist in a manner that reminded me of Douglas Coupland novels in the early 1990s. Obsessive engineer Ada designs storage boxes for STÄDA, a furniture manufacturer that comes across as a cross between Ikea and a Silicon Valley big tech company.</p>
<p>This is a darkly humorous and suspenseful novel that is an easy read. Having bought and enjoyed it in the States around New Year prior to its UK release, I mailed my copy to my friend and erstwhile colleague Steph, as I knew she’d love it too. She soon messaged “I devoured it. I’m reeling. Thank you”.</p>
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
<h2 id="the-best-of-the-rest.wp-block-heading">The Best of the Rest</h2>
<h3 id="a-thousand-brains-a-new-theory-of-intelligence-by-jeff-hawkins.wp-block-heading"><a href="https://amzn.to/3UYv0Ru">A Thousand Brains: A New Theory of Intelligence</a> by Jeff Hawkins</h3>
<p>I bought this book after it was recommended by Bill Gates in one of his periodic <a href="https://www.gatesnotes.com/">Gates Notes</a> emails. It is brimming with fascinating theories on how the human brain works – I was particularly taken by the explanation of “frames of reference” as a model for the way in which we comprehend the world.</p>
<h3 id="bewilderment-by-richard-powers.wp-block-heading"><a href="https://amzn.to/3gqTRy1">Bewilderment</a> by Richard Powers</h3>
<p>I don’t read many books which could be considered to fall within the category of science fiction. But <em>Bewilderment</em> doesn’t feel like traditional science fiction, rather it gently and sensitively covers broader themes of man’s impact on the earth, autism, our political systems, the loss of loved ones, and the workings of brain. This one will linger with me for a while.</p>
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
<h3 id="learn-how-to-solve-cryptic-crosswords-a-course-for-beginners-by-henry-howarth.wp-block-heading"><a href="https://amzn.to/3hMs6QQ">Learn How to Solve Cryptic Crosswords: A Course for Beginners</a> by Henry Howarth</h3>
<p>When not reading books, I also enjoy reading newspapers and magazines_._ I usually skip straight past the cryptic crosswords in these, finding them to be baffling and impenetrable. B<br>
ut one evening this year I lingered for a little while over a crossword in <em>New Statesman</em> and was pleasantly surprised to realise that I could work out the answer to one of the easier anagram clues.</p>
<p>This epiphany caused a curious tingle in my brain which I wanted to experience again. So I sought assistance via this excellent textbook-like work, which takes the reader on a step-by-step course explaining the different types of clues to be found in cryptic crosswords and techniques for solving these.</p>
<p>Thanks to this book, I now find myself capable of tackling the relatively easy <em>Everyman</em> crossword in <em>The Observer</em> each week, and sometimes the cryptic crossword in <em>New Statesman</em>, dependent on the setter. The tingles in my brain keep coming along with those “a-ha!” moments when the penny drops on a cute parsing. I’m enjoying building my vocabulary and general knowledge, and hope to build up to tackling the tougher problems in the national dailies next year.</p>
<h3 id="exponential-how-accelerating-technology-is-leaving-us-behind-and-what-to-do-about-it-by-azeem-azhar.wp-block-heading"><a href="https://amzn.to/3XkdecX">Exponential: How Accelerating Technology is Leaving Us Behind and What to Do About It</a> by Azeem Azhar</h3>
<p>This book considers the potential impact upon the world of technologies that are currently improving at an exponential rate. I found much of this far-sighted work to be reassuringly optimistic in nature, such as the potential for 3D printing to decentralise manufacturing bases, or the transition away from fossil fuels. Elsewhere however, Azhar highlights the inability of slowly-acting national governments to respond to a changing world with fast-moving social problems.</p>
<h3 id="software-architecture-the-hard-parts-modern-trade-off-analyses-for-distributed-architectures-by-neal-ford-mark-richards-pramod-sadalage-and-zhamak-dehghani.wp-block-heading"><a href="https://amzn.to/3EJmAHI">Software Architecture: The Hard Parts. Modern Trade-Off Analyses for Distributed Architectures</a> by Neal Ford, Mark Richards, Pramod Sadalage and Zhamak Dehghani</h3>
<p>This was my favourite technical book of the year. The weak joke about software architecture is that the answer to any question is “it depends”. As a result of this truism, most other books on the subject tend to give an overview of various nonfunctional considerations (scalability, deployability, testability, extensibility, etc) while stopping short of offering any firm guidance. After all, “it depends” on the specific system and business drivers.</p>
<p>“The Hard Parts” faces head-on the complexities involved in making such trade-off decisions in the world of distributed systems in general and microservices in particular. Aided by an extended case study that runs throughout the book, it offers techniques to identify appropriate levels of reuse, decomposition, data ownership, distributed workflows, transactional sagas, and more. I particularly appreciated one of the later chapters on managing analytical data, which compared traditional Data Warehouses and Data Lakes with a more contemporary Data Mesh approach.</p>
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
<h3 id="if-its-smart-its-vulnerable-by-mikko-hypponen.wp-block-heading"><a href="https://amzn.to/3AwStkl">If It’s Smart, It’s Vulnerable</a> by Mikko Hypponen</h3>
<p>Mikko Hypponen is a global cybersecurity expert with over thirty years’ experience working as a researcher and investigator. This short breezy book provides a fascinating array of anecdotes and insights from his career in infosec, in addition to concrete advice for how we as individuals can better protect ourselves in our increasingly interconnected world.</p>
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
<h3 id="no-one-round-here-reads-tolstoy-memoirs-of-a-working-class-reader-by-mark-hodkinson.wp-block-heading"><a href="https://amzn.to/3Gvv5Yr">No One Round Here Reads Tolstoy: Memoirs of a Working-Class Reader</a> by Mark Hodkinson</h3>
<p>It seems that since reading <em><a href="https://amzn.to/3jaOZyd">Lowborn</a></em> and <em><a href="https://amzn.to/3YyP4fp">Poverty Safari</a></em>, the Audible recommendation algorithm has concluded that I want to hear more tales of working class folk achieving against the odds. That’s how I discovered this charming and drily humorous autobiography by Lancastrian author, publicist and bibliophile Mark Hodkinson. In addition to the many anecdotes about reading and the publishing industry, this also features poignant yet often wildly funny chapters on music, schools, family relationships and terrible jobs.</p>
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
<h3 id="seven-games-a-human-history-by-oliver-roeder.wp-block-heading"><a href="https://amzn.to/3AvZH8l">Seven Games: A Human History</a> by Oliver Roeder</h3>
<p>The seven eponymous games covered in this book are checkers, chess, Go, backgammon, poker, Scrabble and bridge. For each, Roeder dives into the history, basic strategies, the personalities involved at the highest levels of the game, and what makes each game challenging for humans (and computers) to play. His first-hand reports of his experiences entering world poker and Scrabble competitions were particularly entertaining.</p>
<p>I enjoyed studying Game theory at university in the mid-1990s where part of the course covered the basics of developing chess-playing software in a rather deterministic, brute-force manner. It was interesting to contrast those techniques with some of the modern AI/ML approaches described in this book that have been used to allow computers to succeed at these games.</p>
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
<h3 id="trillions-how-a-band-of-wall-street-renegades-invented-the-index-fund-and-changed-finance-forever-by-robin-wigglesworth.wp-block-heading"><a href="https://amzn.to/3EMw1q4">Trillions: How a Band of Wall Street Renegades Invented the Index Fund and Changed Finance Forever</a> by Robin Wigglesworth</h3>
<p>My favourite financial book of the year, this history of index funds is a surprisingly mesmerising confluence of economics, history, mathematics, psychology, computer science and more. In addition to focusing on the cost savings that can be had to individuals who choose to invest via index funds rather than active managers, it also touches on the implications for corporate governance of the large proportion of companies now owned by “passive” funds.</p>
<h3 id="hope-and-glory-a-peoples-history-of-modern-britain-by-stuart-maconie.wp-block-heading"><a href="https://amzn.to/3V91EPV">Hope and Glory: A People’s History of Modern Britain</a> by Stuart Maconie</h3>
<p>In this warm-hearted look at Britain, broadcaster and author Stuart Maconie selects one key event from each decade of the twentieth century, travelling to the location where they occurred and explaining how they have shaped the country in which we live.</p>
<p>Maconie is an opinionated author, and in these divided times I suspect that levels of enjoyment of this book will depend upon whether your politics fall on the same side of the fence as his. Mine largely do, so I found this to be an entertaining, witty, and insightful read. Some of the scenes and interviews described from Maconie’s travels also made me consider that perhaps Britain (and England in particular) is after all a more welcoming, progressive and tolerant society than I had recently believed… but then I realised that this book was published back in 2012, just ahead of the unifying London olympics, and well before the divisive Brexit referendum.</p>
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
<h3 id="out-of-office-the-big-problem-and-bigger-promise-of-working-from-home-by-anne-helen-petersen-and-charlie-warzel.wp-block-heading"><a href="https://amzn.to/3gj7P50">Out of Office: The Big Problem and Bigger Promise of Working From Home</a> by Anne Helen Petersen and Charlie Warzel</h3>
<p>I have been fortunate enough to be able to work from home for the last 33 months, since the onset of the Covid-19 pandemic made clients such as mine realise that this was a possibility.</p>
<p>This book explores the pros and cons of remote working, and in particular how to use the opportunity that this affords to change our lives and communities for the better. Some aspects of the discussion are rather US-centric in regard to the labour market and geography, but much of this commentary and analysis applies equally to our situation in the UK and Europe.</p>
<h3 id="reclaiming-conversation-the-power-of-talk-in-a-digital-age-by-sherry-turkle.wp-block-heading"><a href="https://amzn.to/3Enn6Kj">Reclaiming Conversation: The Power of Talk in a Digital Age</a> by Sherry Turkle</h3>
<p>It is almost a quarter century since I first read a book by sociologist and clinical psychologist Sherry Turkle. <em><a href="https://amzn.to/3FBGUdx">Life on the Screen: Identity in the Age of the Internet</a></em> made a big impression on me as I was leaving university and stepping out into the world of work, helping me realise that the internet offered the ability to easily connect with people and ideas from far and wide.</p>
<p>By contrast, <em>Reclaiming Conversation</em> argues that we have now taken this search for broad but shallow connections too far, and have largely lost the capacity for the deeper one-to-one conversations that have the power to help us build meaningful lives and relationships. In a world of texts, tweets, and other micro-interactions, Turkle explores the benefits to education, business and family relationships that can be achieved by reclaiming the lost art of conversation.</p>
<h3 id="catch-22-by-joseph-heller-and-a-clockwork-orange-by-antony-burgess.wp-block-heading"><a href="https://amzn.to/3Ot5CRd">Catch-22</a> by Joseph Heller and <a href="https://amzn.to/3hZLme1">A Clockwork Orange</a> by Antony Burgess</h3>
<p>I have been making an attempt to supplement my predominantly contemporary reading diet with the occasional classic novel, and I especially enjoyed reading these two during 2022, in addition to <em><a href="https://amzn.to/3FCXpps">The Catcher In The Rye</a></em> and <em><a href="https://amzn.to/3PDOokD">Of Mice and Men</a></em>.</p>
<p><em>Catch-22</em> had been recommended to me by my friend Jonathan Telfer when we were at university together in 1995, then again last year by colleague Magnus John when the character of Major Major somehow came up in conversation during a code review. I eventually succumbed to listening to the audiobook version narrated by Canadian actor Trevor White which is excellent – the dialogue in this funny and profound novel really benefits from being spoken aloud.</p>
<p>I had bought a paperback of <em>A Clockwork Orange</em> in 1998 and not yet read it until this October. I think the prospect of tackling the <em>Nadsat</em> slang which is used in much of the narrative had dissuaded me from starting this book for so long, but in the event this proved little barrier to understanding and enjoying this short novel. The context in which the slang words were used aided comprehension, as did familiarity with the storyline from having seen Stanley Kubrick’s film adaptation.</p>
<h3 id="prisoners-of-geography-ten-maps-that-tell-you-everything-you-need-to-know-about-global-politics-by-tim-marshall.wp-block-heading"><a href="https://amzn.to/3tI5qDZ">Prisoners of Geography: Ten Maps That Tell You Everything You Need to Know About Global Politics</a> by Tim Marshall</h3>
<p>This illuminating book explains how each nation’s choices and geopolitics are shaped by coasts, rivers, mountains, deserts and plains. It concisely explains why international affairs are the way they are, and how the physical topography of the world has shaped the political world maps with which we are generally more familiar. With particular reference to recent events, it presciently explains the geographical context behind Putin’s war in Ukraine. There is a sequel, <em><a href="https://amzn.to/3hF2SUN">The Power of Geography</a></em>, which I have bought but not yet read.</p>
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Books I Most Enjoyed Reading in 2021</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/the-books-i-most-enjoyed-reading-in-2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Dec 2021 21:21:01 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/the-books-i-most-enjoyed-reading-in-2021/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-top-5-the-top-5&#34;&gt;The Top 5 {#the-top-5}&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://amzn.to/3jwAUs6&#34;&gt;And Away…&lt;/a&gt; by Bob Mortimer&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As was the case in 2020, my favourite book of the year was an autobiography; this time by national treasure Bob Mortimer. Laugh out loud funny in many places, elsewhere this is tinged with melancholy and the realisation that, for all his on-screen tomfoolery, Mortimer is an incredibly shy individual.
Touching, contemplative, warm and kind throughout, there is plenty of food for thought here regarding how we ought to live our lives and interact with those around us. I heartily recommend the audiobook, narrated by the great man himself.&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="the-top-5-the-top-5">The Top 5 {#the-top-5}<!-- raw HTML omitted --></h2>
<p><!-- raw HTML omitted --> <!-- raw HTML omitted --></p>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/3jwAUs6">And Away…</a> by Bob Mortimer</p>
<p>As was the case in 2020, my favourite book of the year was an autobiography; this time by national treasure Bob Mortimer. Laugh out loud funny in many places, elsewhere this is tinged with melancholy and the realisation that, for all his on-screen tomfoolery, Mortimer is an incredibly shy individual.
Touching, contemplative, warm and kind throughout, there is plenty of food for thought here regarding how we ought to live our lives and interact with those around us. I heartily recommend the audiobook, narrated by the great man himself.<!-- raw HTML omitted --></p>
<p><!-- raw HTML omitted --> <!-- raw HTML omitted --></p>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/3prg6CZ">Boy Parts</a> by Eliza Clark</p>
<p>This is a bit of a cheat, as I read this book in a couple of short days at the back end of 2020, in that weird downtime period between Christmas and New Year, at the recommendation of my good friend and erstwhile luncheon companion Stephanie.
I haven’t read much fiction in recent years (only one novel made it on to last my annual round up last year) and tend to gravitate towards authors who are white male Boomers or Gen X. Eliza Clark made me realise what I had been missing – new generations of writers from different backgrounds with contemporary stories to entertain me.</p>
<p><em>Boy Parts</em> is a whirlwind ride – smart, funny, stylish and cinematic – that was genuinely unputdownable (except for the moments when I had to Google some unfamiliar terms, none of which I am going to repeat here). I’m grateful to this title for reawakening my interest in contemporary fiction and broadening my horizons, and hope that further novels from Eliza Clark will soon be forthcoming.<!-- raw HTML omitted --></p>
<p><!-- raw HTML omitted --> <!-- raw HTML omitted --></p>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/3hQ34hu">Built on a Lie: The Rise and Fall of Neil Woodford and the Fate of Middle England’s Money</a> by Owen Walker</p>
<p>One of the nice features of an Audible subscription is the ability to return any titles that you can’t get into. When I tapped the play icon at the start of this nine hour book about the collapse of Neil Woodford’s asset management company, I half-anticipated availing myself of that option shortly afterwards, as it had the potential to be quite dry and boring. But to my pleasant surprise, I found it to be one of the more gripping books that I listened to in 2021.</p>
<p>The journalistic style and chronological telling of a too-good-to-be-true business story gone bad reminded me of John Carreyou’s 2019 <em>Bad Blood</em>, about Elizabeth Holmes and the collapse of Theranos. I also felt that Walker’s clear and patient explanations of the inherent failings of the Woodford funds offered insights into risks to be aware of when managing my own (much smaller) personal investment portfolio.<!-- raw HTML omitted --></p>
<p><!-- raw HTML omitted --> <!-- raw HTML omitted --></p>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/3dGZvZ7">Luckenbooth</a> by Jenni Fagan</p>
<p>I loved the style and structure of this darkly gothic novel. Centred around an accursed Edinburgh tenement, it consists of nine intertwined stories covering different decades and different levels of the building. Stories within the storeys, if you will. This won’t be everyone’s cup of tea, but I found it to be evocative, gritty and thoroughly entertaining.<!-- raw HTML omitted --></p>
<p><!-- raw HTML omitted --> <!-- raw HTML omitted --></p>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/3E6p6VA">Should We Stay or Should We Go</a> by Lionel Shriver</p>
<p>The married protagonists of this satire make a pact to commit suicide together aged 80. There follow many alternative scenarios wherein the couple do or don’t go through with this plan, and different political, economic, scientific and cultural situations arise. Some of these are all too believable, whilst others are stretched to the point of absurdity, as is to be expected from any good satire.</p>
<p>A Brexit subplot and Covid backdrop gave this a contemporary spin, making it an easy pick for one of my books of 2021.</p>
<h2 id="the-best-of-the-rest">The Best of the Rest</h2>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/3rJZwj2">A World Without Email: Reimagining Work in the Age of Overload</a> by Cal Newport</p>
<p>One of those books that you’d love your bosses or clients to read. Having worked wholly remotely since March 2020, and as part of a geo-distributed team for countless years before then, I find myself constantly plugged into what Newport accurately calls the “Hyperactive Hive Mind” approach to modern knowledge work. His argument is that real-time communication tools like Slack and Email serve  to distract us and rob us of the opportunity to focus deeply and achieve truly meaningful productivity.</p>
<p>Split into two sections, this book first explores the case against such tooling, before secondly offering a series of principles and processes for how to rise above the noise and regain more structured and productive workflows. I read this book early in 2021 and appreciated greatly the valuable tactics and strategies it offers.</p>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/3hI2baf">Crossroads: In Search of the Moments that Changed Music</a> by Mark Radcliffe</p>
<p>This summer I tried (and failed) for a second time to read <em><a href="https://amzn.to/3dWaYDa">Yeah Yeah Yeah – The Story of Modern Pop</a></em> by St Etienne’s Bob Stanley. It seems like the kind of book that in theory I ought to like, but in practice I find it too comprehensive, worthy, and academic to be enjoyable. Perhaps I should skim through to the bits about the bands I care for.</p>
<p>Conversely, I found <em>Crossroads: In Search of the Moments that Changed Music</em> to be exactly the kind of music literature that floats my boat. It is packed with information, but delivers this with a fast-paced warm-hearted anecdotal style, much as you might expect from listening to Radcliffe speaking on the radio between records.</p>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/2XxmDUg">Four Thousand Weeks: Time And How To Use It</a> by Oliver Burkeman</p>
<p>I have read very many traditional productivity books in my life. <em>Getting Things Done, Seven Habits of Highly Effective People</em>, <em>Get Everything Done and Still Have Time To Play,</em> you know the kind of thing. This book isn’t one of those. It steps back from that hamster-on-a-wheel design for life, and instead suggests that you should embrace the limitation of a finite lifespan, choosing to recognise the impossibility of achieving everything and hence refocussing on what is genuinely worthwhile.</p>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/358dRwL">How Not To Be Wrong: The Art of Changing Your Mind</a> by James O’Brien</p>
<p>The less arrogant and more contemplative sequel to <em>How To Be Right</em>, this sees O’Brien think again and encourage us to consider the reasons that we might hold the opinions that we do.</p>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/3xNWAEx">How to Make the World Add Up: Ten Rules for Thinking Differently About Numbers</a> by Tim Harford</p>
<p>My favourite statistics book of the year! At a time when we are bombarded more than ever by information and misinformation of huge importance to our lives, this offers some essential advice for how to cut through the noise and our own biases and interpret statistics dispassionately.</p>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/2PeCEtD">Klara and the Sun</a>, and <a href="https://amzn.to/2X0XMaU">Never Let Me Go</a> by Kazuo Ishiguro</p>
<p>I had been intending to read an Ishiguro novel for some time, so when his new novel <em>Klara and the Sun</em> was published in 2021, I took that as my cue to finally do so, and followed it shortly afterwards with <em>Never Let Me Go</em>.</p>
<p>Both novels had a superb pace and economical use of words that made the story flow effortlessly, pulling me along as if I were drifting around a lazy river on a rubber ring. The subject matter of both novels also touched on what it means to be human, which seems to be a recurring theme in my favoured reading material.</p>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/35xZoKK">Let Us Dream: The Path to a Better Future</a> by Pope Francis</p>
<p>Not my usual kind of read (being non-Catholic), but I felt drawn to this title during those long, dark, cold days of the third UK COVID lockdown at the start of 2021. Francis offered much comfort and hope at a bleak time, and also espoused visions and policies that struck me as being more enlightened and progressive than I had expected. Thoughtful, insightful, hopeful.</p>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/3prubje">Luster</a> by Raven Leilani</p>
<p>A debut novel about a Black woman in her twenties who gets involved with a forty-something white man in an open relationship. This was another of the young(-er than me) female writers that I felt compelled to read following my enjoyment of <em>Boy Parts</em>. The relationships described in the novel are complex and nuanced, in particular the protagonist’s relationship with her lover’s Black 12-year-old adoptive daughter.</p>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/2S13GXd">Milk Fed</a> by Melissa Broder</p>
<p>Food, sex, religion, and then some more food for good measure. The eating scenes in this novel about a Jewish lesbian with body dysmorphia felt like far guiltier pleasures than the sex scenes ever could be. A fascinating exploration of hunger, desire and faith.</p>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/2PhMNGA">The Rules of Living Well</a> by Richard Templar</p>
<p>I am a sucker for Richard Templar’s “Rules” series of books with their bite-sized advice on how to approach Life, Wealth, Work, Management, Love, and more. This “..Living Well” volume was published at an apposite time, when lockdowns and the covid pandemic have made many of us reconsider what is truly important in life and how to look after our mental and physical health.</p>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/3sh9gCC">Small Data: The Tiny Clues that Uncover Huge Trends</a> by Martin Lindstrom</p>
<p>This book sat unopened on my Kindle for five years since I bought it in June 2016 before I read it on a sun lounger in a couple of days during the August of 2021. I shouldn’t have waited so long.</p>
<p>Lindstrom is a brand consultant who eschews Big Data and the soulless inferences it produces, in favour of more traditional anthropological research methods – talking to the natives in various target markets throughout the world to understand what really makes them tick. There are many interesting and insightful case studies included here, with chapter titles such as “Fanning Desire: How Siberian Refrigerator Doors and a Saudi Arabian Mall Created a Revolutionary Website for Russian Women” and “The United Colors of India: Selling Breakfast Cereals to Two Generations of Warring Women”.</p>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/2RTt15E">Software Engineering at Google: Lessons Learned from Programming Over Time</a> curated by Titus Winters, Tom Manschreck and Hyrum Wright</p>
<p>I figure that I’m allowed one tech book in my annual round-up, right?<br>
This is an easy-going and varied collection of essays about how things are done at Google (mostly strictly technical things, but also softer things such as achieving a diverse workforce). As such, it offers useful insights for those of us who work on supposedly large-scale technical projects to judge ourselves against.</p>
<p>Of course in truth, most of us will never work on systems with nearly so many users as Google, so it would be madness for us to, say, develop our own bespoke source control system or automated build tooling. But that doesn’t prevent this from being an interesting read. And some of the principles described, such as <a href="https://www.hyrumslaw.com/">Hyrum’s Law</a>, are well worth knowing.</p>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/3kw4was">This is Going to Hurt: Secret Diaries of a Junior Doctor</a> by Adam Kay</p>
<p>A highly engaging set of diaries from Kay’s time as a junior doctor in the NHS, this is one of the better “secret diary of…” books that seem to be en vogue in recent years. Very funny, frequently heartbreaking, and generally politically maddening, this book offered some eye-opening insights into the true nature of a very difficult career path.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The 12 Books I Most Enjoyed Reading in 2020</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/12-books-i-most-enjoyed-reading-in-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Dec 2020 07:07:55 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/12-books-i-most-enjoyed-reading-in-2020/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;So that, then, was 2020. Good riddance. One might imagine that the enforced downtime offered by the pandemic lockdowns would have afforded me the opportunity to read many more books than I did in 2019.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But a displeasing proportion of my evenings in 2020 were spent relentlessly doomscrolling Twitter, eager for the latest morsels of information about the pandemic, US election or (sigh) Brexit. Besides, most of my “reading” in 2019 was actually achieved by listening to Audible while commuting or at the gym, two activities which barely featured in my life this year.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>So that, then, was 2020. Good riddance. One might imagine that the enforced downtime offered by the pandemic lockdowns would have afforded me the opportunity to read many more books than I did in 2019.</p>
<p>But a displeasing proportion of my evenings in 2020 were spent relentlessly doomscrolling Twitter, eager for the latest morsels of information about the pandemic, US election or (sigh) Brexit. Besides, most of my “reading” in 2019 was actually achieved by listening to Audible while commuting or at the gym, two activities which barely featured in my life this year.</p>
<p>Still, by year end it seems I have indeed read slightly more books (36) than I did last year (33), though on reviewing my list there are only a dozen that I feel compelled to tell you about:</p>
<h3 id="the-top-5-the-top-5">The Top 5 {#the-top-5}<!-- raw HTML omitted --></h3>
<p><!-- raw HTML omitted --> <!-- raw HTML omitted --></p>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/3c6wPEm">The Ride of a Lifetime: Lessons in Creative Leadership from 15 Years as CEO of the Walt Disney Company</a> by Robert Iger</p>
<p>My favourite book of the year is this autobiography by outgoing Disney CEO Bob Iger. One of Bill Gates’ regular book recommendations, I likely wouldn’t have considered reading it without his endorsement, as on the face of it this sounds like a typical airport business yawnfest. It’s not.</p>
<p>Rather than being about the dry, cold nature of business, earnings calls and margins, Iger’s book is full of warmth and humanity, with a particular focus on dealing with other people respectfully and understanding their motivations. This obvious genuine interest in other people allowed Iger to clinch stunning deals with Pixar, Lucasfilm, Marvel, and 20th Century Fox, whilst cultivating excellent relationships and friendships with the likes of Rupert Murdoch and Steve Jobs.<!-- raw HTML omitted --></p>
<p><!-- raw HTML omitted --> <!-- raw HTML omitted --></p>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/3hCC4Qb">Airhead: The Imperfect Art of Making News</a> by Emily Maitlis</p>
<p>Exiting my office one afternoon in summer, I overheard Jocelyn listening to this audiobook, specifically a portion describing Maitlis’ <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nqa4kykOsEk">memorable interview with short-lived White House Communications Director Anthony (“The Mooch”) Scaramucci</a>. I knew instantly that I had to listen to the whole book without delay.</p>
<p>In addition to that memorable moment with The Mooch, Maitlis also relates tales of meetings with Donald Trump, Theresa May, Simon Cowell, Bill Clinton, James Comey, Tony Blair, Gordon Ramsay and many more. Russell Brand’s ruminations on the addictive properties of Penguin biscuits will live long in my memory.</p>
<p>On television Maitlis has always come across as a super-smart yet down-to-earth big sister figure, and this compilation of anecdotes from years of reporting the stories of the day and interviewing those who shape our world has a similar quality.<!-- raw HTML omitted --></p>
<p><!-- raw HTML omitted --> <!-- raw HTML omitted --></p>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/3jgPjXI">Sorry I’m Late, I Didn’t Want To Come: An Introvert’s Year of Living Dangerously</a> by Jessica Pan</p>
<p>As a fellow introvert, I naturally found many of Pan’s tales of self-enforced extroversion butt-clenchingly cringy. But there’s no denying that they were also hugely entertaining and perhaps, just perhaps, also offer evidence that occasionally saying “yes” and getting oneself “out there” might lead to a more fulfilling life.</p>
<p>Don’t get me wrong; I don’t plan to try stand up comedy or improv any time soon. But I might be open to the idea of making occasional smalltalk with my neighbours. Maybe.<!-- raw HTML omitted --></p>
<p><!-- raw HTML omitted --> <!-- raw HTML omitted --></p>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/2Fomqtn">Do No Harm: Stories of Life, Death and Brain Surgery</a> by Henry Marsh</p>
<p>Why would I, who as a child hated the very thought of injections, and as a teenager fainted on multiple occasions in biology lessons, possibly want to read a book about brain surgery, of all things?</p>
<p>But this was recommended to me by my erstwhile colleague, good friend and <a href="https://blog.iannelson.uk/its-a-small-world/">surprise cousin</a> <a href="https://johnsad.ventures/">John Conners</a>, whose opinion I respect, so I gave it a go.</p>
<p>Pleasingly, I discovered that Marsh’s memoirs were less about the “gory details” of his chosen vocation (though naturally the topic did crop up), and more about his interactions with patients and their families, existential questions of life and death, and his run-ins with all aspect of our wonderful, bureaucratic, horribly over-stretched NHS.<!-- raw HTML omitted --></p>
<p><!-- raw HTML omitted --> <!-- raw HTML omitted --></p>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/2yRsTcN">The Art of Statistics: Learning from Data</a> by David Spiegelhalter</p>
<p>Finally, an approachable book about statistics to take the baton from Darrell Huff’s 1954 classic <em><a href="https://amzn.to/34ldkXQ">How To Lie With Statistics</a></em>.</p>
<p>The statistician that politicians love to quote has written a book that could easily become the canonical work for explaining the topic to the everyman. There is a surprising amount of warmth, opinion, and good humour between its pages.</p>
<p>If possible, get the hardback edition, or at the very least a physical copy. It is beautifully typeset and an object you’ll want to treasure.</p>
<h3 id="the-best-of-the-rest">The Best of the Rest</h3>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/2LENTqq">Erebus: The Story of a Ship</a> by Michael Palin</p>
<p>In discussing with friends and colleagues the books that we have read this year, I found it curious how frequently the question is broached of whether listening to audiobooks “doesn’t count” or is somehow “cheating”. I don’t think so – I think it is a perfectly reasonable way of efficiently consuming books, perhaps doing so at the same time as some other activity such as commuting, exercise, or other hobbies.</p>
<p>There’s also something quite primeval about stories being handed down by the oral tradition from our forebears. I listened to <em>Erebus</em> during my commutes in those innocent early pre-lockdown weeks of the year, and found it soothing and absorbing to listen to Palin’s familiar dulcit Sheffield tones tell me about this 19th Century ship and its crews’ tales of derring-do. While Spiegelhalter’s statistical tome is a book that naturally succeeds in hardcopy format, <em>Erebus</em> certainly excels as an audiobook.</p>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/31MISFC">Everything Happens for a Reason and Other Lies I’ve Loved</a> by Dr Kate Bowler</p>
<p>Blimey. Kate Bowler is a student of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prosperity_theology">Prosperity theology</a>, the belief that financial blessing and physical well-being are the will of God for believers. The mother of a young son, Bowler’s world was shaken by a stage IV colon cancer diagnosis.</p>
<p>This elegant, grateful, thoughtful book describes Bowler’s experiences coming to terms with that diagnosis, the reaction of her church, and what is truly important in life. Lots of food for thought here.</p>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/2TebFO8">Ghost In The Wires: My Adventures as the World’s Most Wanted Hacker</a> by Kevin Mitnick</p>
<p>Recommended to me by my techie colleague James Lavery, I expected that much of Mitnick’s book would be of a geeky nature, detailing the technical aspects of his exploits that led to his high-profile arrest and imprisonment for computer hacking. In fact, on listening to this book, it transpires that the most efficient technique at Mitnick’s disposal was not his technical skills but social engineering – the ability to convince other human<br>
s to reveal information that they should not have done.</p>
<p>Time and again, in different states and in different ways, Mitnick used his self-confidence and relied on the natural goodwill of others to gain unlawful access to all manner of data and computer systems during the 1980s and 1990s. A thrilling ride.</p>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/2LGruZW">The Life and Times of The Thunderbolt Kid: Travels Through My Childhood</a> by Bill Bryson</p>
<p>During 2020 I read (or re-read) six of Bill Bryson’s books. This was partly a reaction to the uncertainties caused by the coronavirus pandemic. I appreciated hearing his light-hearted travel monologues – exploring the world in my mind while confined to our village.</p>
<p>This particular book, recommended by my colleague Mark D. Goldthorpe, takes the reader/listener back to Bryson’s childhood – midwestern America in the 1950s, a time of unparalleled happiness and bountifulness. A series of naïve early experiences relayed through the reflective prism of one well-travelled gentleman’s memory, it repeatedly brought a smile to my face during this difficult year.</p>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/2LGCaHL">Machines Like Me</a> by Ian McEwan</p>
<p>The only fiction book on my list this year. Set in an alternative history in the 1980s, this sees a version of the UK that loses the Falklands War, but in which technology is more advanced, and artificially intelligent androids are available to own.</p>
<p>I found the storyline to be rather dark, yet captivating. It explores interesting philosophical questions, such as what it means to be human, and lingered long in my memory after I’d finished reading it.</p>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/2TyaUQn">Rebel Ideas: The Power of Diverse Thinking</a> by Matthew Syed</p>
<p>A huge range of case studies explaining the crucial benefits to be had from cognitive diversity – listening to a wide range of voices and opinions from different backgrounds – and the potential tragedies that can unfold when we limit ourselves to working within homogeneous groups.</p>
<p>As someone who has spent the majority of his career working on lone tasks – i.e. programming computers – but has in recent years broadened into more of a team lead role, I found some of these insights very helpful in my working life. They have persuaded me of the value of increasingly working together – pair-programming or mobbing – to pool cognitive diversity and solve complex problems more efficiently.</p>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/38tBFLT">Why We Sleep: The New Science of Sleep and Dreams</a> by Matthew Walker</p>
<p>I found this somewhat dry, theoretical, and biological in nature in the earlier chapters. But as the book progressed and more applied examples were given it hammered home the wide-ranging benefits of getting a good night’s sleep.</p>
<p>Since reading this I’ve been tracking the amount of time I spend asleep, and have been increasingly aware of the correlation between being suitably rested over an extended period, and my physical and cognitive wellbeing. I no longer labour under the delusion that time spent asleep is wasted time, or begrudge my teenaged son sleeping in at the weekends!</p>
<h3 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h3>
<p>Part-way through writing this blog post explaining why these books have appealed to me, I was surprised to note that there is an obvious theme running through many of these choice: People.</p>
<p>More than anything else in 2020, I have appreciated reading books which explore humanity, what it means to be human, and how to improve our interactions with other people:</p>
<ul>
<li>Iger’s advice on how to treat others with respect for the advancement of business interests.</li>
<li>Maitlis’s trying to understand what makes her interviewees tick.</li>
<li>Pan’s attempts to be less introverted and increase her interactions with other people.</li>
<li><em>Rebel Ideas</em> explaining the devastating effects of failing to solicit a diverse range of opinions.</li>
<li>The ease with which Kevin Mitnick repeatedly used social engineering techniques on other people who are predisposed to be helpful.</li>
<li>Henry Marsh opening up skulls and operating on the incredible delicate brains that make us who we are.</li>
<li>And even the sole fiction book on my list this year – <em>Machines Like Me</em> – is a fascinating exploration of what makes us human.</li>
</ul>
<p>I hope that as the roll-out of COVID-19 vaccines progresses, 2021 will bring more opportunities for us all to resume our interactions with each other, and practice doing so in more thoughtful and respectful ways.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The 20 Books I Most Enjoyed Reading in 2019</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/20-books-i-most-enjoyed-reading-in-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Jan 2020 22:40:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/20-books-i-most-enjoyed-reading-in-2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Near the end of 2018, I stumbled upon a thread of tweets by First Minister of Scotland Nicola Sturgeon in which she shared some of the many books that she had enjoyed during that year. I was both amazed and ashamed that a leader of a nation could consume so much literature whilst I, a mere sellsword codemonkey, barely got through a book every month (or two).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It wasn’t that I didn’t enjoy reading – I have always loved reading (and buying) books – it was just that I had somehow convinced myself that I didn’t have the time to read. I realised that this simply wasn’t true, that I could easily make time to read if I so desired, and vowed to consume more books during 2019.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Near the end of 2018, I stumbled upon a thread of tweets by First Minister of Scotland Nicola Sturgeon in which she shared some of the many books that she had enjoyed during that year. I was both amazed and ashamed that a leader of a nation could consume so much literature whilst I, a mere sellsword codemonkey, barely got through a book every month (or two).</p>
<p>It wasn’t that I didn’t enjoy reading – I have always loved reading (and buying) books – it was just that I had somehow convinced myself that I didn’t have the time to read. I realised that this simply wasn’t true, that I could easily make time to read if I so desired, and vowed to consume more books during 2019.</p>
<p>Pleasingly, I’ve been quite successful in my endeavours. <a href="https://www.audible.co.uk">Audible</a> has helped greatly, turning otherwise dead time spent commuting, walking the dog, mowing the lawn, or working out at the gym into productive book consumption time.</p>
<p>Here are the twenty books that I’ve most enjoyed during the year:</p>
<h2 id="the-top-5-the-top-5">The Top 5 {#the-top-5}<!-- raw HTML omitted --></h2>
<p><!-- raw HTML omitted --> <!-- raw HTML omitted --></p>
<p><strong><a href="https://amzn.to/35syPU6">Digital Minimalism: Choosing a Focused Life in a Noisy World</a></strong> by Cal Newport</p>
<p>The only book that I read cover-to-cover on two separate occasions during 2019. Following on from <em>So Good They Can’t Ignore You</em> and <em>Deep Work</em>, two other favourites of mine, Cal’s latest book offers practical concrete advice on how to regain focus in these digitally-distracted times.<!-- raw HTML omitted --></p>
<p><!-- raw HTML omitted --> <!-- raw HTML omitted --></p>
<p><strong><a href="https://amzn.to/36sTVTL">Talking to Strangers: What We Should Know about the People We Don’t Know</a></strong> by Malcolm Gladwell</p>
<p>A wonderful book that opened my eyes to how I engage and interact with other humans, and the many potential opportunities for devastating misunderstandings. I recommend the enhanced audiobook highly, as (where possible) it features original audio recordings and interviews with people involved in the case studies.<!-- raw HTML omitted --></p>
<p><!-- raw HTML omitted --> <!-- raw HTML omitted --></p>
<p><strong><a href="https://amzn.to/2tsQuxY">Bad Blood: Secrets and Lies in a Silicon Valley Startup</a></strong> by John Carreyrou</p>
<p>I had never heard of Theranos nor Elizabeth Holmes before reading this gripping true-life tale of organisational deception and misbehaviour, written by the WSJ investigative journalist who broke the story.<!-- raw HTML omitted --></p>
<p><!-- raw HTML omitted --> <!-- raw HTML omitted --></p>
<p><strong><a href="https://amzn.to/2MVFAaG">How to Be Right: … in a world gone wrong</a></strong> by James O’Brien</p>
<p>A great book written from the relatively unusual vantage point of talk radio host James O’Brien, who spends his days calmly and rationally explaining to callers the absurdity of their stated viewpoints (often, it seems, by simply giving them sufficient opportunity to explain themselves, or consider the meaning of the cliched words that they spout). Despite the title, O’Brien doesn’t claim to always be right, and in some chapters explains how the discourse on his show has led to the maturation of his own viewpoints.<!-- raw HTML omitted --></p>
<p><!-- raw HTML omitted --> <!-- raw HTML omitted --></p>
<p><strong><a href="https://amzn.to/36DaMmM">Coders: Who They Are, What They Think And How They Are Changing Our World</a></strong> by Clive Thompson</p>
<p>A bit of navel-gazing really, I enjoyed reading Wired Magazine’s Clive Thompson’s masterful description of what coders are like, and why. The audiobook is over 13 hours, but it flew by for me in little over a week’s listening. We coders are a funny (and disturbingly homogenous) breed, and this timely work explains us perfectly.</p>
<h2 id="the-best-of-the-rest">The Best of the Rest</h2>
<p><strong><a href="https://amzn.to/37HMKHp">Atomic Habits: An Easy and Proven Way to Build Good Habits and Break Bad Ones</a></strong> by James Clear</p>
<p>It’s the little things, you know? I read this book in the first half of the year, and its advice was instrumental in helping me (as the subtitle clearly says) to break some terrible habits and form some wonderful new ones (like reading more books!). I think it’s high time I flicked through this modern classic again, as I set new goals for 2020.</p>
<p><strong><a href="https://amzn.to/35lNnFa">The Behavioral Investor</a></strong> by Daniel Crosby</p>
<p>I read a surprising number of books about investing, most of which are too humdrum to mention here. But <em>The Behavioral Investor</em> is a brilliant, comprehensive explication of the psychological and physiological impediments on successful investing, along with tactics and strategies to overcome these.</p>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/35uEnxn"><strong>The Body</strong></a> by Bill Bryson</p>
<p>As someone who dislikes the thought of blood and dropped the study of Biology at the first opportunity aged 14, I’m amazed that I made it through this book. In the interests of road safety I did postpone listening to a couple of chapters whilst driving. As with most Bryson books, there is an engaging mix of science, history and human interest anecdotes to avoid the topics ever becoming too dry.</p>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/2QrgQt6"><strong>The Creativity Code</strong></a> by Marcus du Sautoy</p>
<p>I read a few different popular books on AI, Machine Learning and Algorithms in 2019. This was my favourite, as it delved down to (for me) the right levels of mathematical and computational detail without being either facile nor bewildering.</p>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/39GavkZ"><strong>Essentialism: The Disciplined Pursuit of Less</strong></a> by Greg McKeown</p>
<p>A relatively short book that, in places, inevitably covers some of the same ground as <em>Atomic Habits</em>, <em>Digital Minimalism</em> and <em>Ten Arguments for Deleting Your Social Media Accounts Right Now</em>. But nonetheless, it’s a decent high-level overview of how to do less yet accomplish more (or rather, more of <em>the right things</em>). I’ll most likely reread this at some point in 2020.</p>
<p><strong><a href="https://amzn.to/2Qqc52T">Fifty Things That Made the Modern Economy</a></strong> by Tim Harford</p>
<p>A lovely easy book to dip into. Fifty bite-sized micro-documentaries explaining how the modern economy as we know it was formed. I listened to much of this while decorating my study and mowing the lawn. I fear it may have resulted in my becoming a tedious bore (“Did you know…?”) in conversations with Mrs Nelson for weeks afterwards.</p>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/37F3QWI"><strong>Gotta Get Theroux This: My Life and Strange Times in Television</strong></a> by Louis Theroux</p>
<p>One of the few biographical books I read during the year, from <em>national treasure</em> and documentary maker Louis Theroux. I was in need of something lighter after wading through Yuval Noah Harari’s <em>Sapiens: A Brief History of Humankind</em>, and Jocelyn wisely suggested I read this. Entertaining, yet more than a little poignant in many places, most obviously in the chapters on Jimmy Savile.</p>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/2ttLWY2"><strong>Hidden Figures: The Untold Story of the African American Women Who Helped Win the Space Race</strong></a> by Margot Lee Shetterley</p>
<p>Not remotely techie or geeky, this is a fascinating social history of how a group of brilliant women helped the US Space Program to succeed, despite facing twin prejudices due to their gender and the colour of their skin. Some of these themes also crop up in <em>Coders</em>, one of my other favourites from 2019<br>
.</p>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/2Qq11mh"><strong>Invisible Women: Exposing Data Bias in a World Designed for Men</strong></a> by Caroline Criado Perez</p>
<p>Guaranteed to make every feminist’s piss boil, and rightly so. Superbly researched book exposing shocking gaps in datasets as far as women’s requirements are concerned.</p>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/2ZVdf9D"><strong>The Only Story</strong></a> by Julian Barnes</p>
<p>I don’t often read novels about love, but when I do they are usually written by Julian Barnes.</p>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/2Fm0JXB"><strong>Poverty Safari: Understanding the Anger of Britain’s Underclass</strong></a> by Darren McGarvey</p>
<p>I chanced upon this book in Waterstones while on a weekend city break to Glasgow for August Bank Holiday. Unexpectedly hilarious, well-paced and thought-provoking. Quite insightful reading for middle-class pricks like me.</p>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/2ulT896"><strong>Ready Player One</strong></a> by Ernest Cline</p>
<p>Not the kind of thing I would usually buy, but the Wil Wheaton narrated audiobook was recommended to me by <a href="https://twitter.com/nickmckenna">Nick McKenna</a>, so I gave it a go and thoroughly enjoyed it. Filled with much 1980s nerdy nostalgia which warmed the cockles of my heart. Subsequently made into a moving picture directed by one Steven Spielberg, apparently.</p>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/2ZSCCZO"><strong>Ten Arguments For Deleting Your Social Media Accounts Right Now</strong></a> by Jaron Lanier</p>
<p>Eloquent, well-argued, and coming from a very smart Silicon Valley pioneer like Lanier, these ten arguments are difficult to ignore. Combined with <em>Essentialism</em> and <em>Digital Minimalism</em>, this helped to persuade me to spend more time engaging in meaningful activities and less time frittering my life away on social media in 2019.</p>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/2QMPpsO"><strong>Who Owns England?: How We Lost Our Green and Pleasant Land, and How to Take it Back</strong></a> by Guy Shrubsole</p>
<p>A bit of a wildcard, but this book featured a combination of statistics, history, cartography and lefty politics that I couldn’t resist.</p>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/36tf00f"><strong>Why We Get The Wrong Politicians</strong></a> by Isabel Hardman</p>
<p>The system’s fucked. But then, you probably guessed that. Hardman goes into much more detail, which you will either appreciate (like me) or find tedious (like Mrs Nelson, who heard several chapters of this book by proxy when we were decorating the living room).</p>
<h2 id="what-s-next">What’s Next?</h2>
<p>You’ve seen the kind of things I enjoyed reading in 2019; what should I read in 2020? Let me know in the comments below.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
