<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>USA Trip 2006 on Ian Nelson</title>
    <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/series/usa-trip-2006/</link>
    <description>Recent content in USA Trip 2006 on Ian Nelson</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.146.6</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 23 Apr 2025 21:18:19 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://blog.iannelson.uk/series/usa-trip-2006/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>USA Trip 2006: Breakfast Prep</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/usa-trip-2006-breakfast-prep/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 May 2006 15:05:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/usa-trip-2006-breakfast-prep/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On our first morning in California, we headed out to breakfast, which was preceded by a short session of Breakfast Prep’, courtesy of Jocelyn.  It had been a couple of years since I’d last had Breakfast In America, and I’d forgotten how to respond to the awesome number of choices and options that would be flung in my direction by the waitperson.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s how you order breakfast in Britain:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;  &amp;lt;td&amp;gt;
    “&amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Full_English_Breakfast&amp;quot;&amp;gt;Full English Breakfast&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;, please.”
  &amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/tr&amp;gt;

&amp;lt;tr&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;td&amp;gt;
    Waitress:
  &amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;
  
  &amp;lt;td&amp;gt;
    “D’you want tea or coffee with that?”
  &amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/tr&amp;gt;

&amp;lt;tr&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;td&amp;gt;
    Diner:
  &amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;
  
  &amp;lt;td&amp;gt;
    “Tea, please.”
  &amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/tr&amp;gt;

&amp;lt;tr&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;td&amp;gt;
    Waitress:
  &amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;
  
  &amp;lt;td&amp;gt;
    “OK.”
  &amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/tr&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In due course, the standard, empire-forging breakfast is served, and is consumed heartily, perhaps after a little trading with your breakfasting companions (“I’ll swap you my tomatoes for a rasher of your bacon?”).  Everybody knows what is expected, nobody has tricky decisions to make, there are no surprises, and everyone enjoys what they get – and if they don’t enjoy it, well, they don’t mention it, because complaining about such things just wouldn’t be British, damn it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>On our first morning in California, we headed out to breakfast, which was preceded by a short session of Breakfast Prep’, courtesy of Jocelyn.  It had been a couple of years since I’d last had Breakfast In America, and I’d forgotten how to respond to the awesome number of choices and options that would be flung in my direction by the waitperson.</p>
<p>Here’s how you order breakfast in Britain:</p>
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
<pre><code>  &lt;td&gt;
    “&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Full_English_Breakfast&quot;&gt;Full English Breakfast&lt;/a&gt;, please.”
  &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;
    Waitress:
  &lt;/td&gt;
  
  &lt;td&gt;
    “D’you want tea or coffee with that?”
  &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;
    Diner:
  &lt;/td&gt;
  
  &lt;td&gt;
    “Tea, please.”
  &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;
    Waitress:
  &lt;/td&gt;
  
  &lt;td&gt;
    “OK.”
  &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
</code></pre>
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
<p>In due course, the standard, empire-forging breakfast is served, and is consumed heartily, perhaps after a little trading with your breakfasting companions (“I’ll swap you my tomatoes for a rasher of your bacon?”).  Everybody knows what is expected, nobody has tricky decisions to make, there are no surprises, and everyone enjoys what they get – and if they don’t enjoy it, well, they don’t mention it, because complaining about such things just wouldn’t be British, damn it.</p>
<p>Now, compare that if you will to the American breakfasting experience.  The sheer size of the American breakfast menu is symptomatic of the culture of Choice that seems to pervade all aspects of the consumer experience here (especially in California), and it really can take some time to pick an option.  But making your selection is only the beginning.  Here’s how a sample breakfast order conversation with an unexpecting Brit (i.e. me, two years ago), might go:</p>
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
<pre><code>  &lt;td&gt;
    “Are you ready to order?”
  &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;
    Me:
  &lt;/td&gt;
  
  &lt;td&gt;
    “I think so.  I’ll have the Sausage and Eggs, please.”
  &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;
    Waitperson:
  &lt;/td&gt;
  
  &lt;td&gt;
    “Do you want links sausages or patty?
  &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;
    Me:
  &lt;/td&gt;
  
  &lt;td&gt;
    “Oh.  Um, links, please.”
  &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;
    Waitperson:
  &lt;/td&gt;
  
  &lt;td&gt;
    “How do you want your eggs?
  &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;
    Me:
  &lt;/td&gt;
  
  &lt;td&gt;
    “Fried, please.”
  &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;
    Waitperson:
  &lt;/td&gt;
  
  &lt;td&gt;
    “Fried how?”
  &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;
    Me:
  &lt;/td&gt;
  
  &lt;td&gt;
    “Fried how?  In a frying pan, preferably!”
  &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;
    Waitperson:
  &lt;/td&gt;
  
  &lt;td&gt;
    “Over hard, over easy, over medium, or sunny side up?”
  &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;
    Me:
  &lt;/td&gt;
  
  &lt;td&gt;
    “What the&amp;#8230;?”
  &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;
    Jocelyn:
  &lt;/td&gt;
  
  &lt;td&gt;
    “You have them sunny side up, honey.”
  &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;
    Me:
  &lt;/td&gt;
  
  &lt;td&gt;
    “Oh, OK.  Sunny side up then, please.”
  &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;
    Waitperson:
  &lt;/td&gt;
  
  &lt;td&gt;
    “And what two sides would you like?”
  &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;
    Me:
  &lt;/td&gt;
  
  &lt;td&gt;
    “I beg your pardon?”
  &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;
    Waitperson:
  &lt;/td&gt;
  
  &lt;td&gt;
    “You get a choice of two side options from the list there&amp;#8230;”
  &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
</code></pre>
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
<p>I consult the list, by this time panicking a tad, and wondering what exactly “Campfire potatoes” (one of the options) are…</p>
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
<pre><code>  &lt;td&gt;
    “OK, I’ll go for hash browns and bacon, please.”
  &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;
    Waitperson:
  &lt;/td&gt;
  
  &lt;td&gt;
    “And what would you like to drink with that?”
  &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;
    Me:
  &lt;/td&gt;
  
  &lt;td&gt;
    “Coffee, please.”
  &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;
    Waitperson:
  &lt;/td&gt;
  
  &lt;td&gt;
    “Latte, Americano, Cappuccino, Espresso&amp;#8230;?  Decaf or Regular&amp;#8230;?”
  &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;
    Me:
  &lt;/td&gt;
  
  &lt;td&gt;
    “Oh God, er, regular cappuccino, please.”
  &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;
    Waitperson:
  &lt;/td&gt;
  
  &lt;td&gt;
    “And what bread would you like for your toast?”
  &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;
    Me:
  &lt;/td&gt;
  
  &lt;td&gt;
    “Brown, please.”
  &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;
    Waitperson:
  &lt;/td&gt;
  
  &lt;td&gt;
    “Brown?!”
  &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;
    Jocelyn:
  &lt;/td&gt;
  
  &lt;td&gt;
    “He means &amp;#8216;wheat’.”
  &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;
    Waitperson:
  &lt;/td&gt;
  
  &lt;td&gt;
    “OK, coming up..”
  &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
</code></pre>
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
<p>At which point I breathed a sigh of relief and started to dab at my heavily perspiring brow.  Who ever knew that ordering breakfast could be such a complicated experience?  The food is invariably delicious and the portions are big enough to feed a family of four for a week – after a decent US-style breakfast I rarely feel the need for a big lunch or dinner.  I can see how these levels of choice might be appealing if you’ve grown up with them and come to expect such options, but for the uninitiated it’s just baffling, confusing, and seems unnecessary.  Which is why, two years later, I won’t venture into a breakfast restaurant until I’ve done a bit of preparation into my responses to the likely questions.</p>
<p>Even the simplest snippets of dialogue can provoke unexpected reactions.  Back to that restaurant conversation from two years ago, when we’d finished eating, and I’d relaxed my guard a bit, the waitperson came to clear up:</p>
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
<pre><code>  &lt;td&gt;
    “So, how were your eggs?
  &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;
    Me:
  &lt;/td&gt;
  
  &lt;td&gt;
    “They were lovely, thank you.”
  &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;
    Waitperson:
  &lt;/td&gt;
  
  &lt;td&gt;
    “&lt;em&gt;Lovely&lt;/em&gt;?!  Ha ha!  Where the hell are &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; from?!”
  &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
</code></pre>
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
<p>Utterly bemusing!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>USA Trip 2006: Arrival</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/usa-trip-2006-arrival/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 May 2006 13:05:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/usa-trip-2006-arrival/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Monday 10th April 2006&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sun was still shining as we touched down at SFO, about 22 hours after we’d woken up.  If every day could last that long, I swear I’d get more work done – or maybe I’d just spend more time playing &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.civ4.com&#34;&gt;Civilization&lt;/a&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We picked up the car – a Pontiac Impala which initially seemed unfeasibly huge compared to our Focus, but it’s funny how quickly you adjust and get used to the size, making use of the available space – then it was off down US 101 on the final leg of our journey.  Despite it being rush hour, we had a swift journey due to being able to use the Car Pool lane (by virtue of not being a single-occupant vehicle).  I was amazed how under-utilised this lane was, and started wondering how much of an incentive would be needed for more Bay area commuters to start sharing rides – there’s another good question for &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.freakonomics.com&#34;&gt;the economists&lt;/a&gt; to ponder.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Monday 10th April 2006</em></p>
<p>The sun was still shining as we touched down at SFO, about 22 hours after we’d woken up.  If every day could last that long, I swear I’d get more work done – or maybe I’d just spend more time playing <a href="http://www.civ4.com">Civilization</a>…</p>
<p>We picked up the car – a Pontiac Impala which initially seemed unfeasibly huge compared to our Focus, but it’s funny how quickly you adjust and get used to the size, making use of the available space – then it was off down US 101 on the final leg of our journey.  Despite it being rush hour, we had a swift journey due to being able to use the Car Pool lane (by virtue of not being a single-occupant vehicle).  I was amazed how under-utilised this lane was, and started wondering how much of an incentive would be needed for more Bay area commuters to start sharing rides – there’s another good question for <a href="http://www.freakonomics.com">the economists</a> to ponder.</p>
<p>Joce drove – I didn’t think it prudent for my first transatlantic driving experience to come during rush hour at the end of a long day’s travelling – and I gazed out of the window, musing again at the open, opportune feeling of the region, despite its large population.  There are new buildings springing up, visible signs of affluence, and it all combines to create the feeling (illusion?) that anything is possible, there’s no history to hold back your dreams.  And of course, as a professional software developer, I was very aware of the kind of businesses to be found in cities such as Mountain View, Sunnyvale, and Palo Alto, that we sped through.</p>
<p>Back home, there’s something about York – the wealth of history, the cramped streets maybe – that convinces me that it’s nigh-on impossible to get noticed or make an impact in such a city.  How can you make your mark in a city with so many Roman remains on every street corner?  There’s always a nagging feeling that someone got there first, that it’s all been done before.  Name some famous people who’ve made an impact in York?  <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ivar_the_Boneless">Ivar the Boneless</a>?  <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Sentamu">John Sentamu</a>?  <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Judi_Dench">Dame Judi Dench</a>?  <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rick_Witter">Rick Witter</a>…?  I hypothesised that this might partly explain the large number of Guilds, Companies, Lodges, Fraternities and Clubs in the city – people band together in an effort to attain power and influence.  Is there a Company of Merchant Adventurers in North California?  I suspect not.</p>
<p>I shared my musings with Jocelyn.  She said &ldquo;Well… what sort of an impact would you like to make?&rdquo;  I confessed that I didn’t have the foggiest idea.  She rightly suggested that maybe it would be a good idea to decide that first, and worry about geography later.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>USA Trip 2006: Journey</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/usa-trip-2006-journey/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 May 2006 13:05:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/usa-trip-2006-journey/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;_Monday 10th April 2006&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;Travelling West during the daytime is a blast, especially on a sunny day.  Time it right and you can experience daylight for 24 hours, which afforded me time to catch up on some reading.  For Christmas Joce had given a book entitled &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.freakonomics.com/&#34;&gt;Freakonomics – A Rogue Economist Explores The Hidden Side Of Eveything&lt;/a&gt;, and now I finally had time to read through it.  I surprised myself by finishing it by the time we reached Chicago – this may be a chunky hardback book on economics, but it’s also &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; interesting and easy-going.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>_Monday 10th April 2006<!-- raw HTML omitted --></p>
<p><!-- raw HTML omitted -->Travelling West during the daytime is a blast, especially on a sunny day.  Time it right and you can experience daylight for 24 hours, which afforded me time to catch up on some reading.  For Christmas Joce had given a book entitled <a href="http://www.freakonomics.com/">Freakonomics – A Rogue Economist Explores The Hidden Side Of Eveything</a>, and now I finally had time to read through it.  I surprised myself by finishing it by the time we reached Chicago – this may be a chunky hardback book on economics, but it’s also <em>really</em> interesting and easy-going.</p>
<p>The book answers a mixed bag of questions – Which is more dangerous, a gun or a swimming pool? What do schoolteachers and sumo wrestlers have in common? Why do drug dealers still live with their moms? How much do parents really matter? – by using standard economic tools.  The results are fascinating – go check out some <a href="http://www.freakonomics.com/chapter.php">chapter excerpts</a> on the website if you don’t believe me.</p>
<p>Anyway, that book, combined with Barney, my trusty iPod made the flights, well, fly by.  It was the first time I’ve travelled whilst carrying almost my entire music collection in my pocket, and having that level of choice really pleased me.  Previously, no matter how many tapes or CDs I carried, there would always be something left at home that I had a desperate urge to listen to, and I never seemed to have the music to match my mood – which is <a href="http://www.intp.org/intprofile.html">essential for an INTP</a>.</p>
<p>At O’Hare airport, we discovered a small advantage of our transatlantic marriage – we can choose to go through passport control together through either the &ldquo;citizens&rdquo; or &ldquo;foreigners&rdquo; queue (natually, we picked the shorter one), in order to provide a complete picture to the immigration officer.  The time savings we gained here were, however, subsequently lost when we inadvertantly picked up the wrong suitcase at baggage reclaim – I ask you, what are the chances of somebody else having the exact same model of case, <em>and</em> tying a blue ribbon around the handle to make it more easily identifiable?  Less minimal than we expected, evidently…</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>USA Trip 2006: Departure</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/usa-trip-2006-departure/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 May 2006 21:05:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/usa-trip-2006-departure/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last month Jocelyn and I took a trip to the States to visit friends and family, attend Teri &amp;amp; Jimmy’s wedding, and take a vacation to Nevada and Arizona.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, there we were, sitting at the departure gate at Manchester Airport on a bright Monday morning, having awoken at 0430 to make our way across the Pennines.  A few seats away were a group of teenagers.  They were from Michigan, and they were annoyingly noisy.  Thus began our American adventure.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Last month Jocelyn and I took a trip to the States to visit friends and family, attend Teri &amp; Jimmy’s wedding, and take a vacation to Nevada and Arizona.</p>
<p>So, there we were, sitting at the departure gate at Manchester Airport on a bright Monday morning, having awoken at 0430 to make our way across the Pennines.  A few seats away were a group of teenagers.  They were from Michigan, and they were annoyingly noisy.  Thus began our American adventure.</p>
<p>Joce was the first to show irritation at her countrymen – &ldquo;God, why is it that only the fat obnoxious noisy American choose to travel abroad?&rdquo;.  In retrospect, I’m not sure that’s true – it’s just that, by their nature, you’re more likely to notice obnoxious noisy people, of any nationality, and the non-native accents just make them stand out even more.  As it happened, there were some British teens mixed into the group – some kind of exchange trip between West Yorkshire and Michigan, no doubt providing some well-earned relief for the parents.</p>
<p>Ignoring this noise, we focused our attentions instead on the cute little lass (circa 2 or 3 years?) wandering round with wide eyes, and playing with her dad.<br>
&ldquo;We’ll have kids like that,&rdquo; Joce told me.</p>
<p>Yikes!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
