<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Fun on Ian Nelson</title>
    <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/categories/fun/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Fun on Ian Nelson</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.146.6</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 16 May 2025 20:51:16 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://blog.iannelson.uk/categories/fun/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Who Reigns Supreme? Parsing Our WhatsApp Chat for Wordle Glory</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/who-reigns-supreme-parsing-our-whatsapp-chat-for-wordle-glory/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 15:42:39 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/who-reigns-supreme-parsing-our-whatsapp-chat-for-wordle-glory/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Back in 2022, in a bid to outwit my mother in our daily Wordle battles, I wrote some C# code to explore optimal starting guesses. &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.iannelson.uk/the-best-wordle-starter-words/&#34;&gt;You can read about that experiment here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fast forward two years, and my Wordle addiction is alive and well. The daily challenge remains as compelling as ever, but it’s the family WhatsApp group – where scores are shared, victories boasted, and failures commiserated – that adds an extra layer of fun.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Back in 2022, in a bid to outwit my mother in our daily Wordle battles, I wrote some C# code to explore optimal starting guesses. <a href="https://blog.iannelson.uk/the-best-wordle-starter-words/">You can read about that experiment here</a>.</p>
<p>Fast forward two years, and my Wordle addiction is alive and well. The daily challenge remains as compelling as ever, but it’s the family WhatsApp group – where scores are shared, victories boasted, and failures commiserated – that adds an extra layer of fun.</p>
<p>As 2024 winds down, I decided to dust off my coding skills and whip up a quick C# console application. The goal? To parse an export of our WhatsApp chat, gather all the shared Wordle scores, and find out if my strategies have paid off this year. Spoiler alert: they haven’t.</p>
<p>If you’ve got a similar Wordle-centric group chat with family or friends and fancy crowning your own Wordle Champion of the Year, the source code is available on GitHub: <a href="https://github.com/ianfnelson/WordleParser">WordleParser</a>.</p>
<h2 id="how-it-works">How It Works</h2>
<p>The application takes a single argument: the path to an exported chat text file. It parses the file using a <a href="https://github.com/ianfnelson/WordleParser/blob/main/WordleParser/WordleParser.cs#L46">regular expression</a> to extract anything resembling a Wordle score. <a href="https://github.com/ianfnelson/WordleParser/blob/main/WordleParser/WordleParser.cs#L27">Duplicate scores are weeded out</a>, and the <a href="https://github.com/ianfnelson/WordleParser/blob/main/WordleParser/WordleParser.cs#L32">average family score for each calendar day is logged</a>. For those unfortunate days when a puzzle remains unsolved, the application <a href="https://github.com/ianfnelson/WordleParser/blob/main/WordleParser/WordleParser.cs#L59">assigns a ‘seven’</a> to reflect the failure.</p>
<p>The app then aggregates scores into calendar <a href="https://github.com/ianfnelson/WordleParser/blob/main/WordleParser/WordleParser.cs#L17">months</a> and <a href="https://github.com/ianfnelson/WordleParser/blob/main/WordleParser/WordleParser.cs#L11">years</a>, <a href="https://github.com/ianfnelson/WordleParser/blob/main/WordleParser/WordleParser.cs#L76">calculating each family member’s stats for the chosen date range</a>. Participants are ranked based on their mean difference from the average family score per day.</p>
<p>For example, if three family members scored a 4, but one managed a dazzling 2, the day’s average would be 3.5. The three “fours” would each have a daily difference of +0.5, while the lucky “two” would boast a difference of -1.5.</p>
<h2 id="the-results">The Results</h2>
<p>So, who triumphed in the Nelson family Wordle-off this year? Did my painstaking analysis from 2022 finally give me the edge?</p>
<p>Reader, it did not.</p>
<p>Despite my best efforts, I only just managed to sneak into second place. Predictably, my mother reigned supreme, crushing us all with an average score of <strong>4.055</strong> and a mean difference from the family average of <strong>-0.128</strong>. This consistency made her our undisputed <strong>Wordle Family Champion of 2024</strong>.</p>
<p><img alt="Nelson Family Wordle Champion 2024" loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2024/12/7DD41AB4-B664-4276-B1A1-3E9EA0F0DFB7-1.jpeg"></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Best Wordle Starter Words</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/the-best-wordle-starter-words/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Jan 2022 19:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/the-best-wordle-starter-words/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Like (it would seem) most of the rest of humanity, the start of my 2022 has been immeasurably enhanced by starting each day playing &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.powerlanguage.co.uk/&#34;&gt;Josh Wardle’s&lt;/a&gt; charming word game &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.powerlanguage.co.uk/wordle/&#34;&gt;Wordle&lt;/a&gt;. Which got me wondering – what are the best starter words to play in the opening lines at Wordle? I have been habitually using “&lt;strong&gt;ADIEU&lt;/strong&gt;” as my starter word, reasoning that it contains a large number of vowels. But is &lt;strong&gt;D&lt;/strong&gt; a particularly common consonant? And should I be trying to get &lt;strong&gt;O&lt;/strong&gt; in there rather than the less frequently used &lt;strong&gt;U&lt;/strong&gt;? I decided to do some computer-aided analysis to find the answer.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Like (it would seem) most of the rest of humanity, the start of my 2022 has been immeasurably enhanced by starting each day playing <a href="https://www.powerlanguage.co.uk/">Josh Wardle’s</a> charming word game <a href="https://www.powerlanguage.co.uk/wordle/">Wordle</a>. Which got me wondering – what are the best starter words to play in the opening lines at Wordle? I have been habitually using “<strong>ADIEU</strong>” as my starter word, reasoning that it contains a large number of vowels. But is <strong>D</strong> a particularly common consonant? And should I be trying to get <strong>O</strong> in there rather than the less frequently used <strong>U</strong>? I decided to do some computer-aided analysis to find the answer.</p>
<p><em><strong>SPOILER WARNING</strong> – this blog post contains information that may lead you to play more optimal Wordle starter words than you otherwise would have done if left to your own imagination. If you consider that this may take the fun out of an enjoyable daily practice, then I suggest that you stop reading. Now.</em></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2023/08/photo-1512799906445-d591d53082c0cropentropyampcstinysrgbampfitmaxampfmjpgampixidMnwxMTc3M3wwfDF8c2VhcmNofDR8fGNsb3NlZCUyMGV5ZXN8ZW58MHx8fHwxNjQyNTM4MzU2ampixlibrb-1.2.jpg">
Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@ryoji__iwata?utm_source=ghost&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=api-credit">Ryoji Iwata</a> / <a href="https://unsplash.com/?utm_source=ghost&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=api-credit">Unsplash</a></p>
<h2 id="definition">Definition</h2>
<p>Still here? OK, first a definition. What do I consider to be a good Wordle starter word? What makes one starter word better than another?</p>
<p>I assert that the best Wordle starter words are those which are expected to result in the highest number of yellow (right letter, wrong spot) or green (right letter, right spot) tiles. Let’s call this E(Y|G).  As a tie-breaker, where two words have the same value of E(Y|G), I consider the better word to be the one which is expected to result in the highest number of green tiles – let’s call this E(G).</p>
<p>I’ve seen alternative approaches posted on Twitter that rank guesses in different ways, such as one which was based on how many possible answers from the Wordle corpus are excluded by guessing them. But my brain doesn’t work that way round – I don’t have the full list of Wordle words in my head to sieve through, and instead seek the positive reinforcement of yellow and green tiles to use as the basis for my later guesses.</p>
<h2 id="assumption">Assumption</h2>
<p>There are 12,972 valid words in the Wordle dictionary. For the purposes of this analysis, I’m going to assume that they all have an equal likelihood of being the Wordle answer on any given day. Clearly this is not true. I’ve only been playing Wordle for a couple of weeks but it’s immediately apparent that the winning words tend to be those in common everyday use. I doubt that the game would have its current levels of popularity were this not the case. My nine year old son loves playing Wordle every day, and this shared common bond is one of the things that makes Wordle so fun. There was quite some brouhaha on Twitter when the answer to Wordle 207 was the US English spelling of “<strong>FAVOR</strong>“, I can only imagine what an uproar there would be if the answer was ever something truly random like “<strong>QAJAQ</strong>“, “<strong>XYLYL</strong>” or “<strong>HYPHY</strong>“. But I digress. Whatever aspects of curation are taking place to select the daily Wordle, be it automated or human, I’m going to ignore it and assume that the Wordle is chosen randomly from the list of valid Wordle words.</p>
<h2 id="the-top-10-best-wordle-starter-words">The Top 10 Best Wordle Starter Words</h2>
<p>This is your last chance to look away. Having iterated through all 168,272,784 pairs of guessed word and answer, here are the ten best Wordle starter words</p>
<table>
  <thead>
      <tr>
          <th>Rank</th>
          <th>Word</th>
          <th>E(Y|G)</th>
          <th>E(G)</th>
      </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
      <tr>
          <td>1.</td>
          <td>AEROS</td>
          <td>1.91111</td>
          <td>0.63360</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>2.</td>
          <td>SOARE</td>
          <td>1.91111</td>
          <td>0.55026</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>3.</td>
          <td>AROSE</td>
          <td>1.91111</td>
          <td>0.36294</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>4.</td>
          <td>REAIS</td>
          <td>1.88629</td>
          <td>0.64215</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>5.</td>
          <td>RAISE</td>
          <td>1.88629</td>
          <td>0.46099</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>6.</td>
          <td>SERAI</td>
          <td>1.88629</td>
          <td>0.44288</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>7.</td>
          <td>ARISE</td>
          <td>1.88629</td>
          <td>0.36741</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>8.</td>
          <td>AESIR</td>
          <td>1.88629</td>
          <td>0.34312</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>9.</td>
          <td>ALOES</td>
          <td>1.84983</td>
          <td>0.67175</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>10.</td>
          <td>LARES</td>
          <td>1.84968</td>
          <td>0.79579</td>
      </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>
<p>Therefore, if you want to turn over the highest number of yellow and green tiles on your first Wordle play, and favour seeing the green tiles, then “<strong>AEROS</strong>” is your best bet. By comparison my previous favourite of “<strong>ADIEU</strong>” has an E(Y|G) of 1.49229 and E(G) of 0.32886.</p>
<h2 id="the-best-words-to-play-second">The Best Words To Play Second</h2>
<p>But what comes next? What words are best to play on the second line? It depends how you like to play the game. If you’re like my mother, or have “hard mode” turned on, then your second and subsequent guesses will be influenced by the hints received in response to your first guess.</p>
<p>On the other hand, if you’re like me, at this early stage you’ll want to continue exploring the full breadth of the alphabet to increase the probability of identifying additional letters in the answer. For example I have generally been following up my “<strong>ADIEU</strong>” starter with “<strong>GHOST</strong>” to finish off the vowels and include <strong>T</strong> and <strong>S</strong> in the mix.</p>
<p>With this in mind, I extended my analysis to determine the combined E(Y|G) and E(G) values for pairs of valid Wordle words. All of the best results came from pairing together words that cover 10 distinct letters. Perhaps that seems intuitive, but it wasn’t a foregone conclusion. There are many guesses containing repeated letters which have excellent prospects, especially those with pairs of <strong>E</strong> or <strong>S</strong>. “<strong>EASER</strong>” is the best of these with an E(Y|G) of 1.68039, and pleasingly even “<strong>ARSES</strong>” weighs in with an E(Y|G) of 1.66489.</p>
<p>Here are the ten best combinations of ten letters to cover with the first two guesses, with an example of two valid Wordle words covering those letters:</p>
<table>
  <thead>
      <tr>
          <th>Rank</th>
          <th>Letters</th>
          <th>Example Words</th>
          <th>Combined E(Y|G)</th>
      </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
      <tr>
          <td>1.</td>
          <td>AEILNORSTU</td>
          <td>AEROS, UNLIT</td>
          <td>3.06429</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>2.</td>
          <td>ADEILNORTS</td>
          <td>ADITS, ENROL</td>
          <td>3.05365</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>3.</td>
          <td>AEILONRSTY</td>
          <td>AEROS, LINTY</td>
          <td>3.03307</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>4.</td>
          <td>ADEILORSTU</td>
          <td>ADIEU, ROTLS</td>
          <td>3.02660</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>5.</td>
          <td>ACEILNORST</td>
          <td>ACNES, LIROT</td>
          <td>3.02451</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>6.</td>
          <td>AEILONPRST</td>
          <td>AIRTS, PELON</td>
          <td>3.02182</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>7.</td>
          <td>AIMERSTOLN</td>
          <td>AIMER, STOLN</td>
          <td>3.02051</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>8.</td>
          <td>AEHILNORST</td>
          <td>AEONS, THIRL</td>
          <td>3.00817</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>9.</td>
          <td>ADEILNORSU</td>
          <td>ADORN, ILEUS</td>
          <td>3.00763</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>10.</td>
          <td>AEILORSTUY</td>
          <td>AIERY, LOTUS</td>
          <td>3.00601</td>
      </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>
<p>By comparison, my previous favoured pairing of “<strong>ADIEU</strong>” and “<strong>GHOST</strong>” has an E(Y|G) of 2.7358. Switching to a combination of words that covers the letters AEILNORSTU such as “<strong>AEROS</strong>” and “<strong>UNLIT</strong>” should boost my expected number of hints from my first two guesses by 12%!</p>
<h2 id="the-best-of-the-best">The Best of the Best</h2>
<p>But which two words to pick? There are no fewer than <strong>300 combinations</strong> of valid Wordle words which cover those best ten letters, all having a combined E(Y|G) of 3.06429. Again, I decided to use E(G) as a tie-breaker, which leads to the following ranking of pairs of starting words:</p>
<table>
  <thead>
      <tr>
          <th>Rank</th>
          <th>Word 1</th>
          <th>Word 1 E(Y|G)</th>
          <th>Word 2</th>
          <th>Word 2 E(Y|G)</th>
          <th>Combined E(G)</th>
      </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
      <tr>
          <td>1.</td>
          <td>TAILS</td>
          <td>1.61903</td>
          <td>ROUEN</td>
          <td>1.44527</td>
          <td>1.16454</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>2.</td>
          <td>TARNS</td>
          <td>1.61849</td>
          <td>LOUIE</td>
          <td>1.44581</td>
          <td>1.13818</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>3.</td>
          <td>LORES</td>
          <td>1.74029</td>
          <td>TUINA</td>
          <td>1.32401</td>
          <td>1.13146</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>4.</td>
          <td>RAILE</td>
          <td>1.66875</td>
          <td>TOUNS</td>
          <td>1.39554</td>
          <td>1.39554</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>5.</td>
          <td>TAINS</td>
          <td>1.59382</td>
          <td>ROULE</td>
          <td>1.47047</td>
          <td>1.12243</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>6.</td>
          <td>RAUNS</td>
          <td>1.57246</td>
          <td>TOILE</td>
          <td>1.49183</td>
          <td>1.12239</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>7.</td>
          <td>RAILE</td>
          <td>1.66875</td>
          <td>TONUS</td>
          <td>1.39554</td>
          <td>1.11549</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>8.</td>
          <td>TOLES</td>
          <td>1.67276</td>
          <td>NAIRU</td>
          <td>1.39153</td>
          <td>1.11543</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>9.</td>
          <td>TAINS</td>
          <td>1.59382</td>
          <td>LOURE</td>
          <td>1.47047</td>
          <td>1.11443</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>10.</td>
          <td>RANTS</td>
          <td>1.61849</td>
          <td>LOUIE</td>
          <td>1.44581</td>
          <td>1.11417</td>
      </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="adieu-adieu">Adieu, “ADIEU”</h2>
<p>So there you have it. Having crunched the numbers, my new pair of Wordle starter words from tomorrow morning shall be “<strong>TAILS</strong>” followed by “<strong>ROUEN</strong>“. <a href="https://twitter.com/ianfnelson">Follow me on Twitter</a> to see how it works out for me. I have a suspicion that despite this analysis, my mother will still reach the answer in fewer guesses than me more often than not!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Inherent Negativity of Computer Programmers</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/on-the-inherent-negativity-of-computer-programmers/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2010 20:02:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/on-the-inherent-negativity-of-computer-programmers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A couple of weeks ago, early one morning, my friend and fellow coder Scott asked a curious question:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Do you think that programming computers for a living gives you a negative outlook on life?”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, Scott is unfortunately responsible for administering occasional TLC to a codebase that I cut as long ago as 2004, so I assumed he was referring to this and was about to raise some complaints about my hand-rolled query object criteria framework or other coding horror. I steeled myself to defend my work as he continued to explain:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A couple of weeks ago, early one morning, my friend and fellow coder Scott asked a curious question:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“Do you think that programming computers for a living gives you a negative outlook on life?”</p></blockquote>
<p>Now, Scott is unfortunately responsible for administering occasional TLC to a codebase that I cut as long ago as 2004, so I assumed he was referring to this and was about to raise some complaints about my hand-rolled query object criteria framework or other coding horror. I steeled myself to defend my work as he continued to explain:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“Well, when coding we have to consider all the potential edge cases and exceptions – what happens if our methods get dodgy inputs etcetera. And it’s spilling over into my real life. We’re moving house at the moment, and I just find myself worrying about what happens if the buyers pull out, if we can’t get the mortgage, if the survey reveals problems… I’m really negative about the whole process.”</p></blockquote>
<p>At the time I smiled and put this down to the notoriously tortuous British house-buying process, but the more I think about it, the more I think Scott might be onto something.</p>
<p><img alt="Pissed Off Ian, by John Conners" loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2023/08/310411215_3dd7f5cd07_m_1__3.jpg"></p>
<p>My wife and I are currently plotting a well-deserved summer vacation in sunnier climes, which theoretically should be an enjoyable task, right? But I can’t simply enjoy it and focus on the “sunny-day scenario”. My mind is full of edge cases (“What if we can’t fit all our stuff in the car?”), unhandled exceptions (“Will we get our passports in time?”), compatibility issues (“will our choice of dates suit my clients?”), unwise over-reliance on dependent components (“Will the airline have any child seats available?”) and of course user errors (“Suppose we book the wrong dates?!”). No focusing on the happy path for this codemonkey.</p>
<p>The more I think about it, the more I see that Scott has a point. Professional software development forces us to anticipate invalid input, stupid users, hackers,  insufficient hardware, unreachable remote services, and whether our software can pass <a href="http://www.moserware.com/2008/02/does-your-code-pass-turkey-test.html">the Turkey test</a>. We consider SQL injection, cross-site scripting, buffer overflows, and countless other common <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Category:Computer_security_exploits">threats and exploits</a>. Not to mention worrying about what happens when other devs get their grubby mitts on our codebase, or when the client inevitably unleashes some game-changing requirements late in the lifecycle. We’re all about expecting the worse, coding <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Defensive_programming">defensively</a>, and decoupling ourselves from dependencies. The ever-present potential for high-profile failures caused by something as simple as an inverted boolean comparison, combined with the likelihood of critique and criticism from our fellow coders, DBAs, auditors and sysadmins is enough to turn most devs into a nervous wreck before they’ve so much as initialised a variable. That reminds me, I must check that my Professional Indemnity insurance policy is up to date.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2023/08/sb_2.png"></p>
<p>So, anecdotal evidence and my own experience suggests to me that Border’s First Law is a truism. Programming Computers Can Cause Negativity, Cynicism and Pessimism.</p>
<p>Are these necessarily negative traits to have, or can such enforced forethought and consideration of potential issues be a benefit in “real life”, away from the screen? I suspect as with many things, the answer is that there is some balance to be had. So – getting to the airport on time is A Good Thing. Spending a fortnight’s vacation panicking on the offchance that the flight operator goes bust is, probabilistically, a bit silly.</p>
<p>I’m not sure where I’m going with this, or what the answer is, except perhaps to be a little more aware of this mindset and try to adopt a little restrain when applying programming principles to “real-life” conversations. Life, alas, is not a well-defined algorithm, and God knows it doesn’t come complete with a full suite of regression tests.</p>
<p>PS – You know, I just remembered that I <a href="https://blog.iannelson.uk/edge-cases/">blogged about this topic before</a>!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deduplication Fail</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/deduplication-fail/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Dec 2009 12:12:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/deduplication-fail/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Oh, the irony!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img loading=&#34;lazy&#34; src=&#34;https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2023/08/Deduplication_2.png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Oh, the irony!</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2023/08/Deduplication_2.png"></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Primality In Packsizes</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/on-primality-in-packsizes/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Oct 2009 10:10:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/on-primality-in-packsizes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Benny George, our precocious two-year-old, is quite the fan of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bbc.co.uk/cbeebies/mistermaker/&#34;&gt;Mister Maker&lt;/a&gt;, and enjoys spending time doing arty crafty stuff with his mum. Now, the great thing about the BBC is that they tend to suggest projects which can be created using bits and bobs that you’re likely to have around the home – old cereal boxes and the like. But occasionally some specialist resources have to be procured in the name of Ben’s art, and so it was that Joce today spent £1.99 on a pack of the “googly eyes” so beloved of Maker.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Benny George, our precocious two-year-old, is quite the fan of <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/cbeebies/mistermaker/">Mister Maker</a>, and enjoys spending time doing arty crafty stuff with his mum. Now, the great thing about the BBC is that they tend to suggest projects which can be created using bits and bobs that you’re likely to have around the home – old cereal boxes and the like. But occasionally some specialist resources have to be procured in the name of Ben’s art, and so it was that Joce today spent £1.99 on a pack of the “googly eyes” so beloved of Maker.</p>
<p><img alt="Oooh la la Mister Maker!" loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2023/08/mistermaker_slideshow4_385_3.jpg"></p>
<p>Here’s the thing though – I couldn’t help but noticing that these 20mm googly eyes come in packs of <em>seventeen</em>. Joce charitably suggested that this was simply the number of eyes that could fit in the packet, but I am more cynical. Can it really be a coincidence that <em>eyes</em> – which are surely generally found in pairs – are sold in an odd quantity, forcing the purchaser to buy slightly more than they required?</p>
<p>And we’re not just looking at an odd number here – 17 is prime too, so even if you happened to be creating models of, say, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tuatara">the three-eyed Tuatara lizard</a>, you’re still going to end up with some product left over or feel obliged to buy another pack.</p>
<p>Cunning folk, these googly eye marketers, and it makes me wonder why other manufacturers stick to selling their products in multiples of integers with many divisors. Ease of packaging, perhaps.</p>
<p>What other products are sold in prime quantities?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New Office Photos</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/new-office-photos/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 May 2009 07:05:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/new-office-photos/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I promised you some photos of my new office a while back, didn’t I? OK, here you go…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;The Desk&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; src=&#34;https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2023/08/3542421968_6e26feee92_b.jpg&#34;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;The Computer&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; src=&#34;https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2023/08/3542422352_90c1bfc575_b.jpg&#34;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;One of These Books Is Not Like The Others&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; src=&#34;https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2023/08/3541613985_66cced4663_b.jpg&#34;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;Bits n Bobs&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; src=&#34;https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2023/08/3541614871_41633d1a8a_b.jpg&#34;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;In Gnasher We Trust&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; src=&#34;https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2023/08/3542422842_a7532a6094_b.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I promised you some photos of my new office a while back, didn’t I? OK, here you go…</p>
<p><img alt="The Desk" loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2023/08/3542421968_6e26feee92_b.jpg">
<img alt="The Computer" loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2023/08/3542422352_90c1bfc575_b.jpg">
<img alt="One of These Books Is Not Like The Others" loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2023/08/3541613985_66cced4663_b.jpg">
<img alt="Bits n Bobs" loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2023/08/3541614871_41633d1a8a_b.jpg">
<img alt="In Gnasher We Trust" loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2023/08/3542422842_a7532a6094_b.jpg"></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Zero Interest Bug Arrives</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/zero-interest-bug-arrives/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2009 15:02:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/zero-interest-bug-arrives/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;So, base rates are now down to 1.0%, and the &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.iannelson.uk/zero-interest-bug/&#34;&gt;Zero Interest Bug&lt;/a&gt; is not just conjecture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/money/property_and_mortgages/article5668432.ece&#34;&gt;The Times&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“About 1,500 customers who took out a tracker mortgages pegged at 1.01 points below the base rate with Cheltenham &amp;amp; Gloucester (C&amp;amp;G), owned by Lloyds Banking Group, will be paying no interest at all on their home loans from next month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is the first time that a mortgage lender has been forced to reduce the interest on their home loans to zero.
Lloyds Banking Group, now 43 per cent owned by the taxpayer and also the owner of C&amp;amp;G, said that there was a zero floor to the deal and that &lt;strong&gt;because its computer systems could not cope with zero&lt;/strong&gt;, it would be temporarily charging 0.001 per cent, or 8p a month for a borrower with a £100,000 mortgage. However, that money will be refunded.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>So, base rates are now down to 1.0%, and the <a href="https://blog.iannelson.uk/zero-interest-bug/">Zero Interest Bug</a> is not just conjecture.</p>
<p>From <a href="http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/money/property_and_mortgages/article5668432.ece">The Times</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“About 1,500 customers who took out a tracker mortgages pegged at 1.01 points below the base rate with Cheltenham &amp; Gloucester (C&amp;G), owned by Lloyds Banking Group, will be paying no interest at all on their home loans from next month.</p>
<p>It is the first time that a mortgage lender has been forced to reduce the interest on their home loans to zero.
Lloyds Banking Group, now 43 per cent owned by the taxpayer and also the owner of C&amp;G, said that there was a zero floor to the deal and that <strong>because its computer systems could not cope with zero</strong>, it would be temporarily charging 0.001 per cent, or 8p a month for a borrower with a £100,000 mortgage. However, that money will be refunded.”</p></blockquote>
<p>I bet those jammy 1,500 people are feeling quite smug today. Needless to say, I’m still kicking myself very hard for fixing my mortgage last summer… sob!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What&#39;s In Your Wallet?</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/whats-in-your-wallet/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Aug 2008 21:08:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/whats-in-your-wallet/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My good buddy &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.johnsadventures.com&#34;&gt;John&lt;/a&gt; just published &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.johnsadventures.com/archives/2008/08/the-contents-of-my-wallet.html&#34;&gt;a typically navel-gazing post detailing the contents of his wallet&lt;/a&gt;, and went on to invite readers to divulge details of their own &lt;em&gt;billfolds&lt;/em&gt; in what I can only presume is some cunning and evil plan for mass identity-theft 🙂&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, as I said in the comments to John’s post, I was surprised at the quantity of sentimental knick-knacks and memorabilia he has in there, compared to the rather prosaic and functional contents of my own wallet.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>My good buddy <a href="http://www.johnsadventures.com">John</a> just published <a href="http://www.johnsadventures.com/archives/2008/08/the-contents-of-my-wallet.html">a typically navel-gazing post detailing the contents of his wallet</a>, and went on to invite readers to divulge details of their own <em>billfolds</em> in what I can only presume is some cunning and evil plan for mass identity-theft 🙂</p>
<p>Well, as I said in the comments to John’s post, I was surprised at the quantity of sentimental knick-knacks and memorabilia he has in there, compared to the rather prosaic and functional contents of my own wallet.</p>
<p>The wallet itself is a simple black leather one from <a href="http://www.burberry.com">Burberry</a>, and tonight contains the following:</p>
<ul>
<li>£90. In case you were thinking of mugging me, you should know that I don’t usually carry nearly so much.</li>
<li>A bunch of receipts from the week. Come tomorrow evening the details will all have been religiously input into MS Money, and the receipts shredded.</li>
<li>Four first-class stamps.</li>
<li>A Starbucks card – essential for those occasional lunches with John 🙂</li>
<li>Three credit cards, one from each of the major providers. You can never be sure which will be accepted, and the occasional system failure or over-zealous anti-fraud software has resulted in me having to offer all three before a transaction could be processed.</li>
<li>A debit card, which I mostly use this for taking cash out of ATMs. I don’t see the point in using it for payments if I can help it, preferring to get the interest-free period and insurance that comes from using a credit card instead.</li>
<li>My Microsoft Certified Professional card. I’m not sure what the point of carrying this is – maybe I won’t put it back!</li>
<li>A “Club Toyota” membership card. I don’t really get the point of this one, either.</li>
<li>A membership card for my local gym. This whole gym-going malarkey is a relatively new thing for me, and I’m grateful to my wifey for persuading me to join, as I feel much fitter for getting a bit of exercise a few times a week. I think having kids is a big incentive to start taking care of yourself, as you want to stick around as long as possible to share their lives.</li>
<li>A Costco trade membership card. One of the nice perks of being a company director is being able to go to Costco and buy 45 toilet rolls and a gallon of Tabasco whenever I fancy!</li>
<li>National Trust membership card. We find ourselves wandering round stately piles quite often, in an effort to Bentertain the one year old.</li>
<li>Driving license.</li>
<li>North Yorkshire County Libraries card. Libraries gave us power!</li>
<li>“Loyalty” cards from Boots, Shell, WHSmith, Coop, Tesco and Nectar. I’m not very loyal, but I don’t look a gift horse in the mouth.</li>
</ul>
<p>And that’s your lot. Not very interesting really, eh?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Edge Cases</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/edge-cases/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Dec 2007 14:12:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/edge-cases/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Ten years of professional software development have given me a healthy awareness of edge cases – I’m always trying to code defensively, validate input, catch exceptions, use assertions, and of course pick holes in sloppy specifications (“ah, but what if…”).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I must learn that these skills should not always be applied to my personal life though, as exemplified by a conversation with The Wife yesterday:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;_Jocelyn (excitedly): “We’re going to have a &amp;lsquo;Secret Santa&amp;rsquo; for all the babies in our antenatal group!”&lt;br&gt;
Me: “Huh. How does that work then?”&lt;br&gt;
Jocelyn: “Well, we each buy a gift for under £10, put them into a bag, and each pick one.”&lt;br&gt;
Me: “What happens if you pick out the gift you bought?”&lt;br&gt;
Jocelyn (less excitedly): “Well, you put it back and pick another.”&lt;br&gt;
Me: “So, you have an even number of babies in the group?”&lt;br&gt;
Jocelyn (testily): “There are seven.”&lt;br&gt;
Me: “Then what happens if the last person picks their own gift?”&lt;br&gt;
Jocelyn (deflated): “Ian…!  OK, so we won’t open any gifts until they’re all selected – happy now?”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Ten years of professional software development have given me a healthy awareness of edge cases – I’m always trying to code defensively, validate input, catch exceptions, use assertions, and of course pick holes in sloppy specifications (“ah, but what if…”).</p>
<p>I must learn that these skills should not always be applied to my personal life though, as exemplified by a conversation with The Wife yesterday:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>_Jocelyn (excitedly): “We’re going to have a &lsquo;Secret Santa&rsquo; for all the babies in our antenatal group!”<br>
Me: “Huh. How does that work then?”<br>
Jocelyn: “Well, we each buy a gift for under £10, put them into a bag, and each pick one.”<br>
Me: “What happens if you pick out the gift you bought?”<br>
Jocelyn (less excitedly): “Well, you put it back and pick another.”<br>
Me: “So, you have an even number of babies in the group?”<br>
Jocelyn (testily): “There are seven.”<br>
Me: “Then what happens if the last person picks their own gift?”<br>
Jocelyn (deflated): “Ian…!  OK, so we won’t open any gifts until they’re all selected – happy now?”</p></blockquote>
<p>I was. In my mind this is like recursively calling an algorithm if a post-check fails. It’s an unusual approach, but it should work OK here.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Postcode Validation</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/postcode-validation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 May 2007 13:05:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/postcode-validation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Wikipedia cracks me up sometimes. I’m sat here at my desk, trying to knock together some C# code to quickly validate an entered string as being a UK postcode. Naturally I turned to this &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/UK_postcodes&#34;&gt;Wikipedia article&lt;/a&gt; for assistance, where I find this quip:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Automatic validation of postcodes on the basis of pattern feasibility is therefore almost impossible to design, and the system contains no self-validating feature such as a check digit. &lt;strong&gt;Completely accurate validation is only possible by attempting to deliver mail to the address, and verifying with the recipient.&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Wikipedia cracks me up sometimes. I’m sat here at my desk, trying to knock together some C# code to quickly validate an entered string as being a UK postcode. Naturally I turned to this <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/UK_postcodes">Wikipedia article</a> for assistance, where I find this quip:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>&ldquo;Automatic validation of postcodes on the basis of pattern feasibility is therefore almost impossible to design, and the system contains no self-validating feature such as a check digit. <strong>Completely accurate validation is only possible by attempting to deliver mail to the address, and verifying with the recipient.</strong>&rdquo;</p></blockquote>
<p>I think that’s what is known as a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Long_running_transaction">long-running transaction</a>!!</p>
<p><strong>Update</strong> – the C# code that I wrote to handle this issue is available <a href="https://blog.iannelson.uk/a-c-postcode-struct-with-parser/">here</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spot The Misleading Graph</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/spot-the-misleading-graph/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Feb 2007 19:02:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/spot-the-misleading-graph/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Fifty-three years since Darrell Huff published the seminal &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/0140136290?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=ianesbl-21&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=1634&amp;amp;creative=6738&amp;amp;creativeASIN=0140136290&#34;&gt;How to Lie with Statistics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, and still we have newspapers as august as &lt;em&gt;The Times&lt;/em&gt; pulling the oldest trick in the book:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img loading=&#34;lazy&#34; src=&#34;https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2023/08/times.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At first glance it all looks very impressive, but closer inspection of the comparison with sales of the Torygraph reveal a mere 8.7% sales lead, not more than double as suggested by the graphic.Not fooled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another favourite book of mine that covers the still-relevant topic of graphical integrity is Edward Tufte’s &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/0961392142?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=ianesbl-21&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=1634&amp;amp;creative=6738&amp;amp;creativeASIN=0961392142&#34;&gt;The Visual Display of Quantitative Information&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. It’s one of those timeless works that I look forward to sharing with the next generation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Fifty-three years since Darrell Huff published the seminal <em><a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/0140136290?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=ianesbl-21&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1634&amp;creative=6738&amp;creativeASIN=0140136290">How to Lie with Statistics</a></em>, and still we have newspapers as august as <em>The Times</em> pulling the oldest trick in the book:</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2023/08/times.jpg"></p>
<p>At first glance it all looks very impressive, but closer inspection of the comparison with sales of the Torygraph reveal a mere 8.7% sales lead, not more than double as suggested by the graphic.Not fooled.</p>
<p>Another favourite book of mine that covers the still-relevant topic of graphical integrity is Edward Tufte’s <em><a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/0961392142?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=ianesbl-21&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1634&amp;creative=6738&amp;creativeASIN=0961392142">The Visual Display of Quantitative Information</a></em>. It’s one of those timeless works that I look forward to sharing with the next generation.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dangling Off A Skyscraper</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/dangling-off-a-skyscraper/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Feb 2007 16:02:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/dangling-off-a-skyscraper/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I keep intending, and forgetting to post a couple of videos from our US holiday last April. I suppose I was hoping to get round to writing up my paper notes from the holiday, but it’s becoming apparent that won’t happen anytime soon, so let’s skip forward to the funny bits:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We spent a couple of nights at the Stratosphere Hotel in Las Vegas, which is the tallest observation tower in the United States. Atop the tower are three “thrill rides”, and I foolishly tried all of them whilst Jocelyn videoed proceedings from a safe distance.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I keep intending, and forgetting to post a couple of videos from our US holiday last April. I suppose I was hoping to get round to writing up my paper notes from the holiday, but it’s becoming apparent that won’t happen anytime soon, so let’s skip forward to the funny bits:</p>
<p>We spent a couple of nights at the Stratosphere Hotel in Las Vegas, which is the tallest observation tower in the United States. Atop the tower are three “thrill rides”, and I foolishly tried all of them whilst Jocelyn videoed proceedings from a safe distance.</p>
<p>The Big Shot, at 329m high is the highest ride in the world. This is essentially a big pole with seats around the side that flings you straight up, quickly, and drops you down again. You’ve probably seen these elsewhere, this is much the same except it happens to be on the top of a very tall building and hence offers mighty fine views over the Las Vegas desert. We don’t have any video of this as it all happened a bit too quickly for Joce to catch.</p>
<p>X-Scream, at 264m high is the third highest ride in the world. This is basically a glorified bench that dangles off the edge of the building, and it is one of the scariest things I’ve ever experienced!  From inside the building Jocelyn captured the video below – turn up the volume to hear some Aussie tourists laughing at my predicament!</p>
<div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
      <iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" loading="eager" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/ANTRHMjBRbU?autoplay=0&amp;controls=1&amp;end=0&amp;loop=0&amp;mute=0&amp;start=0" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" title="YouTube video"></iframe>
    </div>

<p>Insanity, at 274m high is the second highest ride in the world. According to Wikipedia, “it dangles riders over the edge of the tower and then spins in a circular pattern at approximately forty miles per hour”. This was also pretty scary, though the constant circular motion made it less terrifying than the X-Scream (with its stop-start “aha, you thought you were going to continue falling for another 100+ storeys” shenanigans). Here’s a video of me on the Insanity – can’t think why I’m the only partipant…</p>
<div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
      <iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" loading="eager" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Rv5Ni1hUv_A?autoplay=0&amp;controls=1&amp;end=0&amp;loop=0&amp;mute=0&amp;start=0" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" title="YouTube video"></iframe>
    </div>

<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2023/08/IMG_4371.jpg">
<img loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2023/08/IMG_4379.jpg">
<img loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2023/08/IMG_4381.jpg"></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beer Advent Calendar – Day Twenty-Four</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-day-twenty-four/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Dec 2005 17:12:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-day-twenty-four/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Hertog Jan Doppio Double&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; src=&#34;https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2023/08/hertog-jan-doppio-double_76906363_o.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hertog Jan Doppio Double is the only one of my twenty-four Advent beers to come in a stone cork-stoppered bottle that weighs more than the drink contained within! At 7.3% ABV, it’s also the &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-days-sixteen-and-seventeen/&#34;&gt;second-strongest&lt;/a&gt; drink in my selection, and hence has a real kick to it.That said, it also has a gorgeous malty aroma, and strong aftertaste which beer lovers will appreciate.So whilst it’s not quite my &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-day-six/&#34;&gt;personal favourite&lt;/a&gt; of the twenty-four beers I’ve had the pleasure of sampling this yuletide, it’s certainly an appropriately worthy and warming drink on which to finish.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img alt="Hertog Jan Doppio Double" loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2023/08/hertog-jan-doppio-double_76906363_o.jpg"></p>
<p>Hertog Jan Doppio Double is the only one of my twenty-four Advent beers to come in a stone cork-stoppered bottle that weighs more than the drink contained within! At 7.3% ABV, it’s also the <a href="https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-days-sixteen-and-seventeen/">second-strongest</a> drink in my selection, and hence has a real kick to it.That said, it also has a gorgeous malty aroma, and strong aftertaste which beer lovers will appreciate.So whilst it’s not quite my <a href="https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-day-six/">personal favourite</a> of the twenty-four beers I’ve had the pleasure of sampling this yuletide, it’s certainly an appropriately worthy and warming drink on which to finish.</p>
<p>I’ve been asked to summarise my findings on these beers at the end of the season, and was considering publishing a spreadsheet noting my opinions in various categories (colour, aroma, aftertaste, strength, packaging, cute names…), but having consumed so many fine ales this month, it was beyond me to come up with such a complicated scoring system.Instead, I’ve made an effort to merely triage the beers according to my overall opinion and likelihood of repurchase – those with three stars will be on our shopping list in future, whilst those with one star will be avoided like the plague.</p>
<h2 id="three-star-beers">Three-star beers</h2>
<p><a href="https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-days-thirteen-fourteen-and-fifteen/">Bitter &amp; Twisted</a><br>
<a href="https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-days-thirteen-fourteen-and-fifteen/">Festive Filly</a><br>
<a href="https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-day-twenty-two/">Fraoch</a><br>
<a href="https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-day-twenty-four/">Hertog Jan</a><br>
<a href="https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-day-four/">Nightmare</a><br>
<a href="https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-day-six/">Riggwelter</a><br>
<a href="https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-day-three/">Schiehallion</a><br>
<a href="https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-day-ten/">Whirlygig</a></p>
<h2 id="two-star-beers">Two-star beers</h2>
<p><a href="https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-days-sixteen-and-seventeen/">Delirium Nocturnum</a><br>
<a href="https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-day-twenty-two/">Jingle Knockers</a><br>
<a href="https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-days-sixteen-and-seventeen/">Rolling Hitch</a><br>
<a href="https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-day-nine/">Rosey Nosey</a><br>
<a href="https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-day-twelve/">Leffe Blonde</a><br>
<a href="https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-days-thirteen-fourteen-and-fifteen/">Nessie’s Monster Mash</a><br>
<a href="https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-day-twenty-three/">Ruby Red</a><br>
<a href="https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-day-nineteen/">Smuggler’s Ale</a><br>
<a href="https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-day-one/">Young’s Christmas Pudding Ale</a></p>
<h2 id="one-star-beers">One-star beers</h2>
<p><a href="https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-day-two">Crazy Ed’s Cave Creek Chili Beer</a><br>
<a href="https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-day-twenty/">Honker’s Ale</a><br>
<a href="https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-day-seven/">Kronenbourg Blanc</a><br>
<a href="https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-day-eight/">Mars Magic</a><br>
<a href="https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-day-eighteen/">Morocco Ale</a><br>
<a href="https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-day-eleven/">Rudolph’s Revenge</a><br>
<a href="https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-day-five/">Teignworthy Christmas Cracker</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beer Advent Calendar – Day Twenty-Three</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-day-twenty-three/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Dec 2005 14:12:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-day-twenty-three/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The penultimate beer on my 2005 advent calendar was &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stpetersbrewery.co.uk/range/prod_detail.asp?CatID=1&amp;amp;Code=RUCASE&#34;&gt;Ruby Red&lt;/a&gt; from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stpetersbrewery.co.uk/&#34;&gt;St. Peter’s Brewery&lt;/a&gt; in Suffolk. I’d been looking forward to this 4.3% ABV red ale, which, like all of the beers from St. Peter’s, comes in a distinctive flask-shaped oval bottle, so I was somewhat disappointed by the intense bitterness of the first few mouthfuls. However, I think this was mostly due to the effects of the Mexican dinner laced with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.enconasauces.co.uk&#34;&gt;Encona sauces&lt;/a&gt; that I’d scoffed a few minutes previously. Further into the bottle, the “subtle malt undertones and spicy aroma” became more apparent, and overall I really enjoyed this beer – I’ll definitely be trying some of the others from the range.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The penultimate beer on my 2005 advent calendar was <a href="http://www.stpetersbrewery.co.uk/range/prod_detail.asp?CatID=1&amp;Code=RUCASE">Ruby Red</a> from the <a href="http://www.stpetersbrewery.co.uk/">St. Peter’s Brewery</a> in Suffolk. I’d been looking forward to this 4.3% ABV red ale, which, like all of the beers from St. Peter’s, comes in a distinctive flask-shaped oval bottle, so I was somewhat disappointed by the intense bitterness of the first few mouthfuls. However, I think this was mostly due to the effects of the Mexican dinner laced with <a href="http://www.enconasauces.co.uk">Encona sauces</a> that I’d scoffed a few minutes previously. Further into the bottle, the “subtle malt undertones and spicy aroma” became more apparent, and overall I really enjoyed this beer – I’ll definitely be trying some of the others from the range.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beer Advent Calendar – Day Twenty-Two</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-day-twenty-two/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2005 21:12:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-day-twenty-two/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.fraoch.com/&#34;&gt;Fraoch&lt;/a&gt; is a 5% ABV Scottish beer that brings back many happy memories of late nights spent in the bar at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.clachaig.com/&#34;&gt;Clachaig Inn&lt;/a&gt;. “Fraoch” is the Gaelic for heather, so take a guess what this beer is made from?  If you’ve never tried it, that might sound a bit weird, but believe me that this is a great beer with “a floral, peaty aroma, full malt body, spicy herbal flavour and a dry wine like finish”. What more could you ask for?  Slainte!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.fraoch.com/">Fraoch</a> is a 5% ABV Scottish beer that brings back many happy memories of late nights spent in the bar at the <a href="http://www.clachaig.com/">Clachaig Inn</a>. “Fraoch” is the Gaelic for heather, so take a guess what this beer is made from?  If you’ve never tried it, that might sound a bit weird, but believe me that this is a great beer with “a floral, peaty aroma, full malt body, spicy herbal flavour and a dry wine like finish”. What more could you ask for?  Slainte!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beer Advent Calendar – Day Twenty-One</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-day-twenty-one/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Dec 2005 21:12:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-day-twenty-one/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;“Jingle Knockers” isn’t exactly a phrase that inspires confidence, but this 5.5% ABV from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skinnersbrewery.com/&#34;&gt;Skinner’s Brewery&lt;/a&gt; in Cornwall is really good, definitely on a par with the stuff I’ve tried from Hambleton Ales and the Harviestoun Brewery. Smooth and strong, with subtle hints of Christmas pud – mmmm…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh, and if you’re still confused by that name, the label handily explains all:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Known as the Tin Mine Fairies, the Cornish Knockers used to guide the miners to the rich veins of ore by knocking. With the demise of mining over the years, many knockers have ;returned to grass’ where, in disguise, they help with the brewing of their ales.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>“Jingle Knockers” isn’t exactly a phrase that inspires confidence, but this 5.5% ABV from <a href="http://www.skinnersbrewery.com/">Skinner’s Brewery</a> in Cornwall is really good, definitely on a par with the stuff I’ve tried from Hambleton Ales and the Harviestoun Brewery. Smooth and strong, with subtle hints of Christmas pud – mmmm…</p>
<p>Oh, and if you’re still confused by that name, the label handily explains all:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><em>“Known as the Tin Mine Fairies, the Cornish Knockers used to guide the miners to the rich veins of ore by knocking. With the demise of mining over the years, many knockers have ;returned to grass’ where, in disguise, they help with the brewing of their ales.”</em></p></blockquote>
<p>So there you go!  Gosh, isn’t drinking beer every day educational?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beer Advent Calendar – Day Twenty</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-day-twenty/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Dec 2005 21:12:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-day-twenty/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Now, don’t get me wrong, there are many great things that have originated from America – not least of all my good lady wife – but I’ve always thought that “American Beer” is something of an anachronism!  Let’s face it, most beers from across the Altlantic are sorely lacking in flavour, body, bitterness, or, well, anything remotely beerlike. So, whilst on my search for twenty-four bottled beers for this advent calendar, I was intrigued to find Honker’s Ale from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gooseisland.com/&#34;&gt;Goose Island Beer Company&lt;/a&gt; in Chicago which describes itself as “a smooth, drinkable English bitter for those drinkers who want more from their beer”. Well, let’s hope they’re not looking for too much more, as it only comes in a 355ml bottle. It tastes OK when compared to the likes of Budweiser and Samuel Adams, but it’s not exactly bold or challenging, and the whole experience was over far too quickly. Not exactly one to savour on a cold winter’s night in Yorkshire, but I can imagine these going down quite well in the sports stadia of Iliinois.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Now, don’t get me wrong, there are many great things that have originated from America – not least of all my good lady wife – but I’ve always thought that “American Beer” is something of an anachronism!  Let’s face it, most beers from across the Altlantic are sorely lacking in flavour, body, bitterness, or, well, anything remotely beerlike. So, whilst on my search for twenty-four bottled beers for this advent calendar, I was intrigued to find Honker’s Ale from the <a href="http://www.gooseisland.com/">Goose Island Beer Company</a> in Chicago which describes itself as “a smooth, drinkable English bitter for those drinkers who want more from their beer”. Well, let’s hope they’re not looking for too much more, as it only comes in a 355ml bottle. It tastes OK when compared to the likes of Budweiser and Samuel Adams, but it’s not exactly bold or challenging, and the whole experience was over far too quickly. Not exactly one to savour on a cold winter’s night in Yorkshire, but I can imagine these going down quite well in the sports stadia of Iliinois.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beer Advent Calendar – Day Nineteen</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-day-nineteen/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Dec 2005 20:12:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-day-nineteen/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Smuggler’s Ale is another bottled beer which found its way into my calendar via an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.asda-beer.co.uk/pages/competition.html&#34;&gt;Asda beer competition&lt;/a&gt;. It’s 5% ABV, with hints of treacle, and is really rather enjoyable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And to paraphrase Forrest Gump, that’s all I have to say about that. Back to my beer and a DVD of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.familyguy.com&#34;&gt;Family Guy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Smuggler’s Ale is another bottled beer which found its way into my calendar via an <a href="http://www.asda-beer.co.uk/pages/competition.html">Asda beer competition</a>. It’s 5% ABV, with hints of treacle, and is really rather enjoyable.</p>
<p>And to paraphrase Forrest Gump, that’s all I have to say about that. Back to my beer and a DVD of <a href="http://www.familyguy.com">Family Guy</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beer Advent Calendar – Day Eighteen</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-day-eighteen/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Dec 2005 21:12:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-day-eighteen/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There’s something a wee bit disappointing about picking up a bottle labelled “MOROCCO ALE” and finding that it is, in fact, from nowhere more distant than Harrogate – the Daleside Brewery to be precise. According to the label:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The recipe for Morocco Ale is believed to date from Elizabethan times. Colonel John Grahme of Levens was a courtier to James II and the name ‘Morocco’ may have been associated with the dark Moors who came to the court when Catherine of Braganza married Charles II and brought Tangiers as part of her dowry.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>There’s something a wee bit disappointing about picking up a bottle labelled “MOROCCO ALE” and finding that it is, in fact, from nowhere more distant than Harrogate – the Daleside Brewery to be precise. According to the label:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“The recipe for Morocco Ale is believed to date from Elizabethan times. Colonel John Grahme of Levens was a courtier to James II and the name ‘Morocco’ may have been associated with the dark Moors who came to the court when Catherine of Braganza married Charles II and brought Tangiers as part of her dowry.”</p></blockquote>
<p>Right. Whatever. Apparently this 5.5% beer is brewed to an ancient secret recipe, so it’s curious that it tastes so strongly of rosemary. I mean, not just a little hint of the stuff, this really could conceivably be nothing more than fermented rosemary, the taste is so overwhelming. Which is certainly different, but I’m not sure it’s really my thing.</p>
<p>Six beers to go – wonder what tomorrow will bring?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beer Advent Calendar – Days Sixteen And Seventeen</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-days-sixteen-and-seventeen/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Dec 2005 23:12:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-days-sixteen-and-seventeen/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img loading=&#34;lazy&#34; src=&#34;https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2023/08/delirium_nocturnum_150.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Friday night saw me out celebrating in Halifax at our departmental Christmas meal (FWIW, I drank a few pints of Santa’s Little Helper from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.caledonian-brewery.co.uk/&#34;&gt;Caledonian brewery&lt;/a&gt;). As a result, I didn’t get chance to enjoy my advent beer, and have been playing catch-up with a couple of randomly-selected bottles tonight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firstly, the sixteenth beer to be selected from the vase of fate was Delirium Nocturnum, a &lt;strong&gt;9.0%&lt;/strong&gt; ABV dark ale from the Huyghe-Melle brewery in Belgium which comes in silver glittery 330ml bottles featuring pictures of pink elephants. I was somewhat apprehensive, but needlessly so, as this is a surprisingly well-balanced and hoppy triply-fermented ale – not a novelty drink at all (despite the packaging being somewhat reminiscent of a Pizza Express salad dressing bottle).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2023/08/delirium_nocturnum_150.jpg"></p>
<p>Friday night saw me out celebrating in Halifax at our departmental Christmas meal (FWIW, I drank a few pints of Santa’s Little Helper from the <a href="http://www.caledonian-brewery.co.uk/">Caledonian brewery</a>). As a result, I didn’t get chance to enjoy my advent beer, and have been playing catch-up with a couple of randomly-selected bottles tonight.</p>
<p>Firstly, the sixteenth beer to be selected from the vase of fate was Delirium Nocturnum, a <strong>9.0%</strong> ABV dark ale from the Huyghe-Melle brewery in Belgium which comes in silver glittery 330ml bottles featuring pictures of pink elephants. I was somewhat apprehensive, but needlessly so, as this is a surprisingly well-balanced and hoppy triply-fermented ale – not a novelty drink at all (despite the packaging being somewhat reminiscent of a Pizza Express salad dressing bottle).</p>
<p>Secondly, today’s drink was Rolling Hitch, a 5.2% ABV India pale ale from the <a href="http://www.darwinbrewery.com">Darwin Brewery</a> in Sunderland. This was specially created for the purposes of entering (and winning) a competition to supply all Asda stores. It’s fruity, sharp, bitter and hoppy – very enjoyable.
Oh, and in case you were wondering,a quick <a href="http://www.google.com/search?q=%22rolling&#43;hitch%22">Googling</a> reveals that a Rolling Hitch is a seafaring knot – <a href="http://www.apparent-wind.com/knots/rolling-hitch/"><em>“if a jib sheet jams in a winch, you can attach a rolling hitch to take the pressure off the line as you undo the jam”</em></a> – so now you know.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beer Advent Calendar – Days Thirteen, Fourteen and Fifteen!</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-days-thirteen-fourteen-and-fifteen/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Dec 2005 19:12:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-days-thirteen-fourteen-and-fifteen/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Gadzooks!  Who would have thought that it would be so difficult to find a few minutes each day to transcribe a few words about a bottle of beer?  But it is – especially as we enter the party season and my evenings are filled with festivities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The good news is, I have three excellent beers to report on; the first two of which are from breweries that I’ve already “visited” during this advent calendar.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Gadzooks!  Who would have thought that it would be so difficult to find a few minutes each day to transcribe a few words about a bottle of beer?  But it is – especially as we enter the party season and my evenings are filled with festivities.</p>
<p>The good news is, I have three excellent beers to report on; the first two of which are from breweries that I’ve already “visited” during this advent calendar.</p>
<p>Tuesday’s beer was Bitter &amp; Twisted, from the Harviestoun Brewery (c.f. <a href="https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-day-three/">Schiehallion</a> on day three). At 4.2% ABV it’s a little lighter than Schiehallion, but it’s equally delicious – very fresh, sharp and hoppy, it was voted Champion Bottled Ale 2004. Mmmmm.</p>
<p>Wednesday I came back closer to home for a second beer from the <a href="http://www.hambletonales.co.uk/">Hambleton Ales</a> microbrewery in Thirsk – this time it was Festive Filly (ABV 4.5%), which is presumably a seasonal ale, and damn nice it is too. Another good winter warming beer.</p>
<p>Finally, today I enjoyed Nessie’s Monster Mash, a 4.4% “premium beer” from the <a href="http://www.cairngormbrewery.com/">Cairngorm Brewery Company</a>. Very pleasant, plenty of flavour – I’d be interested in trying the cask version of this for comparison.</p>
<p>So there we have it, a trio of mighty fine ales from northern Britain, any one of which I’d love to have for a second time. Aaah, this beer advent calendar was *such* a good idea…</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beer Advent Calendar – Day Twelve</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-day-twelve/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Dec 2005 22:12:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-day-twelve/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Halfway through my great beer advent calendar 2005, and tonight I’ve enjoyed the popular Leffe Blonde, a potent and delicious 6.6% ABV beer from Belgium. I’ve been meaning to try this reknowned tipple since I utterly failed to identify a snippet of the label in one of those irritating Excel-based quizzes that circulates on the interweb periodically. Anyway, I wasn’t disappointed – the small bottle size (33cl) being more than made up for by the strength and the flavour (quite almondy, I thought). There’s a good detailed review by someone with more effective taste buds than I over at the excellent &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bottledbeer.co.uk/index.html?beerid=386&#34;&gt;Oxford Bottled Beer Database&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Halfway through my great beer advent calendar 2005, and tonight I’ve enjoyed the popular Leffe Blonde, a potent and delicious 6.6% ABV beer from Belgium. I’ve been meaning to try this reknowned tipple since I utterly failed to identify a snippet of the label in one of those irritating Excel-based quizzes that circulates on the interweb periodically. Anyway, I wasn’t disappointed – the small bottle size (33cl) being more than made up for by the strength and the flavour (quite almondy, I thought). There’s a good detailed review by someone with more effective taste buds than I over at the excellent <a href="http://www.bottledbeer.co.uk/index.html?beerid=386">Oxford Bottled Beer Database</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beer Advent Calendar – Day Eleven</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-day-eleven/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Dec 2005 15:12:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-day-eleven/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I just realised that I forgot to blog about yesterday’s advent beer. Sorry for keeping you all on tenterhooks like that!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be honest I was a bit disappointed and couldn’t think of anything interesting to say about &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.croptonbrewery.com/product.asp?cookiecheck=yes&amp;amp;P_ID=126&#34;&gt;Rudolph’s Revenge&lt;/a&gt;, a 4.6% ABV bitter from Cropton Brewery. It was quite similar to the equally uninspiring &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-day-eight/&#34;&gt;Mars Magic&lt;/a&gt; from last Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I just realised that I forgot to blog about yesterday’s advent beer. Sorry for keeping you all on tenterhooks like that!</p>
<p>To be honest I was a bit disappointed and couldn’t think of anything interesting to say about <a href="http://www.croptonbrewery.com/product.asp?cookiecheck=yes&amp;P_ID=126">Rudolph’s Revenge</a>, a 4.6% ABV bitter from Cropton Brewery. It was quite similar to the equally uninspiring <a href="https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-day-eight/">Mars Magic</a> from last Thursday.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beer Advent Calendar – Day Ten</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-day-ten/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Dec 2005 18:12:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-day-ten/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Ah, I do enjoy beers by the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wychwood.co.uk/&#34;&gt;Wychwood Brewery&lt;/a&gt;, who have a particularly good website (i.e. better than most of the brewery sites I’ve come across so far). Hobgoblin is an obvious favourite, easily available from any supermarket worth its salt. Today I sampled their &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wychwood.co.uk/wychwood_whirlygig.htm&#34;&gt;Whirlygig&lt;/a&gt; ale, a 4.5% “frenzy of hops and malt”, which really is delicious. Lots of flavour, lots of character – very enjoyable indeed. This one goes into the “buy again” column. Jocelyn didn’t get a look in, so I can’t give you the female opinion, sorry.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Ah, I do enjoy beers by the <a href="http://www.wychwood.co.uk/">Wychwood Brewery</a>, who have a particularly good website (i.e. better than most of the brewery sites I’ve come across so far). Hobgoblin is an obvious favourite, easily available from any supermarket worth its salt. Today I sampled their <a href="http://www.wychwood.co.uk/wychwood_whirlygig.htm">Whirlygig</a> ale, a 4.5% “frenzy of hops and malt”, which really is delicious. Lots of flavour, lots of character – very enjoyable indeed. This one goes into the “buy again” column. Jocelyn didn’t get a look in, so I can’t give you the female opinion, sorry.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beer Advent Calendar – Day Nine</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-day-nine/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Dec 2005 23:12:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-day-nine/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bateman.co.uk/Beers/btroseynosey.htm&#34;&gt;Rosey Nosey&lt;/a&gt; by Bateman’s Brewery has a deceptively cutesy name, but it turns out to be a really decent-quality ale with plenty of flavour and a pleasing warmth. If you have to buy one festive-themed beer this year, you could do much worse than this one.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.bateman.co.uk/Beers/btroseynosey.htm">Rosey Nosey</a> by Bateman’s Brewery has a deceptively cutesy name, but it turns out to be a really decent-quality ale with plenty of flavour and a pleasing warmth. If you have to buy one festive-themed beer this year, you could do much worse than this one.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beer Advent Calendar – Day Eight</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-day-eight/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Dec 2005 19:12:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-day-eight/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Another day, another beer.It’s a hard life.&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.woldtopbrewery.co.uk/products_3.htm&#34;&gt;Mars Magic&lt;/a&gt; is a rather unexciting 4.6% ABV “Premium Ale” (it says here) from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.woldtopbrewery.co.uk/index.htm&#34;&gt;Wold Top Brewery&lt;/a&gt;.Noticeably lacking in anything resembling a head, it did however seem to improve as I progressed through the half-litre (funny how that happens).So, with my whistle well and truly whetted, I’m off down &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.yorkpubguide.com/pubs/details.asp?PubId=4&#34;&gt;the pub&lt;/a&gt;.Cya!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh, I nearly forgot to record Joce’s comments on the bitter.It went something like: “Eurgh!”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Another day, another beer.It’s a hard life.<a href="http://www.woldtopbrewery.co.uk/products_3.htm">Mars Magic</a> is a rather unexciting 4.6% ABV “Premium Ale” (it says here) from the <a href="http://www.woldtopbrewery.co.uk/index.htm">Wold Top Brewery</a>.Noticeably lacking in anything resembling a head, it did however seem to improve as I progressed through the half-litre (funny how that happens).So, with my whistle well and truly whetted, I’m off down <a href="http://www.yorkpubguide.com/pubs/details.asp?PubId=4">the pub</a>.Cya!</p>
<p>Oh, I nearly forgot to record Joce’s comments on the bitter.It went something like: “Eurgh!”</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beer Advent Calendar – Day Seven</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-day-seven/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Dec 2005 14:12:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-day-seven/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Wednesday night’s tipple was the rather strange 5% ABV &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.k1664.co.uk&#34;&gt;Kronenbourg Blanc&lt;/a&gt;, from UK brewing giant &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;amp;ct=res&amp;amp;cd=1&amp;amp;url=http%3A//www.scottish-newcastle.com/&#34;&gt;Scottish &amp;amp; Newcastle&lt;/a&gt;. Described as a “refreshing, fruity white beer”, this is in fact blatantly piss-coloured (which probably explains why it comes in an opaque bottle). I found this to be more reminiscent of a weak cider or some kind of bizarre citrus alcopop than anything deserving to have the word “beer” on the label. Still, try everything once except Morris Dancing and incest, as the saying goes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Wednesday night’s tipple was the rather strange 5% ABV <a href="http://www.k1664.co.uk">Kronenbourg Blanc</a>, from UK brewing giant <a href="http://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;ct=res&amp;cd=1&amp;url=http%3A//www.scottish-newcastle.com/">Scottish &amp; Newcastle</a>. Described as a “refreshing, fruity white beer”, this is in fact blatantly piss-coloured (which probably explains why it comes in an opaque bottle). I found this to be more reminiscent of a weak cider or some kind of bizarre citrus alcopop than anything deserving to have the word “beer” on the label. Still, try everything once except Morris Dancing and incest, as the saying goes.</p>
<p>Jocelyn says: “This is a girly beer!  I could drink this!  This is fruity, it’s not a beer at all!”</p>
<p>Weird advertising, too – would you buy a drink for this girl?</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2023/08/connie1_large_71473873_o.jpg"></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beer Advent Calendar – Day Six</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-day-six/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Dec 2005 22:12:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-day-six/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A return to form today, with the vase of fate serving up a helping of Riggwelter, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.blacksheepbrewery.com/&#34;&gt;Black Sheep Brewery’s&lt;/a&gt; delicious 4.7% strong Yorkshire ale.I could drink this till the cows come home.Or perhaps that should be the sheep, for (according to the bottle) the name Riggwelter comes from the Old Norse &lt;em&gt;rygg&lt;/em&gt; meaning to overturn.“When a sheep is on its back and cannot get up without help, local dales dialect says it’s &lt;em&gt;rigged&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;riggwelted&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A return to form today, with the vase of fate serving up a helping of Riggwelter, the <a href="http://www.blacksheepbrewery.com/">Black Sheep Brewery’s</a> delicious 4.7% strong Yorkshire ale.I could drink this till the cows come home.Or perhaps that should be the sheep, for (according to the bottle) the name Riggwelter comes from the Old Norse <em>rygg</em> meaning to overturn.“When a sheep is on its back and cannot get up without help, local dales dialect says it’s <em>rigged</em> or <em>riggwelted</em>.”</p>
<p>Jocelyn says: “That’s cheating, you’ve had that one before, you’re supposed to be trying something new.I’m not interested”.</p>
<p>She speaks the truth, this isn’t exactly my first Riggwelter.In fact I’ve taken Joce to visit the brewery in Masham before 🙂</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beer Advent Calendar – Day Five</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-day-five/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Dec 2005 21:12:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-day-five/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today’s festive ale is the Teignworthy Christmas Cracker, a strong (6% ABV) dark and warming malty bottle conditioned ale from deepest Devon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Um, it’s OK, certainly tastes weighty and, well, worthy, but it isn’t really to my taste – it has a very strong aftertaste yet is lacking in any interesting fruity flavours.There are plenty of other things I’d rather drink before picking this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jocelyn says: “Damn, I’ve dripped it on my top, I’ll have to wash this now.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Today’s festive ale is the Teignworthy Christmas Cracker, a strong (6% ABV) dark and warming malty bottle conditioned ale from deepest Devon.</p>
<p>Um, it’s OK, certainly tastes weighty and, well, worthy, but it isn’t really to my taste – it has a very strong aftertaste yet is lacking in any interesting fruity flavours.There are plenty of other things I’d rather drink before picking this.</p>
<p>Jocelyn says: “Damn, I’ve dripped it on my top, I’ll have to wash this now.”</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beer Advent Calendar – Day Four</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-day-four/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Dec 2005 22:12:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-day-four/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Another superb ale tonight, and this one is close to home. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.hambletonales.co.uk/nightmare.htm&#34;&gt;Nightmare&lt;/a&gt; by the Hambleton Ales microbrewery in Thirsk is an extremely creamy, fruity, and flavoursome stout—not as bitter as you might expect from its appearance. Very tasty—I’ll definitely be buying this again.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Another superb ale tonight, and this one is close to home. <a href="http://www.hambletonales.co.uk/nightmare.htm">Nightmare</a> by the Hambleton Ales microbrewery in Thirsk is an extremely creamy, fruity, and flavoursome stout—not as bitter as you might expect from its appearance. Very tasty—I’ll definitely be buying this again.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beer Advent Calendar – Day Three</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-day-three/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Dec 2005 01:12:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-day-three/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Third Time Lucky!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After two days of novelty nonsense, the vase of fate finally served up a half-litre of Harviestoun Brewery’s 4.8% masterpiece, &lt;em&gt;Schiehallion&lt;/em&gt;, named after my all-time favourite &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Munro&#34;&gt;Munro&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s an interesting fact for you: the mass of the Earth was first measured in 1774 when the Astronomer Royal, one Nevil Maskelyne, spent four months mucking about on Schiehallion with pendulums. By observing how the mountain’s bulk caused the pendulums (pendula?) to swing away from the vertical, he was able to estimate the mountain’s mass and extrapolate from this to calculate our planet’s mass at 5,000 million million tonnes—which is a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.google.com/search?q=mass&amp;#43;of&amp;#43;earth&#34;&gt;pretty reasonable estimate&lt;/a&gt;, if you ask me. Based on that work, it then became possible to determine the mass of all the other planets, their moons, and even the Sun itself. All of which rather puts my own summer’s evening stroll up Schiehallion in 1998 into perspective, enjoyable though it was.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong>Third Time Lucky!</strong></p>
<p>After two days of novelty nonsense, the vase of fate finally served up a half-litre of Harviestoun Brewery’s 4.8% masterpiece, <em>Schiehallion</em>, named after my all-time favourite <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Munro">Munro</a>.</p>
<p>Here’s an interesting fact for you: the mass of the Earth was first measured in 1774 when the Astronomer Royal, one Nevil Maskelyne, spent four months mucking about on Schiehallion with pendulums. By observing how the mountain’s bulk caused the pendulums (pendula?) to swing away from the vertical, he was able to estimate the mountain’s mass and extrapolate from this to calculate our planet’s mass at 5,000 million million tonnes—which is a <a href="http://www.google.com/search?q=mass&#43;of&#43;earth">pretty reasonable estimate</a>, if you ask me. Based on that work, it then became possible to determine the mass of all the other planets, their moons, and even the Sun itself. All of which rather puts my own summer’s evening stroll up Schiehallion in 1998 into perspective, enjoyable though it was.</p>
<p>Oh, and the beer’s great too, by the way. Cask-conditioned, Bohemian style, lovely and refreshing, with a taste evocative of Scottish moorland and heather. It’s even won gold medals at CAMRA’s Great British Beer Festival.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beer Advent Calendar – Day Two</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-day-two/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Dec 2005 23:12:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-day-two/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Well, this evening’s advent beer couldn’t be more different from yesterday’s. I had the dubious pleasure of sampling &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.chilibeer.com/&#34;&gt;Crazy Ed’s Cave Creek Chili Beer&lt;/a&gt;, all the way from Arizona.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be warned: the website dates from 1999, and boy, does it show—we’re talking Comic Sans in a scrolling &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;marquee&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; tag, framesets that have a tendency to get confused (try clicking the “home” link), and a 53-kilopixel JPEG weighing in at an astonishing 232 KB (why?!). Seeing those “Netscape Now!” animated GIFs makes me all nostalgic for the twentieth century…&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Well, this evening’s advent beer couldn’t be more different from yesterday’s. I had the dubious pleasure of sampling <a href="http://www.chilibeer.com/">Crazy Ed’s Cave Creek Chili Beer</a>, all the way from Arizona.</p>
<p>Be warned: the website dates from 1999, and boy, does it show—we’re talking Comic Sans in a scrolling <code>&lt;marquee&gt;</code> tag, framesets that have a tendency to get confused (try clicking the “home” link), and a 53-kilopixel JPEG weighing in at an astonishing 232 KB (why?!). Seeing those “Netscape Now!” animated GIFs makes me all nostalgic for the twentieth century…</p>
<p><em>Ahem.</em> But enough about the site—what about the beer? Well, it was a lucky choice for this evening, as Joce had made Mexican for dinner. It was certainly spicy (with a whole chili pod in the bottle), but to be honest, I would have preferred a nice, refreshing Corona or Sol. As with yesterday’s offering, this was a fun novelty drink as a one-off, but not something I could happily sup all evening.</p>
<p>Joce says: “Oh! Ow! Oh my God! Oh, man! That is the hottest thing I’ve ever tasted! My throat is on fire!”</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beer Advent Calendar – Day One</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-day-one/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Dec 2005 20:12:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/beer-advent-calendar-day-one/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is surely one of the best ideas I’ve ever had! I’ve followed through with my plan to buy twenty-four beers from around the world to count down the days until Christmas. Their names are all written on slips of folded paper in a small vase (nobody actually draws things out of a hat anymore, do they?).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today I’m enjoying &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youngsathome.co.uk/&#34;&gt;Young’s Christmas Pudding Ale&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, which is 5.5% ABV according to the bottle but only 5.0% according to the website—don’t believe everything you read on the web, eh?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This is surely one of the best ideas I’ve ever had! I’ve followed through with my plan to buy twenty-four beers from around the world to count down the days until Christmas. Their names are all written on slips of folded paper in a small vase (nobody actually draws things out of a hat anymore, do they?).</p>
<p>Today I’m enjoying <strong><a href="http://www.youngsathome.co.uk/">Young’s Christmas Pudding Ale</a></strong>, which is 5.5% ABV according to the bottle but only 5.0% according to the website—don’t believe everything you read on the web, eh?</p>
<p>The tasting notes say:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>With its warming, dark ruby character and the splendid luscious flavour of dried fruit, Young’s Christmas Pudding Ale is an inspirational addition to any Christmas feast or fireside gathering.</p></blockquote>
<p>I say it’s tasty—pleasant as a singleton but probably a bit too fruity for a prolonged sesh. It really does smell like figgy pudding, too!</p>
<p>If this were a track on my iPod, I’d probably give it four stars.</p>
<p>Jocelyn says: “Huh? I can’t taste any fruit. Nope, tastes like beer to me. I’d prefer a Guinness.”</p>
<p>I wonder what tomorrow will bring…</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Computer Games I Have Loved</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/computer-games-i-have-loved/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Aug 2005 21:08:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/computer-games-i-have-loved/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Isn’t it funny how one’s tastes change as maturity progresses?  I used to spend my summer holidays at the sea-side, playing in arcades and seeking the perfect milkshake (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.snackspot.org.uk/thread.php?story=0408101147daa&#34;&gt;lime&lt;/a&gt;); more recently I’ve been spending them in the highlands, playing on the hills and seeking the perfect dram (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.scotchwhisky.com/focus/lagavulin.htm&#34;&gt;lagavulin&lt;/a&gt;).Hmmm…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think I may have mentioned that the wife is away in the States for a while.At the start of this period of solitude, I panicked, wondering whatever I could do with myself, and came to the conclusion that it would be a good idea to buy a computer game to while away the hours.After all, I spent much of my formative years killing time on a variety of computer and console games, so why not rekindle that prior love affair?  So it was that I bought &lt;a href=&#34;http://thesims2.ea.com/&#34;&gt;The Sims 2&lt;/a&gt;, a truly excellent game, and had an enjoyable evening trying to motivate my wee Sims to improve their skills, better themselves, and generally enjoy life.All good harmless fun.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Isn’t it funny how one’s tastes change as maturity progresses?  I used to spend my summer holidays at the sea-side, playing in arcades and seeking the perfect milkshake (<a href="http://www.snackspot.org.uk/thread.php?story=0408101147daa">lime</a>); more recently I’ve been spending them in the highlands, playing on the hills and seeking the perfect dram (<a href="http://www.scotchwhisky.com/focus/lagavulin.htm">lagavulin</a>).Hmmm…</p>
<p>I think I may have mentioned that the wife is away in the States for a while.At the start of this period of solitude, I panicked, wondering whatever I could do with myself, and came to the conclusion that it would be a good idea to buy a computer game to while away the hours.After all, I spent much of my formative years killing time on a variety of computer and console games, so why not rekindle that prior love affair?  So it was that I bought <a href="http://thesims2.ea.com/">The Sims 2</a>, a truly excellent game, and had an enjoyable evening trying to motivate my wee Sims to improve their skills, better themselves, and generally enjoy life.All good harmless fun.</p>
<p>The following evening, though, I came to resume my game, and…  I just couldn’t be bothered.The whole concept seemed utterly pointless, a real waste of time.Why squander an evening encouraging AI sims to develop their skills and improve their house when, here in the real life, I had bookcases to build, books to read, music to enjoy, new DVDs to watch, a fantastic city to go out and enjoy, and skills to learn for my own career?  It struck me that many of the finely-honed computer game skills I had developed over the past thirtyish years were of absolutely no use outside the parameters of those particular games.</p>
<p>Since then, The Sims has sat on a shelf, and I’ve achieved loads over the past few weeks – Jocelyn is soon returning to find the house at the tidiest it’s been in years.I told my mum all this (as you do).She said I’m growing up.About bloody time.</p>
<p>But still, those earlier computer games <em>did</em> play a big part during the first three decades of my life, so, in way of tribute, here’s a quick rundown of the dozen games responsible for my most wasted hours:</p>
<h2 id="grandstand-adman-2000">Grandstand Adman 2000</h2>
<p>The first “console” I ever owned, this featured four (four!) different games – football, squash, tennis and practice.Not only that, but it boasted configurable options for speed, angle, and bat-size!  You simply cannot appreciate how many hours I frittered away bouncing that square block against a wall until I encountered 15 “faults” – at which point I would press the reset button and repeat the process.If I’m being charitable to my younger self, then I could suggest that this game at least helped me develop hand-eye coordination, and stopped me mithering my parents for a while.
“Real Sports Action”, says the box.Well, only if football ever consisted of four vertical bars deflecting a square ball moving with constant speed.Also – “Realistic Sound Effects”.It beeped!  That was it!  But, y’know, it was all we had, so…</p>
<p><img alt="Grandstand Adman 2000" loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2023/08/grandstand-adman-2000_35626038_o.jpg">
<em>Photo by <a href="http://computermuseum.50megs.com/collectionpong.htm">Erik Klooster</a></em></p>
<h2 id="grandstand-bmx-flyer">Grandstand BMX Flyer</h2>
<p>Oh, now this handheld LCD console was (is?) a most favourite game of mine.I can still hum the tune, and I still know that my highest-ever score was 14,070.Brilliant fun – highly addictive and an appealing concept for a seven year-old lad (“avoid the crows!”  “jump for the girl in the balloon!”  “kick dirt in the baddy’s face!”).</p>
<p><img alt="Grandstand BMX Flyer" loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2023/08/grandstand-bmxflyerboxfrontjpg_35626067_o.jpg">
<em>Photo by <a href="http://www.handheldmuseum.com/Grandstand/BMXF.htm">Handheld Museum</a></em></p>
<h2 id="starter-chess-commodore-16">Starter Chess (Commodore 16)</h2>
<p>I was always a Commodore kid.Speccies and Amstrads, though much more popular with the gamers at school, just didn’t appeal to me.I mean, seriously, how could you write computer programs for hours on end using a rubber keyboard?!  Oh, sure, they were much better for games, if you liked that kind of thing.But the C16 came with games too, like.. Starter Chess!<br>
OK, who am I kidding?  Starter Chess was, in all respects, an exercise in patience and sitting around watching a pitifully underpowered computer fail to do very much for what seemed like an interminably long time.First you had to get the game to load, from cassette tape, which always took the best part of twenty minutes.Then, after every chess move played by oneself, the Commodore spent a good five minutes plotting its next move (which it announced with a loud beep).Not very exciting.On the plus side, the computer player wasn’t particularly strong, so it was actually quite conceivable to win, even as a youngster.</p>
<h2 id="fruit-machine-simulator-commodore-16">Fruit Machine Simulator (Commodore 16)</h2>
<p>I’m beginning to think I must’ve been a bit of a masochist as a child, because I absolutely loved this single-screen game which attempted to “simulate” a pretty simplistic fruit machine.Press a key to enter some coins.Press another key to pull the lever.Maybe, just maybe, you then have the possibility of pressing further keys to “hold” or “nudge” – oh, the excitement was palpable.It sounds really dull now, but I loved it at the time.I remember trying to figure out the probability with which the various game events occurred – were they truly random, or were they influenced by the user’s actions?  What was the average length of a game, before you either went bust or accumulated the target winnings?  A future university career in mathematics was  already evident..</p>
<h2 id="kickstart-commodore-16">Kickstart (Commodore 16)</h2>
<p>Of all the games I had for the C16, Kickstart was the only one that I remember as being truly playable, and remotely “fast”.I was impressed at the time that such a game could run on a machine with such little RAM.This was a motorbike game (as in the old TV show, Kickstart, which I also loved), and, like BMX Flyer years early, basically involved making the bike jump at the appropriate time – balloons were involved again too, and there was an irritating-to-adults soundtrack.Quality.</p>
<h2 id="lemmings-amiga">Lemmings (Amiga)</h2>
<p>The Christmas that brought me an Amiga 500 played a big part in sealing my future career direction.For the first time, I was able to tinker with a real operating system (with GUI), more powerful programming languages, hard disks, multitasking applications, etc.But that Christmas day itself was mostly spent playing Lemmings, which should need no introduction as it’s one of the most popular games of its time, and has been ported across to many platforms, including DHTML!</p>
<p><img alt="Lemmings" loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2023/08/amiga_lemmingspng_35626091_o.png"></p>
<h2 id="stunt-car-racer-amiga">Stunt Car Racer (Amiga)</h2>
<p>Stunt Car Racer was initially a very hard game.But, persevere and you would discover the “knack” to each of the eight challenging courses.So, persevere I did, and eventually reached the top of division one!  It seemed like such an achievement at the time, but it’s not exactly something I can put on my CV in 2005, is it?</p>
<p><img alt="Stunt Car Racer" loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2023/08/stunt_car_racer_06_35626365_o.gif"></p>
<h2 id="gods-amiga">Gods (Amiga)</h2>
<p>Gods was a platform game by the Bitmap Brothers, with a kicking introductory theme tune, and the game was pretty cool too. Lots of different weapons, puzzles, and backgrounds ensured a game which remained enjoyable as you progressed through the levels. Also a good variety of monsters, who boasted a much-hyped AI, in stark contrast to the usual sprites of the day who tended to attack by following predictable (circular) routes. Brilliant.</p>
<p><img alt="Gods" loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2023/08/gods_35626019_o.png"></p>
<h2 id="civilization-series-amiga--pc">Civilization series (Amiga / PC)</h2>
<p>Of all the games mentioned, I have spent the most time playing the various incarnations of Civilization on the Amiga and latterly on the PC.Indeed, Civ 3 with the Play The World expansion gets my vote for greatest computer game of all time.It’s such a brilliant concept – start with a few stone-age settlers in 4000BC and nurture them through 6000 years of growth, discovery, technological development, war and peace until they either achieve world domination or make the leap to Alpha Centauri (OK, I hear there are some other victory conditions, but these are the only two I’ve ever really found interesting).The level of attachment you can feel to your civilization after playing this game for an entire weekend is really quite disturbing.Addictive to the extreme, and often responsible for my eyes feeling very sore indeed…</p>
<p><img alt="Civilization 3" loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2023/08/civ3jpg_35626007_o.jpg"></p>
<h2 id="worms-pc">Worms (PC)</h2>
<p>If it wasn’t for Worms, I suspect myself and some of the other Grovey Roaders would have achieved 2:1 degrees instead of the 2:2s we all took from Nottingham uni.But, alas, Worms was just such good fun, and so sociable… what better way to spend evenings in our final year than commanding crack squads of four worms each to kick each other’s butts to entertaining effect?  Well, except for going to The Irish, of course.</p>
<h2 id="quake-pc">Quake (PC)</h2>
<p>I missed the whole Doom thing as I didn’t get a PC until leaving uni in 1997. Quake was therefore the first FPS I ever played, and thus swiftly passed another summer of my youth.</p>
<h2 id="gran-turismo-2-playstation">Gran Turismo 2 (Playstation)</h2>
<p>GT2 was the reason I bought a Playstation, and it was the only PSX game I played for any length of time.At the time I had a Ford Puma, so within the game I made a point of buying the exact same model in the same colour.How sad is that?  As with my recent Sims 2 epiphany, I was eventually struck by the thought “why am I doing this within the virtual confines of a computer game when I could be doing it out in the real world?”.I didn’t explain this line of reasoning to the magistrate though, and the six points should come off my driving licence in a few year’s time… 😉</p>
<p>There you have it, the dirty dozen responsible for wasting much of the best years of my life.Who knows, without those distractions, maybe by now I would otherwise be a Nobel laureate, or rich and famous…  or maybe I would have no hand-eye coordination, be unable to use a mouse, and not have the programming talents that now put food on our table.Hmmm…</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Project Euler</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/project-euler/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Aug 2005 20:08:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/project-euler/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you like maths problems, and you like programming (and hey, who doesn’t?), then you’ll love &lt;a href=&#34;http://mathschallenge.net/index.php?section=project&#34;&gt;Project Euler&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>If you like maths problems, and you like programming (and hey, who doesn’t?), then you’ll love <a href="http://mathschallenge.net/index.php?section=project">Project Euler</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>999999999..</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/zetafax-999/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Jan 2005 23:01:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/zetafax-999/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Never underestimate the stupidity of users—or the benefits of a little field validation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the web-based systems I’ve been developing allows users to enter a customer’s fax number and automatically fax confirmation details (using Zetafax). It’s been working pretty well—until we discovered a flaw today. One user, tired of obtaining valid fax details from customers, had been entering a string of nines and then actually attempting to send the fax to this number.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Never underestimate the stupidity of users—or the benefits of a little field validation.</p>
<p>One of the web-based systems I’ve been developing allows users to enter a customer’s fax number and automatically fax confirmation details (using Zetafax). It’s been working pretty well—until we discovered a flaw today. One user, tired of obtaining valid fax details from customers, had been entering a string of nines and then actually attempting to send the fax to this number.</p>
<p>We first learned of this issue today, when West Yorkshire Police asked us to stop trying to send faxes to the emergency services!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
