<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Books on Ian Nelson</title>
    <link>https://bloghugo.iannelson.uk/categories/books/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Books on Ian Nelson</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.146.6</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 14 Dec 2024 16:31:33 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://bloghugo.iannelson.uk/categories/books/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The Books I Most Enjoyed Reading in 2024</title>
      <link>https://bloghugo.iannelson.uk/the-books-i-most-enjoyed-reading-in-2024/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Dec 2024 16:31:33 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bloghugo.iannelson.uk/the-books-i-most-enjoyed-reading-in-2024/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As 2024 draws to a close, I’ve taken some time to reflect on the books that made the greatest impact on me this year. From deep dives into technology and politics to introspective reads on life and risk, these are the titles that enriched my year – and might just enrich yours too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you pressed me on the subject, I would say that my very favourite book of 2024 was &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://amzn.to/3DcUiXT&#34;&gt;Burn Book: A Tech Love Story&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; by veteran tech journalist Kara Swisher.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Books I Most Enjoyed Reading in 2023</title>
      <link>https://bloghugo.iannelson.uk/the-books-i-most-enjoyed-reading-in-2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Dec 2023 15:40:15 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bloghugo.iannelson.uk/the-books-i-most-enjoyed-reading-in-2023/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 class=&#34;wp-block-heading&#34; id=&#34;politics-on-the-edge-a-memoir-from-within-by-rory-stewart&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://amzn.to/41sIGYS&#34;&gt;Politics on the Edge: A Memoir from Within&lt;/a&gt; by Rory Stewart&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My very favourite book of 2023 was this autobiography by former Minister and one-time candidate for Conservative Party leader Rory Stewart. I almost didn’t read it at all, as I was feeling a little jaded with politics at the time and considering a more light-hearted Audible purchase. I’m glad I plumped for this though, and it did offer some light relief in the form of Stewart’s dodgy accents when recounting conversations with fellow politicians of all parties and nationalities.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The 20 Books I Most Enjoyed Reading in 2022</title>
      <link>https://bloghugo.iannelson.uk/the-20-books-i-most-enjoyed-reading-in-2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Dec 2022 20:22:49 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bloghugo.iannelson.uk/the-20-books-i-most-enjoyed-reading-in-2022/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-top-5.wp-block-heading&#34;&gt;The Top 5&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;stolen-focus-why-you-cant-pay-attention-by-johann-hari.wp-block-heading&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://amzn.to/3hZsGL5&#34;&gt;Stolen Focus: Why You Can’t Pay Attention&lt;/a&gt; by Johann Hari&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My favourite book of the year &lt;em&gt;partially&lt;/em&gt; covers the same ground as previous favourites &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://amzn.to/3v0oxtC&#34;&gt;A World Without Email&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://amzn.to/3WgPFAm&#34;&gt;Four Thousand Weeks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://amzn.to/3v07N60&#34;&gt;Ten Arguments for Deleting Your Social Media Accounts Right Now&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. But the scope of Hari’s work is much broader than these. Rather than merely telling us to stop doomscrolling Twitter and get on with life, he covers a multiplicity of factors and forces that are combining to steal the ability of many of us to focus. Social media, pollution, lack of sleep, poor diet, overwork and more are all discussed, with many pointers to third-party research.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Books I Most Enjoyed Reading in 2021</title>
      <link>https://bloghugo.iannelson.uk/the-books-i-most-enjoyed-reading-in-2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Dec 2021 21:21:01 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bloghugo.iannelson.uk/the-books-i-most-enjoyed-reading-in-2021/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-top-5-the-top-5&#34;&gt;The Top 5 {#the-top-5}&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://amzn.to/3jwAUs6&#34;&gt;And Away…&lt;/a&gt; by Bob Mortimer&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As was the case in 2020, my favourite book of the year was an autobiography; this time by national treasure Bob Mortimer. Laugh out loud funny in many places, elsewhere this is tinged with melancholy and the realisation that, for all his on-screen tomfoolery, Mortimer is an incredibly shy individual.&lt;br&gt;
Touching, contemplative, warm and kind throughout, there is plenty of food for thought here regarding how we ought to live our lives and interact with those around us. I heartily recommend the audiobook, narrated by the great man himself.&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The 12 Books I Most Enjoyed Reading in 2020</title>
      <link>https://bloghugo.iannelson.uk/12-books-i-most-enjoyed-reading-in-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Dec 2020 07:07:55 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bloghugo.iannelson.uk/12-books-i-most-enjoyed-reading-in-2020/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;So that, then, was 2020. Good riddance. One might imagine that the enforced downtime offered by the pandemic lockdowns would have afforded me the opportunity to read many more books than I did in 2019.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But a displeasing proportion of my evenings in 2020 were spent relentlessly doomscrolling Twitter, eager for the latest morsels of information about the pandemic, US election or (sigh) Brexit. Besides, most of my “reading” in 2019 was actually achieved by listening to Audible while commuting or at the gym, two activities which barely featured in my life this year.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The 20 Books I Most Enjoyed Reading in 2019</title>
      <link>https://bloghugo.iannelson.uk/20-books-i-most-enjoyed-reading-in-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Jan 2020 22:40:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bloghugo.iannelson.uk/20-books-i-most-enjoyed-reading-in-2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Near the end of 2018, I stumbled upon a thread of tweets by First Minister of Scotland Nicola Sturgeon in which she shared some of the many books that she had enjoyed during that year. I was both amazed and ashamed that a leader of a nation could consume so much literature whilst I, a mere sellsword codemonkey, barely got through a book every month (or two).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It wasn’t that I didn’t enjoy reading – I have always loved reading (and buying) books – it was just that I had somehow convinced myself that I didn’t have the time to read. I realised that this simply wasn’t true, that I could easily make time to read if I so desired, and vowed to consume more books during 2019.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>.NET Coding Standards</title>
      <link>https://bloghugo.iannelson.uk/net-coding-standards/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2009 15:01:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bloghugo.iannelson.uk/net-coding-standards/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, when you join a new team as a .NET developer, the team lead proudly points you in the direction of a Word document or wiki page detailing the team’s house coding standards.&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my experience, these documents are invariably:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Incomplete.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Subjective.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not enforced.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Largely copied from the interweb.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Obsessed with the trivial (e.g. whitespace) while failing to mention the genuinely useful (e.g. boxing/unboxing, avoiding use of deprecated classes, Dispose pattern, etc).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know this because I’ve been involved in creating such documents in the past 🙂&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>More Tufte Books</title>
      <link>https://bloghugo.iannelson.uk/more-tufte-books/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Feb 2007 21:02:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bloghugo.iannelson.uk/more-tufte-books/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When I mentioned Edward R. Tufte’s excellent &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/0961392142?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=ianesbl-21&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=1634&amp;amp;creative=6738&amp;amp;creativeASIN=0961392142&#34;&gt;The Visual Display of Quantitative Information&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; in a recent blog post, it prompted me to search North Yorkshire’s online library catalogue to see if they had any more of the great man’s works. I was delighted to find that both &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/0961392118?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=ianesbl-21&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=1634&amp;amp;creative=6738&amp;amp;creativeASIN=0961392118&#34;&gt;Envisioning Information&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/0961392126?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=ianesbl-21&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=1634&amp;amp;creative=6738&amp;amp;creativeASIN=0961392126&#34;&gt;Visual Explanations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; were available, yet languishing in a storage room somewhere rather than being on the shelves of one of the county’s libraries!  So, I placed a request and they turned up at my local branch a few days later.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spot The Misleading Graph</title>
      <link>https://bloghugo.iannelson.uk/spot-the-misleading-graph/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Feb 2007 19:02:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bloghugo.iannelson.uk/spot-the-misleading-graph/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Fifty-three years since Darrell Huff published the seminal &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/0140136290?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=ianesbl-21&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=1634&amp;amp;creative=6738&amp;amp;creativeASIN=0140136290&#34;&gt;How to Lie with Statistics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, and still we have newspapers as august as &lt;em&gt;The Times&lt;/em&gt; pulling the oldest trick in the book:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At first glance it all looks very impressive, but closer inspection of the comparison with sales of the Torygraph reveal a mere 8.7% sales lead, not more than double as suggested by the graphic.  Not fooled.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tech Books</title>
      <link>https://bloghugo.iannelson.uk/tech-books/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jun 2005 21:06:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bloghugo.iannelson.uk/tech-books/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I succumbed to temptation and bought another book at the MSDN briefing yesterday, pausing only out of concern that the guy who mans the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.computermanuals.co.uk&#34;&gt;Computer Manuals&lt;/a&gt; stand at these events might think that I’m stalking him (or fancy him!). Having determined that I could hand over my Barclaycard whilst flashing my wedding ring, I brought my current reading list up to three:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.co.uk/exec/obidos/ASIN/078214361X&#34;&gt;Developer to Designer: GUI Design for the Busy Developer&lt;/a&gt; – this was a wedding present from my mother-in-law and is proving to be an interesting, easy-going read so far. My competencies lie in the middle tier and database, and although I’m technically capable of making GUIs, I prefer to leave the design up to others. It’s inevitable though that most coders end up doing some design, and this book is, er, designed (sorry) to help with that process. The early section of the book concentrates on each UI element in turn, whilst the later part of the book looks at putting it all together, and has particular focus on the web – layout design patterns and interaction patterns. It’s a good read, making a nice contrast from the heavier books, and I’m pleased to learn that I’m not alone in hating Outlook’s labyrinthine Tools-&amp;gt;Options dialog!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Software Development Books</title>
      <link>https://bloghugo.iannelson.uk/software-development-books/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jun 2005 20:06:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bloghugo.iannelson.uk/software-development-books/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Elizabeth Keogh has been blogging her &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.livejournal.com/users/sirenian/19432.html&#34;&gt;advice for software-developer apprentices&lt;/a&gt;, and recommends buying and reading a selection of good software development books. I think this is sound advice – personally I felt that my career and abilities starting taking off when I stopped reading tech-specific Wrox tomes that were obsolete within six months of publication and started buying timeless Addison-Wesley hardbacks. Why so many newbie coders insist on rediscovering solutions to well-known problems instead of leveraging the knowledge of our programming forebears is beyond me, but most of us have behaved in this way at some point. Give yourself a leg-up and read some decent software design books.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ideal World / Real World</title>
      <link>https://bloghugo.iannelson.uk/ideal-world-real-world/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2004 09:09:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bloghugo.iannelson.uk/ideal-world-real-world/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A major project I’ve been working on for the last ten months has just gone live, giving me some time recently to take stock, do a bit of R&amp;amp;D, and catch up on some reading. I’ve been reflecting on how to approach things better in the future, and to this end, I’ve just finished two very different books about the software development process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;O’Reilly’s &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.co.uk/exec/obidos/ASIN/0596004850&#34;&gt;Extreme Programming Pocket Guide&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; is a handy little summary of the approach (only 81 pages), depicting a near-utopian development shop where everyone is happy, and projects come in under budget and on time. It got me quite fired up, actually, and some of the concepts described are interesting. But deep down, I just know this would never happen in the real world—too much politics, too many personalities at play in the workplace, in my humble opinion.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
