<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Wordle on Ian Nelson</title>
    <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/tags/wordle/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Wordle on Ian Nelson</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.146.6</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 10 May 2025 18:01:53 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://blog.iannelson.uk/tags/wordle/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Who Reigns Supreme? Parsing Our WhatsApp Chat for Wordle Glory</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/who-reigns-supreme-parsing-our-whatsapp-chat-for-wordle-glory/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 15:42:39 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/who-reigns-supreme-parsing-our-whatsapp-chat-for-wordle-glory/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Back in 2022, in a bid to outwit my mother in our daily Wordle battles, I wrote some C# code to explore optimal starting guesses. &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.iannelson.uk/the-best-wordle-starter-words/&#34;&gt;You can read about that experiment here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fast forward two years, and my Wordle addiction is alive and well. The daily challenge remains as compelling as ever, but it’s the family WhatsApp group – where scores are shared, victories boasted, and failures commiserated – that adds an extra layer of fun.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Back in 2022, in a bid to outwit my mother in our daily Wordle battles, I wrote some C# code to explore optimal starting guesses. <a href="https://blog.iannelson.uk/the-best-wordle-starter-words/">You can read about that experiment here</a>.</p>
<p>Fast forward two years, and my Wordle addiction is alive and well. The daily challenge remains as compelling as ever, but it’s the family WhatsApp group – where scores are shared, victories boasted, and failures commiserated – that adds an extra layer of fun.</p>
<p>As 2024 winds down, I decided to dust off my coding skills and whip up a quick C# console application. The goal? To parse an export of our WhatsApp chat, gather all the shared Wordle scores, and find out if my strategies have paid off this year. Spoiler alert: they haven’t.</p>
<p>If you’ve got a similar Wordle-centric group chat with family or friends and fancy crowning your own Wordle Champion of the Year, the source code is available on GitHub: <a href="https://github.com/ianfnelson/WordleParser">WordleParser</a>.</p>
<h2 id="how-it-works">How It Works</h2>
<p>The application takes a single argument: the path to an exported chat text file. It parses the file using a <a href="https://github.com/ianfnelson/WordleParser/blob/main/WordleParser/WordleParser.cs#L46">regular expression</a> to extract anything resembling a Wordle score. <a href="https://github.com/ianfnelson/WordleParser/blob/main/WordleParser/WordleParser.cs#L27">Duplicate scores are weeded out</a>, and the <a href="https://github.com/ianfnelson/WordleParser/blob/main/WordleParser/WordleParser.cs#L32">average family score for each calendar day is logged</a>. For those unfortunate days when a puzzle remains unsolved, the application <a href="https://github.com/ianfnelson/WordleParser/blob/main/WordleParser/WordleParser.cs#L59">assigns a ‘seven’</a> to reflect the failure.</p>
<p>The app then aggregates scores into calendar <a href="https://github.com/ianfnelson/WordleParser/blob/main/WordleParser/WordleParser.cs#L17">months</a> and <a href="https://github.com/ianfnelson/WordleParser/blob/main/WordleParser/WordleParser.cs#L11">years</a>, <a href="https://github.com/ianfnelson/WordleParser/blob/main/WordleParser/WordleParser.cs#L76">calculating each family member’s stats for the chosen date range</a>. Participants are ranked based on their mean difference from the average family score per day.</p>
<p>For example, if three family members scored a 4, but one managed a dazzling 2, the day’s average would be 3.5. The three “fours” would each have a daily difference of +0.5, while the lucky “two” would boast a difference of -1.5.</p>
<h2 id="the-results">The Results</h2>
<p>So, who triumphed in the Nelson family Wordle-off this year? Did my painstaking analysis from 2022 finally give me the edge?</p>
<p>Reader, it did not.</p>
<p>Despite my best efforts, I only just managed to sneak into second place. Predictably, my mother reigned supreme, crushing us all with an average score of <strong>4.055</strong> and a mean difference from the family average of <strong>-0.128</strong>. This consistency made her our undisputed <strong>Wordle Family Champion of 2024</strong>.</p>
<p><img alt="Nelson Family Wordle Champion 2024" loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2024/12/7DD41AB4-B664-4276-B1A1-3E9EA0F0DFB7-1.jpeg"></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Best Wordle Starter Words</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/the-best-wordle-starter-words/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Jan 2022 19:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/the-best-wordle-starter-words/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Like (it would seem) most of the rest of humanity, the start of my 2022 has been immeasurably enhanced by starting each day playing &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.powerlanguage.co.uk/&#34;&gt;Josh Wardle’s&lt;/a&gt; charming word game &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.powerlanguage.co.uk/wordle/&#34;&gt;Wordle&lt;/a&gt;. Which got me wondering – what are the best starter words to play in the opening lines at Wordle? I have been habitually using “&lt;strong&gt;ADIEU&lt;/strong&gt;” as my starter word, reasoning that it contains a large number of vowels. But is &lt;strong&gt;D&lt;/strong&gt; a particularly common consonant? And should I be trying to get &lt;strong&gt;O&lt;/strong&gt; in there rather than the less frequently used &lt;strong&gt;U&lt;/strong&gt;? I decided to do some computer-aided analysis to find the answer.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Like (it would seem) most of the rest of humanity, the start of my 2022 has been immeasurably enhanced by starting each day playing <a href="https://www.powerlanguage.co.uk/">Josh Wardle’s</a> charming word game <a href="https://www.powerlanguage.co.uk/wordle/">Wordle</a>. Which got me wondering – what are the best starter words to play in the opening lines at Wordle? I have been habitually using “<strong>ADIEU</strong>” as my starter word, reasoning that it contains a large number of vowels. But is <strong>D</strong> a particularly common consonant? And should I be trying to get <strong>O</strong> in there rather than the less frequently used <strong>U</strong>? I decided to do some computer-aided analysis to find the answer.</p>
<p><em><strong>SPOILER WARNING</strong> – this blog post contains information that may lead you to play more optimal Wordle starter words than you otherwise would have done if left to your own imagination. If you consider that this may take the fun out of an enjoyable daily practice, then I suggest that you stop reading. Now.</em></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2023/08/photo-1512799906445-d591d53082c0cropentropyampcstinysrgbampfitmaxampfmjpgampixidMnwxMTc3M3wwfDF8c2VhcmNofDR8fGNsb3NlZCUyMGV5ZXN8ZW58MHx8fHwxNjQyNTM4MzU2ampixlibrb-1.2.jpg">
Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@ryoji__iwata?utm_source=ghost&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=api-credit">Ryoji Iwata</a> / <a href="https://unsplash.com/?utm_source=ghost&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=api-credit">Unsplash</a></p>
<h2 id="definition">Definition</h2>
<p>Still here? OK, first a definition. What do I consider to be a good Wordle starter word? What makes one starter word better than another?</p>
<p>I assert that the best Wordle starter words are those which are expected to result in the highest number of yellow (right letter, wrong spot) or green (right letter, right spot) tiles. Let’s call this E(Y|G).  As a tie-breaker, where two words have the same value of E(Y|G), I consider the better word to be the one which is expected to result in the highest number of green tiles – let’s call this E(G).</p>
<p>I’ve seen alternative approaches posted on Twitter that rank guesses in different ways, such as one which was based on how many possible answers from the Wordle corpus are excluded by guessing them. But my brain doesn’t work that way round – I don’t have the full list of Wordle words in my head to sieve through, and instead seek the positive reinforcement of yellow and green tiles to use as the basis for my later guesses.</p>
<h2 id="assumption">Assumption</h2>
<p>There are 12,972 valid words in the Wordle dictionary. For the purposes of this analysis, I’m going to assume that they all have an equal likelihood of being the Wordle answer on any given day. Clearly this is not true. I’ve only been playing Wordle for a couple of weeks but it’s immediately apparent that the winning words tend to be those in common everyday use. I doubt that the game would have its current levels of popularity were this not the case. My nine year old son loves playing Wordle every day, and this shared common bond is one of the things that makes Wordle so fun. There was quite some brouhaha on Twitter when the answer to Wordle 207 was the US English spelling of “<strong>FAVOR</strong>“, I can only imagine what an uproar there would be if the answer was ever something truly random like “<strong>QAJAQ</strong>“, “<strong>XYLYL</strong>” or “<strong>HYPHY</strong>“. But I digress. Whatever aspects of curation are taking place to select the daily Wordle, be it automated or human, I’m going to ignore it and assume that the Wordle is chosen randomly from the list of valid Wordle words.</p>
<h2 id="the-top-10-best-wordle-starter-words">The Top 10 Best Wordle Starter Words</h2>
<p>This is your last chance to look away. Having iterated through all 168,272,784 pairs of guessed word and answer, here are the ten best Wordle starter words</p>
<table>
  <thead>
      <tr>
          <th>Rank</th>
          <th>Word</th>
          <th>E(Y|G)</th>
          <th>E(G)</th>
      </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
      <tr>
          <td>1.</td>
          <td>AEROS</td>
          <td>1.91111</td>
          <td>0.63360</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>2.</td>
          <td>SOARE</td>
          <td>1.91111</td>
          <td>0.55026</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>3.</td>
          <td>AROSE</td>
          <td>1.91111</td>
          <td>0.36294</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>4.</td>
          <td>REAIS</td>
          <td>1.88629</td>
          <td>0.64215</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>5.</td>
          <td>RAISE</td>
          <td>1.88629</td>
          <td>0.46099</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>6.</td>
          <td>SERAI</td>
          <td>1.88629</td>
          <td>0.44288</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>7.</td>
          <td>ARISE</td>
          <td>1.88629</td>
          <td>0.36741</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>8.</td>
          <td>AESIR</td>
          <td>1.88629</td>
          <td>0.34312</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>9.</td>
          <td>ALOES</td>
          <td>1.84983</td>
          <td>0.67175</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>10.</td>
          <td>LARES</td>
          <td>1.84968</td>
          <td>0.79579</td>
      </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>
<p>Therefore, if you want to turn over the highest number of yellow and green tiles on your first Wordle play, and favour seeing the green tiles, then “<strong>AEROS</strong>” is your best bet. By comparison my previous favourite of “<strong>ADIEU</strong>” has an E(Y|G) of 1.49229 and E(G) of 0.32886.</p>
<h2 id="the-best-words-to-play-second">The Best Words To Play Second</h2>
<p>But what comes next? What words are best to play on the second line? It depends how you like to play the game. If you’re like my mother, or have “hard mode” turned on, then your second and subsequent guesses will be influenced by the hints received in response to your first guess.</p>
<p>On the other hand, if you’re like me, at this early stage you’ll want to continue exploring the full breadth of the alphabet to increase the probability of identifying additional letters in the answer. For example I have generally been following up my “<strong>ADIEU</strong>” starter with “<strong>GHOST</strong>” to finish off the vowels and include <strong>T</strong> and <strong>S</strong> in the mix.</p>
<p>With this in mind, I extended my analysis to determine the combined E(Y|G) and E(G) values for pairs of valid Wordle words. All of the best results came from pairing together words that cover 10 distinct letters. Perhaps that seems intuitive, but it wasn’t a foregone conclusion. There are many guesses containing repeated letters which have excellent prospects, especially those with pairs of <strong>E</strong> or <strong>S</strong>. “<strong>EASER</strong>” is the best of these with an E(Y|G) of 1.68039, and pleasingly even “<strong>ARSES</strong>” weighs in with an E(Y|G) of 1.66489.</p>
<p>Here are the ten best combinations of ten letters to cover with the first two guesses, with an example of two valid Wordle words covering those letters:</p>
<table>
  <thead>
      <tr>
          <th>Rank</th>
          <th>Letters</th>
          <th>Example Words</th>
          <th>Combined E(Y|G)</th>
      </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
      <tr>
          <td>1.</td>
          <td>AEILNORSTU</td>
          <td>AEROS, UNLIT</td>
          <td>3.06429</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>2.</td>
          <td>ADEILNORTS</td>
          <td>ADITS, ENROL</td>
          <td>3.05365</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>3.</td>
          <td>AEILONRSTY</td>
          <td>AEROS, LINTY</td>
          <td>3.03307</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>4.</td>
          <td>ADEILORSTU</td>
          <td>ADIEU, ROTLS</td>
          <td>3.02660</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>5.</td>
          <td>ACEILNORST</td>
          <td>ACNES, LIROT</td>
          <td>3.02451</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>6.</td>
          <td>AEILONPRST</td>
          <td>AIRTS, PELON</td>
          <td>3.02182</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>7.</td>
          <td>AIMERSTOLN</td>
          <td>AIMER, STOLN</td>
          <td>3.02051</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>8.</td>
          <td>AEHILNORST</td>
          <td>AEONS, THIRL</td>
          <td>3.00817</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>9.</td>
          <td>ADEILNORSU</td>
          <td>ADORN, ILEUS</td>
          <td>3.00763</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>10.</td>
          <td>AEILORSTUY</td>
          <td>AIERY, LOTUS</td>
          <td>3.00601</td>
      </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>
<p>By comparison, my previous favoured pairing of “<strong>ADIEU</strong>” and “<strong>GHOST</strong>” has an E(Y|G) of 2.7358. Switching to a combination of words that covers the letters AEILNORSTU such as “<strong>AEROS</strong>” and “<strong>UNLIT</strong>” should boost my expected number of hints from my first two guesses by 12%!</p>
<h2 id="the-best-of-the-best">The Best of the Best</h2>
<p>But which two words to pick? There are no fewer than <strong>300 combinations</strong> of valid Wordle words which cover those best ten letters, all having a combined E(Y|G) of 3.06429. Again, I decided to use E(G) as a tie-breaker, which leads to the following ranking of pairs of starting words:</p>
<table>
  <thead>
      <tr>
          <th>Rank</th>
          <th>Word 1</th>
          <th>Word 1 E(Y|G)</th>
          <th>Word 2</th>
          <th>Word 2 E(Y|G)</th>
          <th>Combined E(G)</th>
      </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
      <tr>
          <td>1.</td>
          <td>TAILS</td>
          <td>1.61903</td>
          <td>ROUEN</td>
          <td>1.44527</td>
          <td>1.16454</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>2.</td>
          <td>TARNS</td>
          <td>1.61849</td>
          <td>LOUIE</td>
          <td>1.44581</td>
          <td>1.13818</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>3.</td>
          <td>LORES</td>
          <td>1.74029</td>
          <td>TUINA</td>
          <td>1.32401</td>
          <td>1.13146</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>4.</td>
          <td>RAILE</td>
          <td>1.66875</td>
          <td>TOUNS</td>
          <td>1.39554</td>
          <td>1.39554</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>5.</td>
          <td>TAINS</td>
          <td>1.59382</td>
          <td>ROULE</td>
          <td>1.47047</td>
          <td>1.12243</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>6.</td>
          <td>RAUNS</td>
          <td>1.57246</td>
          <td>TOILE</td>
          <td>1.49183</td>
          <td>1.12239</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>7.</td>
          <td>RAILE</td>
          <td>1.66875</td>
          <td>TONUS</td>
          <td>1.39554</td>
          <td>1.11549</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>8.</td>
          <td>TOLES</td>
          <td>1.67276</td>
          <td>NAIRU</td>
          <td>1.39153</td>
          <td>1.11543</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>9.</td>
          <td>TAINS</td>
          <td>1.59382</td>
          <td>LOURE</td>
          <td>1.47047</td>
          <td>1.11443</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>10.</td>
          <td>RANTS</td>
          <td>1.61849</td>
          <td>LOUIE</td>
          <td>1.44581</td>
          <td>1.11417</td>
      </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="adieu-adieu">Adieu, “ADIEU”</h2>
<p>So there you have it. Having crunched the numbers, my new pair of Wordle starter words from tomorrow morning shall be “<strong>TAILS</strong>” followed by “<strong>ROUEN</strong>“. <a href="https://twitter.com/ianfnelson">Follow me on Twitter</a> to see how it works out for me. I have a suspicion that despite this analysis, my mother will still reach the answer in fewer guesses than me more often than not!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
