<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Games on Ian Nelson</title>
    <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/tags/games/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Games on Ian Nelson</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.146.6</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 10 May 2025 18:01:53 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://blog.iannelson.uk/tags/games/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Who Reigns Supreme? Parsing Our WhatsApp Chat for Wordle Glory</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/who-reigns-supreme-parsing-our-whatsapp-chat-for-wordle-glory/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 15:42:39 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/who-reigns-supreme-parsing-our-whatsapp-chat-for-wordle-glory/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Back in 2022, in a bid to outwit my mother in our daily Wordle battles, I wrote some C# code to explore optimal starting guesses. &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.iannelson.uk/the-best-wordle-starter-words/&#34;&gt;You can read about that experiment here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fast forward two years, and my Wordle addiction is alive and well. The daily challenge remains as compelling as ever, but it’s the family WhatsApp group – where scores are shared, victories boasted, and failures commiserated – that adds an extra layer of fun.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Back in 2022, in a bid to outwit my mother in our daily Wordle battles, I wrote some C# code to explore optimal starting guesses. <a href="https://blog.iannelson.uk/the-best-wordle-starter-words/">You can read about that experiment here</a>.</p>
<p>Fast forward two years, and my Wordle addiction is alive and well. The daily challenge remains as compelling as ever, but it’s the family WhatsApp group – where scores are shared, victories boasted, and failures commiserated – that adds an extra layer of fun.</p>
<p>As 2024 winds down, I decided to dust off my coding skills and whip up a quick C# console application. The goal? To parse an export of our WhatsApp chat, gather all the shared Wordle scores, and find out if my strategies have paid off this year. Spoiler alert: they haven’t.</p>
<p>If you’ve got a similar Wordle-centric group chat with family or friends and fancy crowning your own Wordle Champion of the Year, the source code is available on GitHub: <a href="https://github.com/ianfnelson/WordleParser">WordleParser</a>.</p>
<h2 id="how-it-works">How It Works</h2>
<p>The application takes a single argument: the path to an exported chat text file. It parses the file using a <a href="https://github.com/ianfnelson/WordleParser/blob/main/WordleParser/WordleParser.cs#L46">regular expression</a> to extract anything resembling a Wordle score. <a href="https://github.com/ianfnelson/WordleParser/blob/main/WordleParser/WordleParser.cs#L27">Duplicate scores are weeded out</a>, and the <a href="https://github.com/ianfnelson/WordleParser/blob/main/WordleParser/WordleParser.cs#L32">average family score for each calendar day is logged</a>. For those unfortunate days when a puzzle remains unsolved, the application <a href="https://github.com/ianfnelson/WordleParser/blob/main/WordleParser/WordleParser.cs#L59">assigns a ‘seven’</a> to reflect the failure.</p>
<p>The app then aggregates scores into calendar <a href="https://github.com/ianfnelson/WordleParser/blob/main/WordleParser/WordleParser.cs#L17">months</a> and <a href="https://github.com/ianfnelson/WordleParser/blob/main/WordleParser/WordleParser.cs#L11">years</a>, <a href="https://github.com/ianfnelson/WordleParser/blob/main/WordleParser/WordleParser.cs#L76">calculating each family member’s stats for the chosen date range</a>. Participants are ranked based on their mean difference from the average family score per day.</p>
<p>For example, if three family members scored a 4, but one managed a dazzling 2, the day’s average would be 3.5. The three “fours” would each have a daily difference of +0.5, while the lucky “two” would boast a difference of -1.5.</p>
<h2 id="the-results">The Results</h2>
<p>So, who triumphed in the Nelson family Wordle-off this year? Did my painstaking analysis from 2022 finally give me the edge?</p>
<p>Reader, it did not.</p>
<p>Despite my best efforts, I only just managed to sneak into second place. Predictably, my mother reigned supreme, crushing us all with an average score of <strong>4.055</strong> and a mean difference from the family average of <strong>-0.128</strong>. This consistency made her our undisputed <strong>Wordle Family Champion of 2024</strong>.</p>
<p><img alt="Nelson Family Wordle Champion 2024" loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2024/12/7DD41AB4-B664-4276-B1A1-3E9EA0F0DFB7-1.jpeg"></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Best Wordle Starter Words</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/the-best-wordle-starter-words/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Jan 2022 19:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/the-best-wordle-starter-words/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Like (it would seem) most of the rest of humanity, the start of my 2022 has been immeasurably enhanced by starting each day playing &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.powerlanguage.co.uk/&#34;&gt;Josh Wardle’s&lt;/a&gt; charming word game &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.powerlanguage.co.uk/wordle/&#34;&gt;Wordle&lt;/a&gt;. Which got me wondering – what are the best starter words to play in the opening lines at Wordle? I have been habitually using “&lt;strong&gt;ADIEU&lt;/strong&gt;” as my starter word, reasoning that it contains a large number of vowels. But is &lt;strong&gt;D&lt;/strong&gt; a particularly common consonant? And should I be trying to get &lt;strong&gt;O&lt;/strong&gt; in there rather than the less frequently used &lt;strong&gt;U&lt;/strong&gt;? I decided to do some computer-aided analysis to find the answer.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Like (it would seem) most of the rest of humanity, the start of my 2022 has been immeasurably enhanced by starting each day playing <a href="https://www.powerlanguage.co.uk/">Josh Wardle’s</a> charming word game <a href="https://www.powerlanguage.co.uk/wordle/">Wordle</a>. Which got me wondering – what are the best starter words to play in the opening lines at Wordle? I have been habitually using “<strong>ADIEU</strong>” as my starter word, reasoning that it contains a large number of vowels. But is <strong>D</strong> a particularly common consonant? And should I be trying to get <strong>O</strong> in there rather than the less frequently used <strong>U</strong>? I decided to do some computer-aided analysis to find the answer.</p>
<p><em><strong>SPOILER WARNING</strong> – this blog post contains information that may lead you to play more optimal Wordle starter words than you otherwise would have done if left to your own imagination. If you consider that this may take the fun out of an enjoyable daily practice, then I suggest that you stop reading. Now.</em></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2023/08/photo-1512799906445-d591d53082c0cropentropyampcstinysrgbampfitmaxampfmjpgampixidMnwxMTc3M3wwfDF8c2VhcmNofDR8fGNsb3NlZCUyMGV5ZXN8ZW58MHx8fHwxNjQyNTM4MzU2ampixlibrb-1.2.jpg">
Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@ryoji__iwata?utm_source=ghost&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=api-credit">Ryoji Iwata</a> / <a href="https://unsplash.com/?utm_source=ghost&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=api-credit">Unsplash</a></p>
<h2 id="definition">Definition</h2>
<p>Still here? OK, first a definition. What do I consider to be a good Wordle starter word? What makes one starter word better than another?</p>
<p>I assert that the best Wordle starter words are those which are expected to result in the highest number of yellow (right letter, wrong spot) or green (right letter, right spot) tiles. Let’s call this E(Y|G).  As a tie-breaker, where two words have the same value of E(Y|G), I consider the better word to be the one which is expected to result in the highest number of green tiles – let’s call this E(G).</p>
<p>I’ve seen alternative approaches posted on Twitter that rank guesses in different ways, such as one which was based on how many possible answers from the Wordle corpus are excluded by guessing them. But my brain doesn’t work that way round – I don’t have the full list of Wordle words in my head to sieve through, and instead seek the positive reinforcement of yellow and green tiles to use as the basis for my later guesses.</p>
<h2 id="assumption">Assumption</h2>
<p>There are 12,972 valid words in the Wordle dictionary. For the purposes of this analysis, I’m going to assume that they all have an equal likelihood of being the Wordle answer on any given day. Clearly this is not true. I’ve only been playing Wordle for a couple of weeks but it’s immediately apparent that the winning words tend to be those in common everyday use. I doubt that the game would have its current levels of popularity were this not the case. My nine year old son loves playing Wordle every day, and this shared common bond is one of the things that makes Wordle so fun. There was quite some brouhaha on Twitter when the answer to Wordle 207 was the US English spelling of “<strong>FAVOR</strong>“, I can only imagine what an uproar there would be if the answer was ever something truly random like “<strong>QAJAQ</strong>“, “<strong>XYLYL</strong>” or “<strong>HYPHY</strong>“. But I digress. Whatever aspects of curation are taking place to select the daily Wordle, be it automated or human, I’m going to ignore it and assume that the Wordle is chosen randomly from the list of valid Wordle words.</p>
<h2 id="the-top-10-best-wordle-starter-words">The Top 10 Best Wordle Starter Words</h2>
<p>This is your last chance to look away. Having iterated through all 168,272,784 pairs of guessed word and answer, here are the ten best Wordle starter words</p>
<table>
  <thead>
      <tr>
          <th>Rank</th>
          <th>Word</th>
          <th>E(Y|G)</th>
          <th>E(G)</th>
      </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
      <tr>
          <td>1.</td>
          <td>AEROS</td>
          <td>1.91111</td>
          <td>0.63360</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>2.</td>
          <td>SOARE</td>
          <td>1.91111</td>
          <td>0.55026</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>3.</td>
          <td>AROSE</td>
          <td>1.91111</td>
          <td>0.36294</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>4.</td>
          <td>REAIS</td>
          <td>1.88629</td>
          <td>0.64215</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>5.</td>
          <td>RAISE</td>
          <td>1.88629</td>
          <td>0.46099</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>6.</td>
          <td>SERAI</td>
          <td>1.88629</td>
          <td>0.44288</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>7.</td>
          <td>ARISE</td>
          <td>1.88629</td>
          <td>0.36741</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>8.</td>
          <td>AESIR</td>
          <td>1.88629</td>
          <td>0.34312</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>9.</td>
          <td>ALOES</td>
          <td>1.84983</td>
          <td>0.67175</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>10.</td>
          <td>LARES</td>
          <td>1.84968</td>
          <td>0.79579</td>
      </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>
<p>Therefore, if you want to turn over the highest number of yellow and green tiles on your first Wordle play, and favour seeing the green tiles, then “<strong>AEROS</strong>” is your best bet. By comparison my previous favourite of “<strong>ADIEU</strong>” has an E(Y|G) of 1.49229 and E(G) of 0.32886.</p>
<h2 id="the-best-words-to-play-second">The Best Words To Play Second</h2>
<p>But what comes next? What words are best to play on the second line? It depends how you like to play the game. If you’re like my mother, or have “hard mode” turned on, then your second and subsequent guesses will be influenced by the hints received in response to your first guess.</p>
<p>On the other hand, if you’re like me, at this early stage you’ll want to continue exploring the full breadth of the alphabet to increase the probability of identifying additional letters in the answer. For example I have generally been following up my “<strong>ADIEU</strong>” starter with “<strong>GHOST</strong>” to finish off the vowels and include <strong>T</strong> and <strong>S</strong> in the mix.</p>
<p>With this in mind, I extended my analysis to determine the combined E(Y|G) and E(G) values for pairs of valid Wordle words. All of the best results came from pairing together words that cover 10 distinct letters. Perhaps that seems intuitive, but it wasn’t a foregone conclusion. There are many guesses containing repeated letters which have excellent prospects, especially those with pairs of <strong>E</strong> or <strong>S</strong>. “<strong>EASER</strong>” is the best of these with an E(Y|G) of 1.68039, and pleasingly even “<strong>ARSES</strong>” weighs in with an E(Y|G) of 1.66489.</p>
<p>Here are the ten best combinations of ten letters to cover with the first two guesses, with an example of two valid Wordle words covering those letters:</p>
<table>
  <thead>
      <tr>
          <th>Rank</th>
          <th>Letters</th>
          <th>Example Words</th>
          <th>Combined E(Y|G)</th>
      </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
      <tr>
          <td>1.</td>
          <td>AEILNORSTU</td>
          <td>AEROS, UNLIT</td>
          <td>3.06429</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>2.</td>
          <td>ADEILNORTS</td>
          <td>ADITS, ENROL</td>
          <td>3.05365</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>3.</td>
          <td>AEILONRSTY</td>
          <td>AEROS, LINTY</td>
          <td>3.03307</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>4.</td>
          <td>ADEILORSTU</td>
          <td>ADIEU, ROTLS</td>
          <td>3.02660</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>5.</td>
          <td>ACEILNORST</td>
          <td>ACNES, LIROT</td>
          <td>3.02451</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>6.</td>
          <td>AEILONPRST</td>
          <td>AIRTS, PELON</td>
          <td>3.02182</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>7.</td>
          <td>AIMERSTOLN</td>
          <td>AIMER, STOLN</td>
          <td>3.02051</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>8.</td>
          <td>AEHILNORST</td>
          <td>AEONS, THIRL</td>
          <td>3.00817</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>9.</td>
          <td>ADEILNORSU</td>
          <td>ADORN, ILEUS</td>
          <td>3.00763</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>10.</td>
          <td>AEILORSTUY</td>
          <td>AIERY, LOTUS</td>
          <td>3.00601</td>
      </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>
<p>By comparison, my previous favoured pairing of “<strong>ADIEU</strong>” and “<strong>GHOST</strong>” has an E(Y|G) of 2.7358. Switching to a combination of words that covers the letters AEILNORSTU such as “<strong>AEROS</strong>” and “<strong>UNLIT</strong>” should boost my expected number of hints from my first two guesses by 12%!</p>
<h2 id="the-best-of-the-best">The Best of the Best</h2>
<p>But which two words to pick? There are no fewer than <strong>300 combinations</strong> of valid Wordle words which cover those best ten letters, all having a combined E(Y|G) of 3.06429. Again, I decided to use E(G) as a tie-breaker, which leads to the following ranking of pairs of starting words:</p>
<table>
  <thead>
      <tr>
          <th>Rank</th>
          <th>Word 1</th>
          <th>Word 1 E(Y|G)</th>
          <th>Word 2</th>
          <th>Word 2 E(Y|G)</th>
          <th>Combined E(G)</th>
      </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
      <tr>
          <td>1.</td>
          <td>TAILS</td>
          <td>1.61903</td>
          <td>ROUEN</td>
          <td>1.44527</td>
          <td>1.16454</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>2.</td>
          <td>TARNS</td>
          <td>1.61849</td>
          <td>LOUIE</td>
          <td>1.44581</td>
          <td>1.13818</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>3.</td>
          <td>LORES</td>
          <td>1.74029</td>
          <td>TUINA</td>
          <td>1.32401</td>
          <td>1.13146</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>4.</td>
          <td>RAILE</td>
          <td>1.66875</td>
          <td>TOUNS</td>
          <td>1.39554</td>
          <td>1.39554</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>5.</td>
          <td>TAINS</td>
          <td>1.59382</td>
          <td>ROULE</td>
          <td>1.47047</td>
          <td>1.12243</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>6.</td>
          <td>RAUNS</td>
          <td>1.57246</td>
          <td>TOILE</td>
          <td>1.49183</td>
          <td>1.12239</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>7.</td>
          <td>RAILE</td>
          <td>1.66875</td>
          <td>TONUS</td>
          <td>1.39554</td>
          <td>1.11549</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>8.</td>
          <td>TOLES</td>
          <td>1.67276</td>
          <td>NAIRU</td>
          <td>1.39153</td>
          <td>1.11543</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>9.</td>
          <td>TAINS</td>
          <td>1.59382</td>
          <td>LOURE</td>
          <td>1.47047</td>
          <td>1.11443</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>10.</td>
          <td>RANTS</td>
          <td>1.61849</td>
          <td>LOUIE</td>
          <td>1.44581</td>
          <td>1.11417</td>
      </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="adieu-adieu">Adieu, “ADIEU”</h2>
<p>So there you have it. Having crunched the numbers, my new pair of Wordle starter words from tomorrow morning shall be “<strong>TAILS</strong>” followed by “<strong>ROUEN</strong>“. <a href="https://twitter.com/ianfnelson">Follow me on Twitter</a> to see how it works out for me. I have a suspicion that despite this analysis, my mother will still reach the answer in fewer guesses than me more often than not!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Computer Games I Have Loved</title>
      <link>https://blog.iannelson.uk/computer-games-i-have-loved/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Aug 2005 21:08:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.iannelson.uk/computer-games-i-have-loved/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Isn’t it funny how one’s tastes change as maturity progresses?  I used to spend my summer holidays at the sea-side, playing in arcades and seeking the perfect milkshake (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.snackspot.org.uk/thread.php?story=0408101147daa&#34;&gt;lime&lt;/a&gt;); more recently I’ve been spending them in the highlands, playing on the hills and seeking the perfect dram (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.scotchwhisky.com/focus/lagavulin.htm&#34;&gt;lagavulin&lt;/a&gt;).Hmmm…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think I may have mentioned that the wife is away in the States for a while.At the start of this period of solitude, I panicked, wondering whatever I could do with myself, and came to the conclusion that it would be a good idea to buy a computer game to while away the hours.After all, I spent much of my formative years killing time on a variety of computer and console games, so why not rekindle that prior love affair?  So it was that I bought &lt;a href=&#34;http://thesims2.ea.com/&#34;&gt;The Sims 2&lt;/a&gt;, a truly excellent game, and had an enjoyable evening trying to motivate my wee Sims to improve their skills, better themselves, and generally enjoy life.All good harmless fun.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Isn’t it funny how one’s tastes change as maturity progresses?  I used to spend my summer holidays at the sea-side, playing in arcades and seeking the perfect milkshake (<a href="http://www.snackspot.org.uk/thread.php?story=0408101147daa">lime</a>); more recently I’ve been spending them in the highlands, playing on the hills and seeking the perfect dram (<a href="http://www.scotchwhisky.com/focus/lagavulin.htm">lagavulin</a>).Hmmm…</p>
<p>I think I may have mentioned that the wife is away in the States for a while.At the start of this period of solitude, I panicked, wondering whatever I could do with myself, and came to the conclusion that it would be a good idea to buy a computer game to while away the hours.After all, I spent much of my formative years killing time on a variety of computer and console games, so why not rekindle that prior love affair?  So it was that I bought <a href="http://thesims2.ea.com/">The Sims 2</a>, a truly excellent game, and had an enjoyable evening trying to motivate my wee Sims to improve their skills, better themselves, and generally enjoy life.All good harmless fun.</p>
<p>The following evening, though, I came to resume my game, and…  I just couldn’t be bothered.The whole concept seemed utterly pointless, a real waste of time.Why squander an evening encouraging AI sims to develop their skills and improve their house when, here in the real life, I had bookcases to build, books to read, music to enjoy, new DVDs to watch, a fantastic city to go out and enjoy, and skills to learn for my own career?  It struck me that many of the finely-honed computer game skills I had developed over the past thirtyish years were of absolutely no use outside the parameters of those particular games.</p>
<p>Since then, The Sims has sat on a shelf, and I’ve achieved loads over the past few weeks – Jocelyn is soon returning to find the house at the tidiest it’s been in years.I told my mum all this (as you do).She said I’m growing up.About bloody time.</p>
<p>But still, those earlier computer games <em>did</em> play a big part during the first three decades of my life, so, in way of tribute, here’s a quick rundown of the dozen games responsible for my most wasted hours:</p>
<h2 id="grandstand-adman-2000">Grandstand Adman 2000</h2>
<p>The first “console” I ever owned, this featured four (four!) different games – football, squash, tennis and practice.Not only that, but it boasted configurable options for speed, angle, and bat-size!  You simply cannot appreciate how many hours I frittered away bouncing that square block against a wall until I encountered 15 “faults” – at which point I would press the reset button and repeat the process.If I’m being charitable to my younger self, then I could suggest that this game at least helped me develop hand-eye coordination, and stopped me mithering my parents for a while.
“Real Sports Action”, says the box.Well, only if football ever consisted of four vertical bars deflecting a square ball moving with constant speed.Also – “Realistic Sound Effects”.It beeped!  That was it!  But, y’know, it was all we had, so…</p>
<p><img alt="Grandstand Adman 2000" loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2023/08/grandstand-adman-2000_35626038_o.jpg">
<em>Photo by <a href="http://computermuseum.50megs.com/collectionpong.htm">Erik Klooster</a></em></p>
<h2 id="grandstand-bmx-flyer">Grandstand BMX Flyer</h2>
<p>Oh, now this handheld LCD console was (is?) a most favourite game of mine.I can still hum the tune, and I still know that my highest-ever score was 14,070.Brilliant fun – highly addictive and an appealing concept for a seven year-old lad (“avoid the crows!”  “jump for the girl in the balloon!”  “kick dirt in the baddy’s face!”).</p>
<p><img alt="Grandstand BMX Flyer" loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2023/08/grandstand-bmxflyerboxfrontjpg_35626067_o.jpg">
<em>Photo by <a href="http://www.handheldmuseum.com/Grandstand/BMXF.htm">Handheld Museum</a></em></p>
<h2 id="starter-chess-commodore-16">Starter Chess (Commodore 16)</h2>
<p>I was always a Commodore kid.Speccies and Amstrads, though much more popular with the gamers at school, just didn’t appeal to me.I mean, seriously, how could you write computer programs for hours on end using a rubber keyboard?!  Oh, sure, they were much better for games, if you liked that kind of thing.But the C16 came with games too, like.. Starter Chess!<br>
OK, who am I kidding?  Starter Chess was, in all respects, an exercise in patience and sitting around watching a pitifully underpowered computer fail to do very much for what seemed like an interminably long time.First you had to get the game to load, from cassette tape, which always took the best part of twenty minutes.Then, after every chess move played by oneself, the Commodore spent a good five minutes plotting its next move (which it announced with a loud beep).Not very exciting.On the plus side, the computer player wasn’t particularly strong, so it was actually quite conceivable to win, even as a youngster.</p>
<h2 id="fruit-machine-simulator-commodore-16">Fruit Machine Simulator (Commodore 16)</h2>
<p>I’m beginning to think I must’ve been a bit of a masochist as a child, because I absolutely loved this single-screen game which attempted to “simulate” a pretty simplistic fruit machine.Press a key to enter some coins.Press another key to pull the lever.Maybe, just maybe, you then have the possibility of pressing further keys to “hold” or “nudge” – oh, the excitement was palpable.It sounds really dull now, but I loved it at the time.I remember trying to figure out the probability with which the various game events occurred – were they truly random, or were they influenced by the user’s actions?  What was the average length of a game, before you either went bust or accumulated the target winnings?  A future university career in mathematics was  already evident..</p>
<h2 id="kickstart-commodore-16">Kickstart (Commodore 16)</h2>
<p>Of all the games I had for the C16, Kickstart was the only one that I remember as being truly playable, and remotely “fast”.I was impressed at the time that such a game could run on a machine with such little RAM.This was a motorbike game (as in the old TV show, Kickstart, which I also loved), and, like BMX Flyer years early, basically involved making the bike jump at the appropriate time – balloons were involved again too, and there was an irritating-to-adults soundtrack.Quality.</p>
<h2 id="lemmings-amiga">Lemmings (Amiga)</h2>
<p>The Christmas that brought me an Amiga 500 played a big part in sealing my future career direction.For the first time, I was able to tinker with a real operating system (with GUI), more powerful programming languages, hard disks, multitasking applications, etc.But that Christmas day itself was mostly spent playing Lemmings, which should need no introduction as it’s one of the most popular games of its time, and has been ported across to many platforms, including DHTML!</p>
<p><img alt="Lemmings" loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2023/08/amiga_lemmingspng_35626091_o.png"></p>
<h2 id="stunt-car-racer-amiga">Stunt Car Racer (Amiga)</h2>
<p>Stunt Car Racer was initially a very hard game.But, persevere and you would discover the “knack” to each of the eight challenging courses.So, persevere I did, and eventually reached the top of division one!  It seemed like such an achievement at the time, but it’s not exactly something I can put on my CV in 2005, is it?</p>
<p><img alt="Stunt Car Racer" loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2023/08/stunt_car_racer_06_35626365_o.gif"></p>
<h2 id="gods-amiga">Gods (Amiga)</h2>
<p>Gods was a platform game by the Bitmap Brothers, with a kicking introductory theme tune, and the game was pretty cool too. Lots of different weapons, puzzles, and backgrounds ensured a game which remained enjoyable as you progressed through the levels. Also a good variety of monsters, who boasted a much-hyped AI, in stark contrast to the usual sprites of the day who tended to attack by following predictable (circular) routes. Brilliant.</p>
<p><img alt="Gods" loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2023/08/gods_35626019_o.png"></p>
<h2 id="civilization-series-amiga--pc">Civilization series (Amiga / PC)</h2>
<p>Of all the games mentioned, I have spent the most time playing the various incarnations of Civilization on the Amiga and latterly on the PC.Indeed, Civ 3 with the Play The World expansion gets my vote for greatest computer game of all time.It’s such a brilliant concept – start with a few stone-age settlers in 4000BC and nurture them through 6000 years of growth, discovery, technological development, war and peace until they either achieve world domination or make the leap to Alpha Centauri (OK, I hear there are some other victory conditions, but these are the only two I’ve ever really found interesting).The level of attachment you can feel to your civilization after playing this game for an entire weekend is really quite disturbing.Addictive to the extreme, and often responsible for my eyes feeling very sore indeed…</p>
<p><img alt="Civilization 3" loading="lazy" src="https://blogstouks01.z33.web.core.windows.net/2023/08/civ3jpg_35626007_o.jpg"></p>
<h2 id="worms-pc">Worms (PC)</h2>
<p>If it wasn’t for Worms, I suspect myself and some of the other Grovey Roaders would have achieved 2:1 degrees instead of the 2:2s we all took from Nottingham uni.But, alas, Worms was just such good fun, and so sociable… what better way to spend evenings in our final year than commanding crack squads of four worms each to kick each other’s butts to entertaining effect?  Well, except for going to The Irish, of course.</p>
<h2 id="quake-pc">Quake (PC)</h2>
<p>I missed the whole Doom thing as I didn’t get a PC until leaving uni in 1997. Quake was therefore the first FPS I ever played, and thus swiftly passed another summer of my youth.</p>
<h2 id="gran-turismo-2-playstation">Gran Turismo 2 (Playstation)</h2>
<p>GT2 was the reason I bought a Playstation, and it was the only PSX game I played for any length of time.At the time I had a Ford Puma, so within the game I made a point of buying the exact same model in the same colour.How sad is that?  As with my recent Sims 2 epiphany, I was eventually struck by the thought “why am I doing this within the virtual confines of a computer game when I could be doing it out in the real world?”.I didn’t explain this line of reasoning to the magistrate though, and the six points should come off my driving licence in a few year’s time… 😉</p>
<p>There you have it, the dirty dozen responsible for wasting much of the best years of my life.Who knows, without those distractions, maybe by now I would otherwise be a Nobel laureate, or rich and famous…  or maybe I would have no hand-eye coordination, be unable to use a mouse, and not have the programming talents that now put food on our table.Hmmm…</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
